ANNOUNCER: The following program
is brought to you by Caltech.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Welcome back.
Last time, we introduced support
vector machines.
And if you think of linear models as
economy cars, which is what we said
when we introduced them, you can think
of support vector machines as the
luxury line of those cars.
And indeed, they are nothing but
a linear model in the simplest form
except that they actually are a little
bit more keen on the performance.
And the key to the performance was the
idea of the margin-- is that if the
data is linearly separable, there
is more than one line that can
separate the data.
And if you take the line that has the
biggest margin, furthest away from the
closest point, then you
have an advantage.
It's both an intuitive advantage and
an advantage that can be theoretically
established, which we did through
the idea of the growth
function in this case.
And after we determined that it's a good
idea to maximize the margin, we
set out to do that.
And after a chain of mathematics, we
ended up with a Lagrangian that
we're going to maximize.
And the Lagrangian has very
interesting properties.
It's quadratic, so it's
a simple function.
And the constraints are inequality
constraints, very simple inequality
constraints in this case, and
one equality constraint.
And we're not going to actually
do the solving ourselves.
We're going to pass the problem on to
a package of quadratic programming.
And then, we will wait for quadratic
programming to give us back
the values of alphas.
Now, quadratic programming will have
problems with solving this if the
number of examples is bigger.
So once you get to thousands,
its becomes an issue.
And then, there are all kinds of
heuristics to deal with that case.
And in general, quadratic programming
sometimes needs babysitting, tweaking,
limiting range, and whatnot.
But at least someone else wrote it, and
we only have to do these things in
order to get the solution, rather
than to write this from scratch.
So it's not a bad deal for us.
And once we get the alphas back, there
is a very interesting interpretation
that happens.
You look at the alphas, the
Lagrange multipliers.
And some of them will
be greater than 0.
And most of them will be 0,
should be identically 0.
In reality, because of the rounding
error, we might get
them very, very small.
And you set them manually to 0.
But the guys that happen to be bigger
than 0 are special, and they are
called the support vectors.
And whether you're working in the X space,
or took the X space and moved to
a Z space and moved back here, the
support vectors are the ones that
achieve the margin.
They are sitting exactly at
the critical point here.
And they're used to define the plane.
And the most important aspect about them
is the fact that you can predict
a bound on the out-of-sample error, based
on the number of support vectors
that you get.
And it is the normal form of dividing
the complexity, in terms of the number
of parameters, in this case the non-zero
alphas or the number of
support vectors that corresponds to it,
divided by more or less the number
of examples.
We have seen that before.
But the key issue here is something
really worth noting.
The right-hand side without the expected
value-- the expected value just
tells us that we average this over
a number of cases for this to be true.
We are dividing the number of support
vectors by N. The number of support
vectors is an in-sample quantity.
You do all of this.
You get the alphas back.
And you can tell what the number of
support vectors are, in sample.
So we are able to check on the
out-of-sample error, using
an in-sample quantity.
And we know, by the previous experience,
that this is a biggie.
Because now, not only are we going to
check on the in-sample error, we're
also going to check on the
out-of-sample error using
a quantity we can measure.
Now, we applied support vectors only
to linearly separable data, at
least in the previous lecture.
In this lecture, we will
generalize that.
And in order to deal with cases where
the data is not linearly separable in
the X space, what we did is we used
nonlinear transform, as we did before
with linear models.
And a curious thing happened
when we did that.
Because we went to a fairly
high-dimensional Z space.
And we got a surface that is wiggly,
and so on, which in our mind raises
alarm bells as far as generalization
is concerned.
But we ended up with something that can
be stated in a simplistic form as:
we get a complex hypothesis,
which is the snake,
but we don't pay the price for it in
terms of the complexity of the
hypothesis set.
Remember, the complexity of the
hypothesis set is what we pay the
price for in terms of the
VC analysis, right?
And it's typically the case that when
H is more complex,
each individual is also complex.
But here, we sort of did some cheating.
And we managed to use a high-dimensional
Z space,
so it's a complex H,
complex hypothesis set.
But the hypothesis we get is really--
although it looks very complex, it
really belongs to a simple set because
it maximizes the margin.
So we get the benefit of a fairly low
out-of-sample error, in spite of the
fact that we captured the fitting very
well by getting the 0 in-sample error.
Now, this is exaggerated.
I grant you that.
But it has an element of truth in it.
And it captures what support
vector machines do.
They allow you to go very sophisticated,
without fully paying the
price for it.
Today, we're going to continue
this by extending the support vector
machines in the basic case, and we're
going to cover the main method, which
is the kernel methods, in
the bulk of the lecture.
And the two topics are the kernels,
referred to as the kernel trick
actually, formally, and that takes care
of the nonlinear transformation
when the Z space can be very
sophisticated, so sophisticated that
you can't even write it down.
It's an infinite-dimensional
space.
Which would be completely unheard
of if you're using plain
vanilla linear models.
The other topic is to extend support
vector machines from the linearly
separable case to the non-linearly-separable
case, allowing yourself to
make errors.
So this is pretty much that, if you were
using perceptrons and went to
pocket, this would be if you went from
the support vector machines that we
introduced-- that we're going to label now
hard-margin, because they strictly
obey the margin-- to a soft margin
that allows some errors.
And both of these extensions will expand
your horizons in terms of the
problems you're able to deal with.
And chances are, in a practical problem,
you're going to use both.
You're going to go to
a high-dimensional space, sometimes
an infinite-dimensional space, without
paying the price for it, as we'll see
in a moment.
And in addition to that, you're going
to allow some errors in order not to
make outliers dictate an unduly complex
nonlinear transformation.
So both of them will come in handy.
Let's start with the kernels.
So the idea of the kernels is that I
want to go to the Z space without
paying the price for it.
And we are already halfway there.
If you remember from last lecture,
the way z manifests itself in the
computation is very simple.
You do an inner product in the Z
space, and from then on, it's
a regular quadratic programming problem.
And the dimensionality of the problem
depends on the number of examples, not
on the dimensionality of the Z space,
once you get the inner product.
And when you get the result back, you
count the number of support vectors,
which really depends again on the
number of examples, not the
dimensionality. Obviously, the
dimensionality will come in because
you may end up with such a wiggly
surface that every other vector
becomes a support vector in order to
support this type of boundary.
But basically, the dimensionality
of Z explicitly doesn't appear.
Nonetheless, we still have to take
an inner product in the Z space.
So in this viewgraph, I'm going to zoom
in to the very simple question.
What do I need from the Z space in
order to be able to carry out the
machinery that I have seen so far?
So what do we do?
We have a Lagrangian to solve.
So the Lagrangian looks like this.
And since we are interested in what we
do in the Z space, I'm going to make
these purple.
So in order to be able to carry out
the Lagrangian, I need to get the
inner product in the Z space.
But getting an inner product in the Z
space is less demand than getting the
actual vector in the Z space.
Think of it this way.
I am a guardian of the Z space.
I'm closing the door.
Nobody has access to the Z space.
You come to me with requests.
If you give me an x and ask me,
what is the transformation,
that's a big demand.
I have to hand you a big z.
And I may not allow that.
But let's say that all I'm willing
to give you are inner products.
You give me x and x dash, I close the
door, do my thing, and come back with
a number, which is the inner product
between z and z dash, without actually
telling you what z and z dash were.
That would be a simple operation.
And if you can get away with it, then
that's a pretty good thing.
Because now, we can completely focus
on inner products in the Z space
and see if that can lead
to a simplification.
So in this slide, we are going through
step by step in the entire process to
see if we ever need anything
out of the Z space, other
than the inner product.
So in forming the Lagrangian,
we need the inner product.
Let's look at the constraints.
We have to pass the constraints
to quadratic programming.
This is the first constraint.
I don't see any z.
So we're cool.
The other one, the equality,
I don't see any z either.
So if you have an inner product in the
Z space, you are ready with the
problem that you're going to pass
on to the quadratic programming.
You give it to quadratic programming.
Back comes the vector alpha: alpha_1,
alpha_2, up to alpha_N. Now, you need
to implement your function.
You're not just solving this.
You actually are going to hand a hypothesis
to your customer, right?
And the hypothesis looks like this.
Now, I look at this.
And now, I'm a little bit worried
because here's w and z.
Although this is an inner product, it's
not an inner product between points
in X-- between w, and I don't know what
w is. w lives in the Z space.
So I want to make sure: can I get away
with just inner products in order to
solve this?
Well, w is no mystery to us.
We have solved for it explicitly.
And we found that you can find w by
adding up, over all the vectors but in
particular over the support vectors
that happen to have nonzero alpha,
this quantity.
If you take this quantity back and plug
it in for w, what do you get in
terms of what you need to compute?
You need to compute inner products.
That's encouraging.
One more item, this innocent-looking b
is loaded.
This is one of the parameters
that we solved for.
Maybe that's what will kill us.
Let's see.
How do I solve for b?
I solve for b by taking any support
vector, and solving for this equation.
So I take a support vector,
m, and plug it in.
Am I in trouble because I have the w?
No, we already saw that w is here.
It has this form.
So I can plug it in here.
And all I need, in order to solve
for b here, is this fellow.
Done.
We only deal with z as far as the
inner product is concerned.
Now, that raises a very interesting
possibility.
If I am able to compute the inner
product in the Z space, without
visiting the Z space, I still
can carry this machinery.
We can even move further.
If I can carry the inner product in the
Z space, without knowing what the Z
space is, I still will be OK.
You may wonder, how am
I going to do that?
That's a different question.
But all we need to do now is something:
I give you x and x dash,
two points in the X space.
You do your thing, come back with
a number, and promise me that this is
the inner product in the Z space,
the mysterious Z space.
And then, I will do all the support
vector machinery in your space that I
never visited, and come up with the
support vectors which live in your
space, and get the performance based on
the number of support vectors, and
deliver to the customer, and tell
them I used really a very
sophisticated space.
And then, they would ask, what is it?
And usually, we have our stunned-silence
moments in machine learning
where you do something, and you know
that the existence is sufficient.
So let's look at this idea as
being a generalized inner
product. x and x dash,
we transform them and take an inner
product in the Z space.
We're going to treat it as if
it was a generalized inner
product in the X space.
So what are the components?
You take two points.
We're going to label them x and
x dash in the input space.
And we need this quantity.
So this quantity is a function
of x and x dash.
That much we know.
We don't know which function,
but we know it's a function.
Why's that?
Because z is exclusively
a function of x.
z dash is exclusively a function
of x dash, being
transformed versions of them.
And therefore, their inner product will
be a function that is determined
by x and x dash.
So this is the function that
I'm looking for.
Now, we're going to call this
the kernel, hence the name.
So this is the kernel
we're going to use.
A kernel will correspond
to some Z space.
And as I mentioned, this will be
labeled as an inner product--
I put it between quotations because it's
general-- between x and x dash.
It's not a straight inner product,
but an inner product after
a transformation.
Now let me give you an example.
It's a bit of a simplistic example,
but just to illustrate the idea.
Let's say that I have x
being two-dimensional.
Two-dimensional Euclidean space, so
I have two coordinates, x_1 and x_2.
And I'm using a nonlinear
transformation, which happens to be
2nd-order polynomial.
We have seen that a number of times.
So what do we have?
We have a transformation that takes the
vector x, produces the vector z.
And that would be the full 2nd-order
guy, so we have 6 coordinates
corresponding to all terms of the second
order involving x_1 and x_2, and
this is the guy.
We used that before.
And therefore, if you want to get the
kernel, which is formally the inner
product between the transformation of
x and x dash, you will get this.
Nothing mysterious, you're just going
to substitute for this for x, and
substitute for it again for x dash,
multiply the corresponding terms, and
add them up.
And this is what you get.
So the only lesson we're learning here
is that indeed this is just a function
of x and x dash.
If I didn't know this was an inner
product, I can look at this.
This is a function I can compute.
Fine, now we come to the trick.
Can we compute this kernel without
transforming x and x dash?
So let's look at the example again.
I'm going to now improvise a kernel.
It doesn't transform things
to the Z space, and then
does the inner product.
It just tells you what the kernel is.
And then, I'm going to convince you that
this kernel actually corresponds
to a transformation to some Z space,
and taking an inner product there.
So here is my kernel.
It's function of x and x dash.
And it happens to have that form.
This is a special form that
will help me later on.
But the main thing you would want to
look at is that this is not
an inner product in the X space, in spite
of the fact that it involves one
computationally.
I take this, add 1, and square it.
So this is just a function.
I happen to formalize it in terms
of an inner product, just
because it's simple.
So this is a function.
This is also not clearly an inner
product in any other space,
transformed or otherwise.
It is just a function.
So now, I'm going to
take this function.
And I'm going to write it explicitly
in terms of the components.
I'm still working with
two-dimensional input.
So this would be--
the inner product here would be x_1
x_1 dash plus x_2 x_2 dash.
So this is the quantity that I have.
And I can definitely square things.
And I get this quantity.
So this is the value of the kernel.
Now, this looks awfully familiar.
It looks like an inner product,
except for these annoying 2's.
This would have been as if
I transformed to the 2nd order and
took it, except that
I have these guys.
But is this going to discourage me?
No.
This still is an inner product.
And the transformation to the space that
makes this an inner product is
this fellow. x goes through this.
See? I put a square root.
Nonlinear transform, so I can put
anything, right?
This is my transformation.
The only test you need to ask me is
whether I applied exactly the same
transformation to x dash.
Yes, I did.
So that is indeed a transformation
of x into z.
And when I take the inner
product, what do I get?
I get my kernel.
OK, good establishment
of concept here.
But the idea is that's a lot
of fuss about nothing really.
I could have done this
in the first place.
Now, think of what happens if I am, instead
of taking 1 plus x x dash to the 2,
I do it to the 100.
Look at the difference between computing
this quantity and actually
going to the 100-order transformation,
getting this expanded, and getting the
other one expanded, and then
doing the inner product.
So let's see how this works.
That's called the polynomial kernel.
So now I take a d-dimensional
space, not 2, but general d.
And I would like to take
a transformation of that space into
Qth-order polynomial.
And here's my kernel, the
equivalent kernel.
I'm putting it between quotations
because the square root will happen
here again in abundance.
But it's just a scale.
The main idea is still there.
So here's my kernel.
I get 1 plus x-- that to the Q. First,
establishing what does it take
to compute this?
I don't know yet whether this
is a kernel, a valid kernel.
A valid kernel is an inner
product in some space.
I haven't seen that yet.
I pretty much suspect that it will be
by the previous argument, but that
will become clearer when I do this.
So when I evaluate this, so
this is an inner product.
Now, I have d dimensions.
So I have d of these guys corresponding
to each other, and then
multiply them, raised to the power Q. How
much computation does it take you
to do this?
I have d multiplications here.
That's the dimensionality
of the X space.
And then, I need to raise it to the
power Q. Whether Q is 10 or 100 or
a million, it's the same complexity.
What I'm going to do, I'm going to take
the logarithm, multiply it by Q,
and exponentiate.
It doesn't matter what this fellow is.
This is a number.
I'm not expanding them.
I'm just plugging in these,
and this becomes a number.
Raising it to the power 100, or
raising it to the power 1000.
So this is a very simple
operation to carry out.
Now, think of what happens if you were
actually taking d equals 10 and Q
equals 100.
And you can see that if I actually
expanded this conceptually, not
computationally, it's very convenient
because every time an x appears, the x
dash version of it appears.
When I multiply any combination,
that will always be the case.
I will get a tremendous number of terms,
which are all orders up to Q, of
different combinations of the x's.
And I will have a huge expansion here.
And it shouldn't be a surprise that I
will be able to decompose this into
something of x dot something of x dash,
because every term here appears with
both x and x dash--
the same trick we did here,
except more elaborately.
But if you actually go at it explicitly,
you have to give me the
entire vector in the Z space that
results from a 100th-order polynomial
transformation of a 10th-order guy.
This will be an ugly
beast to deal with.
And now I can do this by just computing
this number, just a number.
Take your x and x dash to get this
number, raise it to the power Q, and I
already have, as if I visited the Z
space and got that number there.
OK?
So if you're worried about the square
root-- because obviously,
you will get this.
But you will get a bunch
of combinations.
This gets here, gets here, and
now, you're power 100.
So there will be all kinds
of combinations.
So you'll get a bunch of constants
in front of the terms.
And you're going to square-root them in
order to get it to be a canonical
transformation.
You can adjust the scales a little bit,
not fully, by taking your kernel
instead of being 1 plus, you have scales
'a' and 'b' that will mitigate
a little bit the diversity of the
coefficients you get here.
But the bottom line is that a kernel
of this form does correspond to
an inner product in a higher space.
And by computing it just in the X space,
using this formula, I'm doing all I
need to do in order to carry
out the SV machinery.
Now, with this in mind-- I did this
by construction because it's an easy
polynomial, and we can visualize it.
We can get it in the 2 case,
and extrapolate mentally
for the other cases.
Now, we realize in this case that
we only need z to exist.
In this case, I showed you what z is
explicitly in the case of d equals 2,
and by hand waving in the
bigger case.
But you can visualize what z is.
So now, let's get carried away and try
to just get a kernel that maps us to z
without even imagining what z is.
So this is the case.
We take this to be an inner
product in some space, Z.
And once you do that, we are good with
the entire machinery, and the
guarantees, and we'll get the support
vectors, and we'll get generalization
bound, all of the above.
And here's an example of a kernel.
This will be a useful kernel.
Let's look at it.
It's definitely a function
of x and x dash.
That's as much as I would require--
the minimum requirement
for this to be true.
And now, it doesn't even have an inner
product term clearly, either in X
space or Z space.
And I have no idea what that is.
I can compute it.
And my question is, does this actually
correspond to some Z space, an inner
product in Z space.
So is this equivalent to taking each
of them by itself, transforming it
into z in that space, and taking
a straight inner product
between z and z dash?
Do I get the same number
by visiting some space?
The answer is yes.
And the interesting thing is that
that space is infinite-dimensional.
So by doing this operation, which is
not very difficult to compute, you
have done an inner product in
an infinite-dimensional space.
Congratulations!
And you will get the full benefit of
a horrific nonlinear transformation.
And you don't worry about the
ramifications of going to an infinite
dimensional space.
In the third lecture, when I introduced
linear models, if I told you
go to an infinite-dimensional space, you
would probably be screaming at me
because the generalization issues
become completely ridiculous.
But here, we don't worry.
We'll carry the machinery.
And then, we will count the number
of support vectors.
If I have 1000 examples and you only
have 10 support vectors, I know I'm in
good shape.
Well, if I get 500 support
vectors, tough luck.
It was a nice try.
There's no harm done.
So let's look at the
infinite-dimensional space.
I'm trying to convince you that
this indeed is the case.
What I'm going to do, I'm going
to take a simple case that I can
illustrate.
Let's take the kernel, but apply it in
this case to 1-dimensional space.
So x and x dash are both scalars,
I call them x and x dash.
And I'm going to take gamma to be 1,
which is my modulating constant here,
so I get this fellow.
Now, let me express this
using Taylor series.
First, I do the following.
I expand this, so I get x squared, x
dash squared, and minus twice x x dash,
and minus twice gets the
minus, and becomes a plus.
So I get e to the minus x squared,
e to the minus x dash squared,
e to the 2 x x dash.
So that's a legitimate
expansion of this.
So now, I take this and expand it using
Taylor, and I get this fellow.
You take whatever the argument is,
raise it the power k, divide it by
k factorial, sum up from
k equals 0 to infinity.
That's the Taylor series
for the e, right?
Now, I conveniently took out the x dash
to the k, x to the k, and 2 to
the k, separately.
This is just to put it in that form.
And I get that.
OK, that's very nice.
You seem to be complicating matters,
rather than simplifying it.
Remember, my purpose is to convince you
that there is a Z space in which
this is an inner product.
So now look at this last line.
And miraculously, some
terms will turn blue.
Keep your eyes on it.
Oh, you see where I'm going with this.
The guys that go with
x have turned blue.
The guys that will go with
x dash have turned red.
And why am I doing that?
Because I'm going to separate this
into an inner product, something
coming from x, and something
coming from x dash.
And I want to make sure
that it's the same.
Once it is the same, then
the dimensionality
is really this summation.
Each of these is a coordinate.
And this is the contribution
to the inner product by
this coordinate.
So here, I am getting this
x dash multiplied by x.
Both of them normalized by e to
the minus x squared.
So if I want to see what is the
transformation of the first guy, it
would be e to the minus x squared
multiplied by x to the k.
That's one coordinate.
And as k goes from 0 to infinity,
I get different coordinates.
I would be ready to go, except
for the annoying constants.
so let's put them in purple!
So what do you do with them?
You divide them between red and blue.
Take the square root of that
and put it in the red.
And take the other square root,
and put it in the blue.
And now, we have formally
two identical vectors.
One is a transformed version of x.
And one is a transformed
version of x dash.
And this is the inner product.
And it happens to be in infinite-dimensional
space, because you're
summing for 0 until infinity.
So now, this is a very
interesting kernel.
It's called the radial-basis-function
kernel, if that rings a bell.
Indeed, that's the subject
of the next lecture.
So let us look at this
kernel in action.
And it's very interesting, because it's
a very sophisticated kernel.
It corresponds to an infinite-dimensional
space.
Nonetheless, we can carry it out by
computing a fairly simple exponential
between the x points.
So let's look at it in action.
I'm going to take a slightly
non-separable case in the X space.
After all, I'm taking this glorious
nonlinear transformation.
I'd better have something which is not
linearly separable in order to show
you the goods.
But I'm taking it slightly,
in order to make a point.
So this is my target function.
So if I generate points from here, the
chances are it will not be linearly
separable, because just this wiggling
will result in that.
And indeed, I'm going to generate
100 points at random.
And I get them here.
And if you look at the 100
points, really there's no
line to separate them.
So now what I'm going to do, I'm going
to lighten the target function because
the target function did its job--
generated the examples.
But I'm going to leave it, in order
to compare it with the final
surface that we get.
So I'm just going to have
it as a light surface.
You can't even see it, probably.
It's now a green surface.
This is the data set
that I'm working with.
So this is a slightly
non-separable case.
And now, I'm going to transform X into
an infinite-dimensional space.
Someone else worries about that.
All I'm doing in my mind, I am
effectively doing that by just
computing the kernel instead
of just the simple inner
product in the X space.
And the kernel is the kernel I got from
the last slide, which happens to
be a simple exponential, I
compute it and get that.
What happens when you do that?
You get the kernel.
You pass it on to quadratic
programming.
And quadratic programming gives
you back the support vectors.
You get the support vectors.
Let me magnify it.
So we have the two classes.
And I darken the points that ended
up being support vectors.
These 1, 2, 3, 4 blue guys.
And in the red, I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
I have 9 support vectors altogether.
Now, it's very interesting.
9 support vectors, how many points?
100 points.
Can you tell me what is the
out-of-sample error?
Can you bound it above?
Oh, it looks like it should
be less than 10%.
I have gone to an infinite-dimensional space.
You're a witness to that. Right?
I used what is effectively an infinite
number of parameters.
Completely suicidal in terms of
generalization, but hey, I get 9
support vectors.
I can claim victory.
So now, let's look at the surface
in the Z space when I
transform it back here.
Again, the Z space
is a mysterious guy.
It's a hyperplane of degree
infinity minus 1.
That's very nice.
And now, I'm trying to transform this
to this space and look at it.
And it looks like this.
How did I get that?
I didn't go to the Z space.
What I did, I classified every point on
the grid, and saw when it transforms
from -1 to +1.
That's my only tool.
But I can do it because the
kernel is easy to compute.
If I went into the Z space, you would
have never heard from me again!
So this is a good way of doing it.
You look at it, and it's
really very pretty.
First thing, you don't get
the green thing exactly.
But you can see why support vectors
are called support vectors.
They're sort of holding the guy.
You can see it up and down, up
and down, up and down.
That's pretty good.
The other thing is that, when you think
of the notion of a distance, remember
that-- this is linearly
separable in that
space. Had better be.
We've got the infinite-dimensional space.
If you don't get linearly separability
there, you are really in trouble!
And when I get the linear separability
there, I get a margin.
I try to maximize the margin.
That has already been
maximized by the machinery.
So I get a respectable margin.
And the evidence for the respectable
margin is that I do get the small
number of support vectors,
which are here. Fine.
And now, when I look at the distance,
the value of the margin, the value of
the margin is in the Z space.
I cannot see that.
But here, you can see that if you look
by the distance, these two support
vectors are awfully close
to the surface.
This support vector is not that close.
Well, maybe it will become close
when this goes to extend.
But it's definitely further away,
in the X space as we see it.
But again, this is not the margin.
These guys are pre-images
of support vectors.
They are not support vectors per se.
And the distance that was solved
for happened in the Z space.
Whatever happens here happens here.
You may end up with something,
where you get support vectors far
away, and it's like a strange thing.
Don't sweat bullets over it.
It's happening in a space that
we don't understand.
As long as the machinery for the
solution is correct and I get the
support vectors that happen
to have lambda greater
than 0, I am in business.
Let's shrink this back.
So we get this solution.
And it's a pretty nice tool to have.
And we ask ourselves: was this
an overkill to go to an infinite
dimensional space?
Yes, early on before we studied
this thing, we would say
that's a complete overkill.
Even for these two dimensions,
it's slightly OK.
If you went to a 5th-order polynomial,
I would already be worried
that you're really doing too much.
Now, you went to an infinite one.
But now, we're asking
a different question.
We're asking: check the number
of support vectors.
That is your guide.
And that is an in-sample quantity
that you can observe.
And that will tell you the
generalization property.
So now, we are completely sold
on the idea of the kernels.
Now let's look at if I give you
a kernel, and it's a valid kernel that
corresponds to an inner product in some
Z space, how do you formulate
the problem?
This is just formality.
You already know.
But just let's take it step by step.
What do you do?
You remember quadratic programming?
Yes, I do.
And in quadratic programming,
we have this huge matrix.
This is the big Q matrix that you
pass on to the algorithm.
And you compute it in terms
of inner products.
And these were genuine inner products,
when you were working with linearly
separable data in the X space.
So now, the only thing you're going to
do is that, instead of passing this to
the quadratic programming, you're
going to pass this instead.
That's it.
This may not be too much
computation at all.
I can get the exponentials,
and get this number.
And now, quadratic program
is ready to go.
Absolutely nothing else.
If you look at the rest of the details,
nothing is affected by the
transformation, other than this
quadratic-programming matrix.
That's good.
Now, quadratic programming
passes you the alphas.
You need the hypothesis.
So how do I construct the hypothesis
in terms of the kernel?
So this is g of x equals that.
I'm writing it because
it's safe to write.
There's a Z space.
I know I am linear there.
And this is the form that I've
already been solving in.
Now, I just want to translate
it in terms of the kernel.
I know that I can, because we've spent
a lot of time realizing that we don't
need anything from the Z space other
than the inner product, and the inner
product is the kernel.
I just want to put the
explicit form here.
So you want to put this in terms of
kernel of something and something.
And you take w to be this.
And you're not going to solve
for any of those.
These are just for illustration.
And then, you get: g of x
would be this fellow.
So you took this, substituted there,
you took the inner products.
The inner product is what the kernel is.
You put the kernel in place
of it, and you get that.
Now, this is very interesting because
this is your model, so to speak.
Support vector machines is a plural.
Support vector machines-- doesn't
dictate a particular model.
You choose a kernel, and it'll
give you a different model.
So if you have ever been curious, in the
middle of all of this jungle, what
is the model?
What is the hypothesis that
I'm working with?
It happens to have this
functional form.
The kernel you choose appears here.
It gets summed up with coefficients.
The coefficients happen to
be determined by alpha.
They all happen to agree
in sign with the label.
That's one of the artifacts of that,
because alphas are non-negative.
And we have plus b.
And again, plus b is the one
that we haven't solved for.
But I can solve for it
using the other one.
And I end up with this
equation for it.
Take any support vector, small m, and
you can identify it by having its
alpha being bigger than 0.
You plug it in, and you have that.
So we have the full definition
of your hypothesis.
And you get the solution in this form.
And this is for any support vector
which is defined by: alpha_m
greater than 0.
Now, let me make a point.
The nonlinear transformation
that started support vector
machines is this guy.
So in reality, I have an infinite
dimensional nonlinear transformation.
Each of these is a coordinate
that depends fully on x.
So I end up with 1, x, x squared,
x cubed, x to the 4, and so on.
And if I'm working from an x that is
more than one-dimensional, I get x_1,
x_2 squared, x_1 x_2, whole thing.
I just avoided the labor
by using the kernel.
Nonetheless, when I got the solution,
I got this solution that made me
completely forget that
I did a nonlinear
transformation into the Z space.
I can look at this and say: what
I'm really doing is that this is my
transformation, so to speak, the K's
I have, however many of them as there
are terms here.
And each of them has a coefficient.
This would be a legitimate
way of looking at it.
The only thing to remember, and it's
very important to remember, is that
this transformation depends
on your data set.
You see this x_n?
This one doesn't.
This one, before you gave me the data
set, I decided that I'm going to use
the RBF kernel-- exponential, so I get
1, x, x squared, x cubed, x to the 4.
All of this is determined without
looking at the data set.
This transformation, in order to get
this thing, I need to know what x_n is.
But we have seen this before.
Remember the hidden layer
in neural networks?
It got a nonlinear transform
based on the data set.
So this is not foreign to us.
But this tells you why this
looks very simple.
Where is the infinite-dimensional space?
I'm only determining this.
This is the solution after all the
manipulation has been done.
And that is why it has this form.
But then, it will allow us to compare
support vector machines to other
approaches.
For example, if I put the RBF kernel
here, the one with e to the minus x
squared with the norm, I will
get a functional form.
It is completely legitimate to say:
let me look at functional forms of
that form, and try to solve the learning
problem based on these, without
ever hearing of support vectors.
It's just a model.
Let me see if I can get a solution.
And it's very interesting to go through
this exercise, and to compare
the result of doing it this way
versus doing it the SVM route.
You can also do that for a neural
network and other
kernels that you have.
Now, the question is-- I am
completely ready here.
If you give me the kernel,
everything is understood.
I can solve it, and I can
interpret the solution.
And I can judge the quality of the
solution, and all of that.
The only problem I have is that we don't
know that the kernel is valid.
If I improvise, I tell you
what K of x and x dash is, and
just give you a formula.
The whole idea of the kernel is that
you don't visit the Z space.
So how are you going to verify that
this is a valid kernel, namely
an inner product in some space,
without visiting that space?
That's the question.
How do I know that Z exists
for a given kernel?
By the way, in support vector machines,
you will come up with your
own kernels.
So it's a good idea to just ask yourself,
what are the conditions to get
the kernel right?
In order to get it to be a valid kernel,
there are three approaches.
First approach, we have already seen.
This is by construction, conceptual
construction if not explicit
construction, like we did
with the polynomial.
We looked at it, and we realized that
there is a polynomial thing.
And although I didn't do it for the case
of Q equals 100, I realize that
there will be corresponding terms, and
I will be able to separate them.
So in my mind, that is the Z space.
And without constructing it explicitly,
I realize that the kernel
that I wrote will correspond to
an inner product in that space.
This is a very effective approach, and
the polynomial transformations are the
most famous ones there.
The other one is the one we're going to
talk about in the next slide, which
is using math properties of
the kernel, something
called Mercer's condition.
So I'll talk about it.
I wish it was a practical condition.
It's a very appealing condition
theoretically.
You will find it a little bit
difficult to apply in given
situations.
The good news is that people have
applied it to a bunch of kernels, and
have declared them legitimate.
So you can pick from that catalog
without worrying about it, that these
have already been established.
It comes into play when you
want to test a new kernel.
Not an easy endeavor-- not
an impossible endeavor,
but not an easy endeavor.
The third approach is the one
I find rather interesting.
So how do you know that Z exists?
Who cares?
This is an approach followed by people
who say: this looks like a great
machinery you have.
You give me the kernel.
I do this.
I go to that.
So I'll just improvise a kernel,
and who cares if there is
a Z space or not?
I never visit it anyway.
Wait a minute!
You don't visit it, but it has to exist
for all the guarantees that I
talked about.
Quadratic programming, and you get
support vectors, and alpha greater
than 0, and the generalization, all of that
depends on the Z space being there,
and you're actually separating
the data there.
Believe it or not, there's quite
a number of people who just improvise
a kernel, apply the machinery,
and see what happens.
And sometimes they succeed.
I have my reservations, let
me put it this way!
So let's go for the mathematical
route, if you actually care,
rather than who cares!
So if you design your own kernel, and
then you want to see what happens,
here is the condition.
The following statement holds.
The kernel that you wrote down is a valid
kernel, this is, the Z space that
you're talking about actually exists,
if and only if two conditions in
conjunction are satisfied.
One is the fact that the
kernel is symmetric.
That should be abundantly obvious,
symmetric being K of x and x dash
being equal to K of x dash and x.
Well, this is supposed to be the dot
product in the Z space, right?
So we're going to transform
x and x dash into z and z dash.
While in the Z space, certainly z dot z dash
is the same as z dash dot z.
Inner product is commutative.
So if this has a chance, it
had better be symmetric.
So this is definitely one
of the conditions.
The other one is that there is a matrix
that we're going to require
a property on.
And that matrix looks like this.
Similar to the one you're passing to the
quadratic programming, but without
the y's. What you do, you just list
the value of your kernels on all the
pairs coming from your data set.
So if this was a genuine inner product
and you had it explicitly, each of
these will be the inner product.
This one would be z1 transposed z1.
This would be z2 transposed
z1, et cetera.
And therefore, this thing could be
decomposed as an outer product between
z's standing and z's sitting.
And you will get that.
So the condition here on that matrix,
without visiting the z, is that when
you put these numbers, to your pleasant
surprise, this needs to be positive
semi-definite.
That is, in matrix lingo, this matrix
should be greater than or equal to 0.
That's what positive semi-definite
really means conceptually.
This should be true for any
choice of the points.
And that is Mercer's condition.
Now, we can see the difficulty.
If I want to satisfy that this is true
for any points I choose,
obviously I have to have some math
helping me to corner that this has to
be positive semi-definite
for some reason.
But this is indeed the condition.
And if you look at the case where you
know the transformation into the z and
you put this as an outer product between
a bunch of z's and a bunch of
z's, what you're going to get is
patently positive semi-definite.
Because what is positive semi-definite?
You put a sleeping vector here and
the same vector standing here.
And you're guaranteed to get
a number greater than or equal
to 0 for any vector.
That's what positive
semi-definite means.
If you put that and the matrix happens
to be the outer product of these guys,
then the guy sleeping here gets
multiplied by z, and the other guy is
a transpose of that.
So you get a number squared, and
a number squared is always greater than
or equal to 0.
So the necessity part is obvious.
Sufficiency is a very elaborate
thing to prove.
And actually, it is proved in a fairly
elaborate integral form, not in
a particular realization.
But that is indeed the condition.
And if you manage to establish this
for any kernel, then you establish
that the Z space exists even if you
don't know what the Z space is.
Done with kernels.
That's half the deal.
And now, we are going to the
case where the data is
not linearly separable.
And we still insist on separating
them, with making some errors.
And this brings us back to the old
dichotomy between two types of
non-separable.
We have seen this before.
And this actually turns out to be the
subject of this lecture, if you will.
So if the data is non-separable, that
could be slightly non-separable, like
this, where these guys are just-- you
can take them as here and here.
These are outliers.
I really don't want to go to a high-dimensional
nonlinear space in order
to just go for this guy
and go for this guy.
It doesn't look like a plausible
thing to do.
And even with counting support vectors,
by the time I do this and
come back, I would have touched on so
many points that the chances are the
number of support vectors
would be huge.
So in this case, if there's a method
like the pocket, I would just make
errors on those, accept an E_in
which is non-zero.
But since the generalization is
good, E_out would be OK.
Rather than insist on E_in being 0, and
then go for the generalization error
being huge, because I used something
inordinately complex.
So this is the slightly-case.
And then, there is a seriously
non-separable case,
as in: you get this.
It's not a question of outliers.
The surface is this, and you have to
go to a nonlinear transformation.
Kernels deal with this.
Soft-margin support vector
machines deal with this.
And in all reality, when you deal with
a practical data set, the chance are
the data set will have aspects of both.
It will have a built-in nonlinearity,
and still, even modulo that
nonlinearity, some annoying
guys are there just to test
your learning ability!
And therefore, you will be combining
the kernel with the soft-margin
support vector machines in almost all
the problems that you encounter.
Now, let's focus on this.
I'm now back to the X space.
The data is not linearly separable.
And I want to apply the support
vector machines algorithm,
notwithstanding that.
And after I do that, I'm not going to
even go through the route of: and by
the way, you can transform x into z,
and by the way, you can instead of
going to Z, you do the kernel.
You do that yourself.
I'll just do the basic case.
And you know how to extrapolate, to both
the Z and to the kernel case.
So here is the idea of an error
measure, as we had before.
I'm going to consider the
margin violation.
Let me have a picture
and talk about it.
So when you solve support vector
machines in a linearly separable case,
you maximize the margin.
And these will be the ones
that achieve the margin.
And these guys will be
interior points.
And now, we are going
to consider errors.
There are many ways for
considering errors.
I can consider the number of
points I misclassify.
We realize that it's not a good idea to
deal with the number of points that
are misclassified, because optimization
becomes completely
intractable in this case.
It's a combinatorial optimization.
And we discussed that when we talked
about perceptron and pocket.
And we said that the problem of optimizing--
getting the absolute optimum-- in
this case, is generally NP-hard.
So we are going to have
a numerical value.
And because the margin means something
to me now-- it's not a question of
being on the right side of the line,
it's a question of how far you are
from the line-- that turned out to be
an important notion in support vector
machines, I'm going to define my error
measure based on violating the margin.
So let's see what I mean.
This point that used to be here
has violated the margin.
Now, I'm not saying that once you put
this here, the same solution will hold
or whatever.
I'm just illustrating to you what
is a violation of the margin.
And how do I quantify it.
This is just an illustration.
So this point went in.
In spite of the fact that it's correctly
classified-- yes, because
this is the line, and it's on the blue
side of the line, so to speak.
So there's no change in
terms of the label.
If I'm working with in-sample
error, nothing has changed.
But now, I am not achieving the margin
that I want for this point.
And the amount of violation will be
decided by this displacement.
So here is what I'm going to do.
This will be the case if the margin
is satisfied for every point.
That is the canonical form we put.
And when this fails, the
margin is violated.
And I'd like to quantify that.
The way I'm going to quantify it,
I'm going to introduce a slack for
every point, potentially every point.
Hopefully, most of them will satisfy
the margin, only a few of
them will violate it.
And I'm going to say that the quantity
that used to be greater than or equal
to 1, is actually greater than
or equal to 1 minus a slack.
So this is what I will have.
The movement from here to here
resulted in the red xi.
And the slack is greater
than or equal to 0.
I'm only considering violations.
Now, I'm going to consider--
this is the condition.
And now, I'm going to penalize you
for the total violation you made.
What is the total violation?
I'm just going to add
up these violations.
We have seen error measures before.
We know that it's largely hand-waving,
because I have something in mind.
Either I'm thinking of an optimizer, and
I want to hand something friendly
to it, or I'm thinking of something
that is analytically plausible.
This is no different.
Why did I choose this
instead of squared?
Why did I choose this instead of that?
All of these are considerations that
will come up when you see the result
of choosing this.
This is reasonable.
This does seem like violating
the margin.
This does seem like measuring
the violation of the margin.
So in the absence of further evidence
one way or the other, this is a good
error measure to have.
And then, when I plug this error measure
into what we had, things will
collapse completely back to where
we solved it already.
So this is the big advantage here.
So that is going to be
my error measure.
So now, the new optimization I'm
going to do is the following.
It used to be that I was minimizing this,
because minimizing this maximized
the margin.
That was what we did the last lecture.
And now, I'm going to add an error term
that corresponds to the violation
of the margin, and it is
going to be this.
So this is the quantity that I promised
you captures the violation of
the margin.
And this is a constant that gives me the
relative importance of this term
versus this term.
This is no different from our
notion of augmented error.
In augmented error, we used to have the
in-sample performance, which I guess
would be the violation
of the margin here.
If you're violating too much, you'll
start making errors. Plus lambda
times a regularization term. This
looks pretty much like
a regularization term, like weight decay.
So this C is actually 1
over the other lambda.
But this is a standard formulation
in SVM for a good reason.
C will appear in a very nice
way in the solution.
So this is an augmented error. That
gives different weights.
If I have C close to infinity,
then what am I saying?
You'd better not violate the margins.
Because the slightest violation, you
mess up what you're minimizing.
So the end result is that you're going
to pick xi's, all of them, close to 0.
And then, the data had better
be linearly separable.
And that's what you're solving for.
So we go back to the hard margin.
If C is very, very small, then
you could be violating the
margin right and left.
So nominally, you're getting
a great margin.
But you're violating
it very frequently.
And there's a compromise here.
But that's what you're minimizing.
Subject to: this is what I had before,
and now the condition adds xi to it.
So I'm now requiring this
to be the case.
And I said that xi's are non-negative.
I'm only penalizing the violating
of the margin.
I'm not rewarding the anti-violation
If here's the thing, and one of the
points is there, good for it.
I'm not going to give it credit that
allows me to violate the other guys
because that's not going to help me.
So xi is non-negative.
And I get this condition for all
points, all N of them.
And finally, I have the range in which
I'm optimizing, which used to be this.
And now, I have the xi's being R to the
N. I guess positive, but that is
captured by the constraint.
If you look at this slide, take out the
red, and you have the problem you
already solved, the hard-margin SVM
in the linearly separable case.
So this is the added guy.
Now what we're going to do, we're
actually going to go through the
Lagrangian again, because the Lagrangian
is not that much different
from before.
So we can take it as a review.
And the good thing is that, if you thought
that the terms dropped right and left
before, wait until you see this one.
So here is the Lagrange formulation.
We have L of w, b, and alpha, and some
missing guys that will be filled.
And we have this and minus that.
So you can see that it's spread out,
because obviously I'm going to put the
new stuff in.
What I put here is exactly the
Lagrangian you worked with before.
This was your target.
This was the 0 form of
the inequality--
that means this minus 1 is greater
than or equal to 0.
You put that and multiplied it by the
Lagrange multiplier, which is
non-negative, minus because it's in the
form of greater than or equal to,
and this is your Lagrangian
that we solved.
And we ended up with the quadratic
programming problem we had.
So now, there is a new
guy which is xi.
That's a new variable that
I'm determining.
How does it appear in the Lagrangian?
Well, the target is no longer just
minimizing this, but minimizing this
plus the other guy that penalizes
the violation of the margin.
So let's put that.
Now, the constraint that I had used to
be: this is greater than or equal to 1.
So I had it as minus 1 for the 0 form.
The new constraint is: this is greater
than or equal to 1 minus xi.
So I need to put the new constant,
and when you put, it's minus
minus, you get the plus.
So that's the complete term.
Now, the other guy is that I have
a bunch of constraints on xi itself.
I need to put them in
the Lagrangian form.
And this would be this.
Not scary at all.
xi_n is really the constraint
on xi in the 0 form.
xi is greater than or equal to 0.
So if I wanted to put it in the 0 form,
then I put xi-- that has to be
greater than or equal to 0, pretty
much like this fellow had to be
greater than or equal to 0.
I need to multiply it by a Lagrange
multiplier, a new guy.
So I call those guys beta.
And I do this for all of the
constraints, N of them.
And I have a minus because this
is in the direction greater
than or equal to.
So there's absolutely nothing
different here.
And now, I add the new Lagrange
multipliers to them,
and I get this fellow.
Now, I'm proud of this
because of a reason.
The slides are wide-screen
for this course, right?
I had to have an equation that
takes the full width of that.
And finally, in lecture number
15, I managed to do that!
Now you say: forget it.
This is just too complicated.
Please bear with me, because terms
will be dropping like flies.
Just follow this and
see where we arrive.
We're going to minimize this with respect
to w and b, which we used to
do, and with respect to xi,
which is our new guys.
Minimize, and then we're going to
maximize with respect to the Lagrange
multipliers, the alphas which we used
to have, and the betas are the new
guys in town.
So let's do the first guy.
Let's do the minimization with respect
to w, which we did before.
Can you differentiate this
with respect to w?
I will get a w here.
This red guy doesn't contribute.
Here, I will get what I used to get.
This guy doesn't interfere.
This guy doesn't play a role.
That's encouraging.
I am actually getting
what I got before.
Let's do partial by partial b.
Does this guy play any role?
This guy gets multiplied by here.
Does this guy?
b doesn't appear here.
I get exactly what I got before.
So the final guy is to get the
partial by partial xi's.
That's the new guy.
So you do this.
Let's see what happens.
I'll do it one at a time.
There are N of those.
I didn't put it as a gradient,
just to make it simple.
So I do it one at a time.
And I see xi_n gets multiplied by C.
xi_n gets multiplied by alpha with
a negative sign.
xi gets multiplied by a beta
with a negative sign.
So if I differentiate with respect to
xi, this is what I'm going to get,
C minus alpha minus beta.
Equate that with 0.
Now, isn't that grand?
Because now, you are saying that this
quantity is always 0 for any n
from 1 to N. Let's look at the
ramifications as far as the Lagrangian,
when you substitute in the Lagrangian.
Here, I have a C. Here,
I have a minus alpha.
Here, I have a minus beta.
These are multiplied by xi.
That combination happens to be 0.
So conveniently, this guy and this guy
and this guy, together with beta, are
dropping out.
We are back to exactly the same
Lagrangian we had before, with exactly
the same solution we had before.
And what happened to beta?
Well, beta did its service.
And we thank it for its great service,
and we bid farewell!
It's gone.
The only ramification of beta that we
have is that because beta is greater
than or equal to 0, and we have this
condition, alpha is not only greater
than or equal to 0, which it used to
be. It also cannot be bigger than C,
because if it's bigger than C, this
quantity becomes negative.
And all of a sudden, I cannot find
a legitimate beta to make this true.
So the only thing out of all of this
adventure is that we're going to
require that alpha be at most C.
Everything before, plus this added
condition, that's the whole thing.
So you get the solution.
You get this.
That's what we saw before with respect
to alpha, and beta doesn't appear.
And you have alphas being non-negative
with the added red condition. That's
the only thing which is added,
less than or equal to C.
The equality constraint is there.
The equality constraint, that is
inherited from the condition from the
previous slide, same as we did before.
And when you get the solution,
w will be this.
And w will guarantee that
you're minimizing this
plus the new objective.
So if you already wrote your routine
in order to apply support
vector machines, all you need to do now
is go to that routine, and instead
of 0 less than or equal to alpha less
than or equal to infinity, make it 0
less than or equal to alpha less than
or equal to C. And you have the soft
margin support vector machines.
That is a good bargain.
Let's look at, just very quickly,
types of support vectors.
This is the picture.
And this is the picture where you
have support vectors in the hard
margin case.
There are only two types of points here,
interior, where the margin is
greater than 1 strictly, and the boundary
guys that happen to be support vectors
where the margin is exactly 1, or at
least the quantity that corresponds to
the margin is exactly 1.
And that is all I have.
Now, when you have the soft version,
we are going to label these guys
margin support vectors, just because
there will be other guys that violate
the margin.
And they will be support vectors.
They will get Lagrange multipliers
that are greater than 1.
And in this case, the margin support
vectors that used to be just alpha
greater than 0, they also happen to be
strictly less than C. You can look at
it independently in order to understand,
but let me just give you
the hint here.
When alpha hits C, beta, the
lost multiplier, hits 0.
We know when the Lagrange multiplier
hits 0, the corresponding slack has to
become positive.
That was one of the conditions we had.
And therefore, because here the slack
is 0, you actually don't have xi.
xi is 0.
You have to be clear of C. That
is the reason for it.
So this is the condition
for those guys.
And xi is 0.
And these are the guys you used to
solve in order to get the b.
These are as clean
as they used to be.
Now, we add the non-margin
support vectors.
And by those, we mean that now alpha_n
equals C. So it's positive.
They are support vectors.
Alpha_n is greater than 0.
But they happen to hit C.
And now, I have a slack.
The slack xi starts becoming positive.
And therefore, the margin is violated.
I'm less than 1.
So that's 1 minus xi,
and xi is positive.
Indeed, xi is positive in this case.
So let's look at those non-margin
support vectors, and see
what they look like.
Again, just for illustration, I'm
going to take these two points and
start making them violate the margin,
not that the new solution will be
exactly the same except that
these guys are inside.
You have to re-solve it
with C, et cetera.
But I'm just illustrating, just
to show you the point.
So this is one way to
violate the margin.
You violated the margin, but you're
still classifying them correctly.
These are non-margin support
vectors, one type.
You can violate it further, and cross.
So now, these points
are misclassified.
And they are still non-margin
support vectors.
And now, the E_in is affected.
And you can go wild.
And you're just completely deep.
As long as you're violating,
you are a support vector.
Not a clean support vector, but
a support vector nonetheless.
Now, the value of C is a very important
parameter here because it
tells us how much violation we have,
versus the width of the yellow region.
And this is a quantity that will be
decided in a practical problem using
old-fashioned cross-validation.
This is a point, a parameter
that we need to determine.
And whenever we have one parameter to
determine, and we want to pick it
optimally, we can use
cross-validation.
So as you see, validation and
cross-validation are a layer on top of this.
Here, I'm using a very elaborate
algorithm which is support vector
machines, yet I am resorting to
cross-validation in order to
determine C.
I'll make two quick technical
remarks and end the lecture here.
These are just practical points
in case they bother you.
If you didn't see them, they are
not going to bother you.
Here is the idea.
With the hard margin, I
apply this machinery.
I get the dual, pass it
to quadratic programming.
So I'm asking myself, if the data is
not linearly separable, what gives?
Because think about it.
I never told you to check that the
data is linearly separable.
I gave you the data, formulated--
minimize this subject to that.
Now, if the data is not linearly
separable, subject to that will be
impossible to satisfy.
There will be no feasible solution.
Nonetheless, this didn't prevent me from
getting a dual and passing it to
quadratic programming.
And maybe quadratic programming
will give me back a solution.
So now, I'm in a strange world.
The key thing to realize is that the
translation from the primary form,
minimizing w transposed w, to the dual
form, maximizing with respect to alpha--
the Lagrangian-- that step is
mathematically valid only if there is
a feasible solution.
The KKT conditions are necessary.
So they have to be satisfied
if the point is there.
Obviously if there is no point in the
domain, then I'm now working pretty
much like the guy who improvised
a kernel that does not
correspond to a Z space.
Yeah, you can plug it in
and get a solution.
No guarantees there.
In this case, actually, if you go
to the Lagrangian, the quadratic
programming will try to converge to
something in infinity.
But you need not to worry
about this case at all.
Let's say that you have a buggy
quadratic programming.
And you innocently translate
the problem into the dual.
You pass on to quadratic programming.
Quadratic program passes
alphas back to you.
Now, it's impossible that all of
a sudden, the data became linearly
separable, right?
You don't have to worry.
You can always check if the solution
separates the data.
You can evaluate the solution on every
point, compare it with the label.
And when you realize that it's not
agreeing with the label, you realize
that something is wrong.
So you don't have to go through the
combinatorial problem: is this
linearly separable in the first place?
Should I run the perceptron first
to see if it converges before?
No, no, no, no.
Just be lazy if you want,
and go through this.
And when it comes back, check.
If it's linearly separable,
things are valid.
There is a feasible solution.
The dual solution is valid and
quadratic programming works.
If it's not, then something
went wrong.
Chances are you won't get to that stage,
because quadratic programming
will be complaining.
But quadratic programming will be
complaining anyway, as you may have
experienced when you tried it.
Tells you: ill conditioned, that, there,
and sometimes you have tweaks.
Let me put a bound on this,
in order not to make it go into
a bad region and whatnot.
So it's not a perfect package.
So this is just a reminder that we will
never be susceptible to a big
mistake, like getting a solution
when none exists.
The last point is when we transform to
the Z space, you may have noticed that
some of the transformations had
a constant coordinate, 1.
1 in our mind used to
correspond to w_0.
We made it a point at the beginning
of discussing support vectors
that there is no w_0.
We took it out and called
it b, the bias.
We treated it differently.
So now, we are working
with both w_0 and b.
Because if you have a constant,
you may not call it w_0.
But effectively, it's w_0.
It's the guy that gets multiplied
by the constant.
So what gives?
Now, I have two guys that
play the same role.
And you don't have to worry about
that. Have the Z space have 20
constant coordinates.
Don't worry about it.
Because of what?
Because when you get the solution,
all of the corresponding
weights will go to 0.
And all the bulk of the
bias will go to the b.
How do I know that?
Because you are charged for the size
of w_0 because it's part of w.
You are minimizing half w transposed w.
You're not charged for the size of b.
So obviously, if you want to minimize,
and you can do it with both,
everything will go to the b,
and this guy will go to 0.
So no need to worry about that.
With that, we'll stop here,
and we'll take questions
after a short break.
So let's start the Q&amp;A. And
we have an in-house question.
STUDENT: Hi.
It seems intuitive to me that the
number of support vectors goes
linearly with the dimension of the
space that you're looking at.
For example, in an N-dimensional
Euclidean space, you need N-vectors to
define an N-minus-1 dimensional hyperplane,
and one other to define the
thickness of the fat plane, right?
PROFESSOR: It's not that
easy, because I could get two clusters
that are far away of points, and then
two points that are +1 and -1
that are close to each other.
And in order to separate, I have
to be sandwiched here.
And then, I am guided by these guys--
I have the orientation here.
And the orientation is decided by the
two points that are around me.
So in spite of the fact that in a general
case, I will do that, I could
construct cases where it's not
linear in the dimension.
Let's put it this way.
STUDENT: So you're saying
it's less than linear?
It's better than linear?
PROFESSOR: It's better.
And obviously if it was completely
linear, and I transform it to the
infinite-dimensional space, I obviously
would be in trouble.
STUDENT: Yes, that's my aim.
PROFESSOR: Ah, so that was
that question, yes.
STUDENT: But it should go positively
with the dimension.
PROFESSOR: It's likely
to increase with
the increasing dimension.
And the exact form depends on the data
set, and depends on the position of the
data set, including the
interior points.
Let me put it this way.
If I give you, even without considering
the interior points.
Let's say I give you two points,
one +1 and one -1.
There is an optimal separating plane.
And how many support vectors
am I going to get?
I cannot get more than two because I
only have two, even if I go to 100
dimension space.
So the linearity is an impression that
requires further assumptions.
But in general, it will not hold.
STUDENT: Yes and for example, the RBF
kernel, it may in its form look like
infinite-dimensional.
But in reality, I think its effective
dimension is very small because the
higher-order terms decay very fast.
So with both an exponential term
and a factorial term--
PROFESSOR: Completely agree, and
indeed that affects it because you
are actually measuring a distance
proper, a Euclidean distance proper in
that space.
So if a dimension is very small, then
it doesn't affect it very much.
Whether it's really infinite dimension
or infinite dimension in disguise.
In general, when you have an infinite-dimensional
space, the only way to
really define an inner product
is to have a decaying term so
that the thing converges.
So this is essential when
you want to compute it.
STUDENT: So it doesn't converge, so
you changed the negative sign in the
RBF kernel into positive signs?
Then, it won't be a valid kernel.
PROFESSOR: But the inner product now
is not well defined, right?
STUDENT: So it won't be a valid
kernel, and you'll get horrible--
PROFESSOR: Yeah, because a valid
kernel, I have to be able to
evaluate the inner product.
And lack of convergence would
not allow that, right?
STUDENT: Yeah, OK, thanks.
PROFESSOR: Absolutely.
MODERATOR: People are curious.
How can you generalize SVM's
to a regression case?
PROFESSOR: There's a huge body of
knowledge for generalizing it.
And I didn't touch on
it for two reasons.
Again pretty much like when I did the
VC analysis, it's more technical.
And I get the basic concept without
having to go through the technicality.
The other aspect is that the major
success of support vector machines is
really in classification.
They're not as successful, competitively,
in regression.
That's the practical experience.
So I have found that it's not worth the
amount of time to go into that.
MODERATOR: So is it safe to assume,
then, that if you do the
transformation to an infinite-dimensional
space, the data will be
linearly separable there?
PROFESSOR: It is
safe but not certain.
I can create situations that
are opposed to that.
But again, this is one of the reasons
why I made the final remarks there.
Because let's say that I took my data
and applied RBF, I needn't know
whether they would be linearly separable
in that space or not.
I just apply the machinery, but I can
always find the solution back and see
if the points are classified
correctly.
MODERATOR: So a technical question
on the quadratic programming.
Usually, if the matrix you give is
not positive definite, there will be
complaints by the--
or there would not be complaints
in particular?
PROFESSOR: My experience with quadratic
programming, there are tons
of packages there.
So I'm describing a subset of them
necessarily, the ones I tried.
They tend to complain.
And it's almost like when you use MatLab
and it tells you-- please get me
the inverse.
And it tells you the condition
number is bad, and so on.
So in most of the cases, even with the
complaints, the solution is fine.
It just has a certain reliability
that it has to have in
order not to complain.
So invariably, when you use quadratic
programming, there will be a complaint
one way or another.
But I have learned not to be completely
discouraged by that, and
tweak, limit variables, and whatnot.
But this is just completely
a practical situation,
depending on the package.
MODERATOR: Going back to
a previous question.
So when you said safe but not certain,
so does that mean just in very
degenerate cases, or--?
PROFESSOR: With a real data set
that is not completely
ridiculous, I have never
seen it happen.
In some sense, you can have--
especially with the radial basis function,
you can have one on top of each point,
so you can separate whatever is there.
So I have not encountered it.
MODERATOR: Another question.
Is it possible to combine kernels to
produce new, different kernels?
How useful is it to do
these kind of things?
PROFESSOR: You can do it as long
as the combination is legitimate,
that it maintains that there
is a Z space in which
this is an inner product.
That's really the requirement.
If you have that, then there are many
variations of the methods, the basic
SVM method that are in the literature.
People tried several things.
And as long as what you're doing is
legitimate, so that you have the
generalization guarantees
of SVM, it can be done.
MODERATOR: Since we're only talking
about inner products and they
usually induce a norm, are we always
preferring the Euclidean norm, or can
it still be changed and still
use inner products?
PROFESSOR: The way I derived
it is based on Euclidean norm and
straightforward inner product.
There are obviously variations of that
that you can get, and still have the
machinery go through with
modified quantities.
So it's not impossible.
But you just need to make sure that
the quadratic programming problem
you're solving corresponds to the
version of the norm that you used and
the version of the inner
product that you used.
MODERATOR: What would you say is the
scale of the problems that can be
solved by SVM's, in the number
of points?
PROFESSOR: The scale of problems
that can be solved by
quadratic programming is a more pointed
question, because that's the
bottleneck.
It depends on if you're using MatLab
versus something else, they get
saturated at different stages.
I would say if you get to 10,000 points,
that's pretty formidable.
And if you're below 1000,
you should be OK.
But some packages will still
give you a hard time.
There are packages specifically
for SVM that use heuristics.
So they don't specifically pass on the
thing to quadratic programming
directly, but try to break it into
pieces, get support vectors for each
case, and then get the union
and so on, the hierarchical
methods and other methods.
So they are basically heuristic
methods for solving SVM when
straightforward quadratic
programming will fail.
And these are also available, and should
be used when you have too many
data points.
MODERATOR: I think that's it.
PROFESSOR: Very good.
We'll see you on Thursday.