ANNOUNCER: The following program
is brought to you by Caltech.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Welcome back.
Last time, we talked about the bias-variance
decomposition of the
out-of-sample error.
And we managed, by taking the expected
value of the out-of-sample with
respect to the identity of the data
points-- the size is fixed at N--
to get rid of the variation
due to the data set.
And we ended up with a very clean
decomposition of the expected value of
the E_out, into a bias term and
a variance term, that have very
interesting interpretation.
And they're illustrated here
in terms of a tradeoff.
If you have a small hypothesis set,
the chances are the target
function is far away.
And therefore, there is a significant
bias term, which is the blue one.
And if you have a bigger hypothesis
set, perhaps big enough to include
your target, you don't have very much
of a bias, perhaps none at all.
But on the other hand, you do have
variance depending on which hypothesis
you zoom in based on the
data set you have.
So in the bias-variance decomposition,
we basically had two hops from the
final hypothesis you produced based on
a particular data set, into the target
function which is what we're
trying to approximate.
The intermediate step was the new
notion, which is the expected value
of the hypothesis set with respect to
D. And the jump, from your actual
hypothesis to that fictitious hypothesis,
describes the variance,
because here is the centroid of this,
which is the g bar, and you are
somewhere here.
So in order to get there, that is
described by the size of the red
region, and that is the variance.
And then there is another one, which is
inevitable for a given hypothesis
set, which is the hop from that
one, which designates the best
approximation, in a certain sense, within
the hypothesis set, of your target
function, into your target function.
And that difference is the bias,
which is captured here.
After doing the bias-variance
decomposition, we went into
an illustrative tool called the learning
curves, where we plot the expected
value of the in-sample error and the
out-of-sample error, as you increase
the sample size.
If you look at the curve-- let's
look at the bottom one here.
Not surprisingly, as you increase the
number of examples, the out-of-sample
error goes down.
If you have more examples to learn from,
you are likely to perform better
out-of-sample.
And another interesting observation is
that when you have fewer examples, the
in-sample error goes down.
And that is because you are fitting fewer
examples, and you have the same
resources to fit.
So you tend to fit them better.
And the discrepancy between them
describes the generalization error.
Then we contrasted the analysis of the
bias-variance decomposition, which is
the top curve, to the VC analysis,
which we have done before.
And we realized that both of them
describe a tradeoff between
approximation and generalization.
In the bias-variance case, the
approximation is an absolute
approximation--
how your best hypothesis approximates
the target.
And that is described by g bar, again
with certain liberty.
And in the case of the VC analysis, the
approximation was approximation
in sample only.
So it was E_in.
And then the jump from the approximation
to the final performance
describes the generalization, whether it's
this red region or this red region,
which have basically the same
monotonicity, except that they have
different terms.
The final lesson from the theory, which
is really what we're going to
carry out through the techniques, which
start today until the end of the
course, is that the number of examples
needed to achieve a certain
performance is proportional
to the VC dimension.
And I'm putting it between quotes,
because we defined it formally only for
classification.
But then we took the linear regression
case, which is not classification, and
we found out that the corresponding
quantity, which is the degrees of
freedom-- same thing, d plus 1--
happens to also describe the
generalization property.
And therefore, we basically have
a certain rule that you need examples
in proportion to the VC dimension,
or to the effective degrees of
freedom, in order to
do generalization.
And the more you have, the better
performance you get.
This is the key observation.
Today, I'm going to start
a series of techniques.
And today is special, because the
techniques of the linear models have
already been covered in part.
Remember, this is the part that was
split into two portions.
And we got a portion very early on,
out of sequence, just to give you
something to work with.
And then, I'm going to complete the
exposition of the linear models today.
So let's see where we are.
This is the big picture
of linear models.
And they start with linear
classification-- perceptrons.
We have seen that.
And then go on to linear regression.
We have also seen that.
That was the part that was covered.
There is a third one, which is another
linear model that is neither linear
classification nor linear regression,
which will be the bulk of
the lecture today.
It will be called logistic regression.
And then, for all of these linear models,
we have this nice trick called
nonlinear transforms that allows us to
use the learning algorithms
of linear models, which are
very simple ones, and apply
them to nonlinear transformation.
And if you remember, that the observation
here was that linearity in the
parameters was the key issue
for deriving the algorithm.
So let's see what we finished, and what
we didn't finish in these topics.
Linear classification
is pretty much done.
We know the algorithm,
perceptron or pocket.
There are obviously more sophisticated
algorithms.
And we did the generalization
analysis.
We got the VC dimension of
perceptrons explicitly.
And therefore, we are able to predict
the generalization ability of linear
classification.
So this is a done deal.
Linear regression is also a done deal.
We have the algorithm, remember, that
was the pseudo-inverse, the
one-step learning.
And last time, we did a very brief
analysis of generalization ability.
And we found that it parallels that
of the perceptron, d plus 1 is the
operative point, the operative
quantity in this case.
And therefore, we have linear regression
as a technique, and as
a generalization ability.
In the case of nonlinear transforms,
we are almost done.
We did the techniques, but remember, we
left at a point where we say
nonlinear transforms are
a very useful tool.
And they actually can make us separate
any data points, by going to
a sufficiently high-dimensional space.
And we had a suspicion that this is not
really a safe process to follow.
We have to worry about generalization
issues.
So the generalization issues
were left out.
And I'm going to start this lecture by
tying up the loose ends in
generalization for nonlinear transforms,
before I go into the main
topic, which is the third one.
That is logistic regression.
So.
Very brief analysis of nonlinear
transforms in terms of generalization,
then logistic regression
beginning to end.
That's the plan.
OK.
Nonlinear transforms.
Let's remind ourselves.
We were working in an X space.
And we had a d-dimensional vector
that represented the input.
And we added the constant
+1 coordinate, to
take care of the threshold.
And now, we are going to transform
this into another space using
a transformation we called phi.
This takes us into the Z space,
or the feature space.
So each of these guys is derived
from the raw input x.
And the transformation we have can be
quite general. If you
look at it,
any one of these coordinates can be
an arbitrary nonlinear transformation of
the entire vector x.
It doesn't take one coordinate.
It takes the entire vector--
so all of these guys--
computes any formula you want, and then
puts it as the feature here.
So you can imagine how
general this can be.
And also, the length of
this can be arbitrary.
You can have this as long as you want.
As a matter of fact, when we move to
support vector machines, we will be
able to go to infinite-dimensional
feature space, which is an interesting
generalization.
So, each of them is
a general transformation.
And therefore, the small phi_i is
a member of the big transformation,
capital phi, that takes the vector x,
and produces the vector z working in
the Z space.
That's that transform.
An example for that, which we
used, was 2nd order.
Instead of using linear surfaces here,
we wanted to use quadratic surfaces.
And quadratic surfaces in the X space
correspond to linear surfaces in
a quadratic-transformed space, Z.
So this would be the transformation.
We got all possible factors that
contribute to a 2nd-order
term.
And now if you put coefficients to each
of these and sum them up, you
will get a general 2nd-order
surface in the X space.
Now the final hypothesis for us
will always live in the X space.
The Z space is transparent
to the user.
This is our tool in order to get more
sophisticated surfaces in the X space,
while we are able to use the
linear techniques.
So the final hypothesis will be
mentioned as g of x equals--
So you have the linear thing, but you
have that transformed version of x.
That's what you get the
dot product with.
So this is z.
And in the case of classification, you
take the sign, +1 or -1,
according to the signal whether
it is positive or negative.
And in the case of linear regression,
you get the raw signal itself.
And as we will see, we will have a third
one, which is in-between taking
the sign and leaving the quantity alone,
when we talk about logistic
regression.
That's the summary of nonlinear
transforms that we have seen so far.
And now we talk about generalization,
and ask ourselves: what is the price we pay
when we do a nonlinear transform?
The price we will pay, obviously,
in terms of generalization.
So this is the transform.
Now if you look at the X space, and
ask: what is the generalization
behavior in the X space?
Let's say that you don't do
the nonlinear transform.
You do the linear model
in the X space.
Well, in that case, you are going to
get a weight vector in the X space.
And the dimensionality of the weight
vector is the same as here, so it will
be d plus 1.
There is a weight corresponding
to each of these coordinates.
And then you take the dot product, and
whether you use threshold, or report it,
depending on which type of linear
model you are talking about.
But basically, you have d plus 1
free parameters.
And we realize that d plus 1
free parameters correspond
directly to a VC dimension.
In the case of the Z space, the
feature space, we have
potentially a longer vector--
much longer, possibly.
And the dimensionality
here is d tilde.
That's the notation we give for it.
And the vector that will apply
here will be w tilde.
That will be a much longer vector
in general than w.
So for example, in our case, if we
used the linear with x_0, x_1, x_2,
we would have 3.
If we did the full 2nd order,
we would get 6.
So we get more there.
And we have seen that the VC dimension
is, in this case, for the perceptron,
d plus 1.
So this is the price you pay
for the generalization.
And here, the price you pay for
the generalization can be
pretty serious.
Now you see that if I want to separate
the points, and then I go to
a 17th-order polynomial,
general 17th-order polynomial, and
then you count the number of
coordinates you have gone to, the VC
dimension would be so large that, in
spite of the fact that you were able
to fit-- because you went to a 17th
order polynomial--
you don't really have a real
chance of generalization.
Just to be accurate, this is really not
equality here, because we always
measure the VC dimension
in the X space.
Again, the Z space is transparent
to the user.
So we go here, and we come back, and we
ask ourselves what can we shatter
here and whatnot.
So in spite of the fact that in this
case, if you had the full space, and
you were able to choose the points any
which way you want, you will be able to get
exactly that VC dimension, it is
possible that there are certain
combinations of points here that
are impossible to come by as
transformations of legal points here.
If you want a simple case, let me just
take two coordinates to be identical--
same transformation.
So obviously, now I'm stuck.
I don't have the full benefit of the
coordinates, because if I choose one,
the other one is dictated.
So just because of that fact, in order
to be accurate, we will say that it is
actually, at most d plus 1.
Usually, it's very close to d plus 1--
d tilde plus 1.
So let's apply this to two cases where
we use nonlinear transformations, in
order to appreciate, in practical
terms, what is the price we pay.
The first non-separable
case is a pretty easy one.
It's almost separable, except for some points
that you can consider, maybe, outliers.
This red point is in the blue region,
this blue in the red region.
But otherwise, everything can
be classified linearly.
So one may think of this case--
this case is really linearly
separable, and we just have a bunch of
outliers, maybe we shouldn't use
nonlinear transform, just settle
for the linear--
We will talk about that.
So this is one class of things,
when we look at nonlinear
transforms.
The other one is genuinely nonlinear.
This thing-- I really don't stand
a chance if I use a line, and therefore,
I'm really talking about something
that needs to be transformed.
So let's see how the generalization
behavior goes, for both of them when we
apply the nonlinear transforms.
The first case is pretty easy.
It's almost linearly separable.
So here are the choices.
You can use a linear model in X space,
in the input space that you have, and
then accept that the in-sample
error will be positive.
It's not going to be 0.
In this case, here's the picture.
There is an in-sample error, because this
guy is erroneously classified, and
this guy is erroneously classified
by your hypothesis.
So this is option number one.
Now, option number two is to say I
would like to get E_in to be 0, so you
insist on E_in being zero.
And in order to do that, you have
to go to another space.
So you decide to go to
a high-dimensional space.
Now you can see what the problem is
here, because we are just taking care
of two points, for crying
out loud!
And in order to actually be able to classify
them using a surface, believe it
or not, you're not going to be able to
do it with a 2nd-order surface, or
a 3rd-order surface.
You will have to go to a 4th-order
surface in order to get it all right.
And when you do that, this
is what you get.
Now, you don't need the VC analysis to
realize that this is an overkill, and
this doesn't have a very good
chance of generalizing.
Of course, you can do
the formal thing.
You see 4th order.
Instead of having 3, I
have however many there are.
And therefore, for the limited number
of examples I have, when I see the
generalization behavior, I am
completely in the dark.
So in this case, that is
a straightforward application of the
approximation-generalization
tradeoff.
We went to a more complex model.
We were able to approximate the data
better, but we are generalizing worse.
This has been completely covered
already, so there is no surprise in
this, other than to understand the fact
that at times, you might as
well settle for a small training error,
in order not to use too high
a complexity for the hypothesis set.
The other one is the case where
you really don't stand
a chance with linear.
It will be very, very poor
approximation and generalization.
The data seems to be coming from
inherently a nonlinear surface.
And in this case, we used
this transformation.
And this transformation is my
way of putting a general
2nd-order surface.
And if you look at it, if we use only the
x, which would be conveniently the
first three guys-- that would be
the vector x, get weights--
I have 3 weights, so I pay
for the price of 3.
Whereas if I use this, I have 6,
so I pay for a price of 6.
So basically, in our mind, you need
twice as many examples to do the same
level of performance.
Not that we have a choice in this case,
because the linear doesn't work,
but this is basically the
formula we have in mind.
Now comes an interesting
discussion.
I don't want to pay the 6.
I want to go to the nonlinear space,
but I don't want to pay the 6.
I want to get a discount!
Here is a way to get a discount--
not necessarily legitimate, but let's
pursue it and see why it would be
legitimate or not.
Why not transform x into
this guy only?
The idea here, this
is the origin.
x_1 goes like this, x_2 goes like this,
so it seems that I only need x_1
squared and x_2 squared.
These guys are just making me pay,
without really contributing.
So I'm just going to
use this model.
Well, if I use this model, it looks
like I have now 3.
So I have exactly the same number of
examples as if this was linear, and as
if I was doing it in the X space.
If you are smelling a rat,
you are correct!
And in order to make it clear,
let's just pursue this line.
I can do even better than this.
Why not take 2 guys
instead of 3?
I have the second guy being x_1 squared
plus x_2 squared, because I really don't
care about x_1 squared and x_2
squared being independent.
They are just the radius in my mind.
So I need to do this.
Now we have achieved a lot, because now
we have even fewer parameters than
if we use the linear guy, so the
generalization must be getting better
and better.
Now let's get carried away,
and go for the ultimate.
I have one guy.
I even let go of the mandatory
constant.
I just have this guy.
And all I'm learning in this case is
just what is outside and what is
inside the circle, really.
It doesn't even need a parameter,
just needs a binary one.
Now I have one guy, and
the VC dimension is 1.
And I can generalize greatly--
dot, dot, dot.
Well, something is wrong.
Now it's clear that something is wrong,
but it's very important to
articulate what is wrong.
What is wrong is that you're charging
the VC dimension of this hypothesis
set, right?
Think of the VC inequality as providing
you with a warranty.
Now in order for the warranty to be
valid, you cannot look at the data
before you choose the model.
That will forfeit the warranty.
why does it forfeit it?
Because of the following.
I am going to charge you-- if I
do the analysis correctly--
not the VC dimension of
the final guy you got.
I'm not going to get the VC dimension
of this fellow.
I'm going to charge you the VC dimension
of the entire hypothesis
space, that you explored in your mind
in getting there, because you have
acted as a learning algorithm,
unknowingly.
You looked at the data.
Before you looked at the
data, you had no idea.
Let's say that you decided ahead
of time, I'm going to use
a 2nd-order set.
2nd order, OK?
Now you look at the data, and you
realize that some coefficients are 0.
That's called learning, right?
I don't need this.
You did it very quickly
in your mind.
So the hypothesis that was learned
was a hierarchical learning.
First, you learned, and then you passed
it on to the algorithm to
complete the learning.
So the effective hypothesis set
is what you started with.
You see where the point is.
And the lesson learned from this is that,
if you look at the data before
you choose the model, this can be
hazardous to your health.
Not your health, but the generalization
health.
Why is that?
Because now, the quantity that
describes generalization
becomes very vague.
When we propose a particular model, I can
go and mathematically estimate the
VC dimension.
If you look at the data, we said
that you did learning.
Now I'm asking, what is exactly the
full hypothesis space that you
explored in the beginning?
That's a little bit vague--
very difficult to pin down.
Definitely bigger than what you are
going to use if you use the VC
dimension of the hypothesis set
that you ended up with.
And this is a manifestation
of the biggest trap that
practitioners fall into.
When you go into machine learning, I want
you to learn from the data, and
choosing the model is very tricky.
Some model may work, some
model may not work.
So it's tempting.
Let me just look at the data, and
pick something suitable.
Well, you are allowed to do that.
I'm not saying that this
is against the law.
You can do it.
Just charge accordingly.
Remember that if you do this, and
you end up with a small hypothesis
set, and you have a VC dimension, you have
already forfeited the warranty that is
given by the VC inequality
according to that.
It applies only to the VC
dimension to begin with.
And this is a manifestation
of basically snooping.
You snooped into the data.
You looked at it in a way
that is not allowed.
And when you do this,
bad things happen.
And the formal term for it, actually,
in machine learning, is called data
snooping.
And we will dedicate one third of
a lecture just describing data snooping.
This is the most obvious manifestation
of data snooping.
You look at the data before
you choose the model.
But there are other ways that are so
subtle, that it's very likely that even
a smart person may fall
into those traps.
And it's very important to understand
what these traps are, in order to avoid
them, and make sure that when you apply
the theory, after all of the
sweat we had in order to get
these things, they might as
well be valid.
And you can immediately make them not
valid by doing these things.
So this is the subject
of data snooping.
And I'm not minimizing the idea of
choosing a model. There will be ways to
choose a model.
When we talk about validation,
model selection will be the
order of the day.
But it will be a legitimate
means of model section.
It's a model selection that does
not contaminate the data.
The data here was used
to choose the model.
Therefore, it's contaminated.
It's no longer trusted to reflect the
real performance, because you have
already used it in learning.
This is the lesson we get.
And if you remember when I said linear
models are an economy car, nonlinear
transforms give you a truck.
And we saw that the truck
is very strong.
I can go to very high-dimensional space.
I can have very sophisticated surface.
And then I warned you that, be careful
when you drive a truck.
And this is what I meant by that.
That there are dangers.
You could be well meaning, and you could
simply crash, instead of having
the smaller car that may not be as
impressive, but it will definitely get
you where you want.
Now we move into the main topic
of the lecture, which is logistic
regression, which is a very
important linear model.
And it complements the two models
we have seen so far--
linear classification-- the perceptron,
and linear regression.
And there are three pieces.
First, I'm going to describe
the model.
What is the hypothesis set that
I'm trying to implement.
And then we're going to devise
an error measure for it, which is
a pretty interesting error measure.
And finally, we are going to go
for the learning algorithm
that goes with it.
It turns out that the model is
different, the error measure is
different, and the learning algorithm
is different from what
we have seen before.
So by the time we have done this, we
will have covered enough territory in
these variations.
And this will really be
very representative of
machine learning at large.
So linear models will not only be
a very useful model to use.
They also cover the concepts
in many techniques that
you will see otherwise.
For example, the learning algorithm here
is the same learning algorithm we
are going to use in neural
networks next time.
So let's start with the model.
Here's the third linear model.
Being linear means that we take your
inputs, compute a signal that is
a linear combination of the
input with weights, s.
And then I take s, and
do stuff with it.
And the stuff could be linear
classification, perceptrons.
And what was that?
In this case, you take your
hypothesis to be a decision,
+1 or -1.
And that decision is a direct
thresholding, with
respect to 0, of the signal.
So you take this linear signal, and this
is what you do to it in order to
get the output, and that will
give you the perceptron.
Let's put it in a picture.
Here are your inputs.
x_1 up to x_d, this is
the genuine input.
This is the +1 that takes
care of the threshold.
They go with these into the sum, so
this would be weights going, attached
to these guys.
And then they are summed,
in order to give me s.
And then one linear model or another
will be doing different things to s.
The first model will take s and
pass it through this threshold, in
order to get +1 or -1.
Now the second guy
was linear regression.
What did we do to the signal in
the case of linear regression?
Nothing.
We left it alone.
That was our output, right?
So if you want to put it in
the same diagram, you can.
And in this case, you do the linear
sum, et cetera, and you
get the signal.
And then you have the identity
function, if you want.
You output what you input.
And that's what you get.
Now when you go to the third guy, the
new guy, which is called logistic
regression, we are going to take s
and apply a nonlinearity to it.
The nonlinearity,
which we're going to call theta,
the logistic function--
it is not as harsh as
this nonlinearity.
It is somewhere between this
and leaving it alone.
And it looks like this.
You can see that's
an interesting thing.
I am bounded.
This is the least I can report.
This is the most I can report.
It looks bounded like this.
It actually looks pretty much like this,
except for the softening of it.
But it's a real value, I can return any
real value between this value and
this value, so it has something
of the linear regression.
And the main utility of logistic
regression is that the output is going
to be interpreted as a probability.
And that will cover a lot of problems,
where we want to estimate the
probability of something.
Let's be specific.
Let's look at the logistic
function theta, the
nonlinearity I talked about.
It looks like this.
It can serve as a probability,
because it goes here from 0 to 1.
And if you look at the signal, if the
signal is very, very negative, you're
close to probability 0.
If the signal is very, very
positive, it's close to 1.
And at signal 0, it's probability half.
So that actually corresponds
to something meaningful.
The signal corresponds to the level
of certainty I have about something.
If I have a huge signal, I'm pretty sure
that a binary event will happen.
And if the signal is very negative,
I'm pretty sure that it will not
happen, so the probability is 0.
Now there are many formulas that I can
have that we give you this shape.
This shape is what I'm
interested in.
And I'm going to choose
a particular formula.
And the formula is this.
It's not that difficult.
I have an exponential
here and here.
Let's say that you take s to go to
plus infinity-- very large signal.
This will be huge.
And this will be the same amount, huge.
The 1 will be negligible, so
the ratio will get closer
and closer to 1.
If this s is negative, this is very
small, and this is very small.
So the 1 dominates, and you will get
something small divided by 1, which is
very close to 0.
That's what I get here.
And indeed, if you get s equals 0, you
will get 1 over 1 plus 1, which is
a half, so it will give you this.
This is a nice function.
It's indeed odd around
half, if you will.
This part is the same
as this part.
And the reason for taking this
particular form is that, when we plug
it in, and we get the error measure, and
then we go for the optimization,
it will be a very friendly formula.
You can have another formula that has
the same shape, and then you run into
trouble when you go into
the next steps.
So this is with a view to
what is going to happen.
This thing is called soft threshold,
for obvious reasons.
That is, the hard version would
be, just decide this or this.
So this softens it, and gives you
a reliability of a decision.
If you think that we are talking about
the credit card application, it
used to be that I want to know
if a customer is good or bad.
Instead of deciding if the customer
is good or bad, which is
a binary classification, I ask
myself: what is the probability
that this customer will be good?
Or what is the probability
that they will be bad?
That is, what is the probability
of default?
And then I can say 0.8, 0.7, 0.3, and
let the bank decide what to do
according to this probability, to extend
credit, how much credit to do,
and so on.
So there is a utility for that.
And the soft threshold
reflects the uncertainty.
Seldom do we know the binary decision
with certainty, and it might be more
information to give you the uncertainty
as part of the deal.
And that is reflected in
this soft threshold.
It's also called sigmoid, for a simple
reason-- because it looks like
a flattened out s.
This is an s, so you call it sigmoid.
You'll hear sigmoidal function, or soft
threshold, and whatnot.
And there's more than one sigmoidal
function or soft threshold.
I told you this was one formula.
There are other formulas.
In fact, when we go to neural networks,
there will be another formula that is
very closely related.
And you can invent other
formulas, as well.
So this is the logistic function.
This is the model.
We know what the model does.
The main idea is the probability
interpretation.
We have the model-- the model is:
you take the linear signal, pass it
through this logistic function, and
that will be your value of the
hypothesis at the x that gave
rise to that signal.
And we are going to interpret
it as a probability.
So we think that there is a probability
sitting out there,
generating examples.
Let's say a probability of default,
based on credit information.
I'm going to give you an example
where it's patent that you
actually need a probability.
It would be absurd to try to predict the
thing outright as a decision.
And that is the unfortunate
prediction of heart attacks.
Now heart attacks, or the risk of heart
attacks, depends on a number of
factors.
And you would like to predict whether
there is a big risk or
a small risk.
The kind of input you will have is
data that are relevant to having
a heart attack.
You can look at cholesterol level,
the age, the weight-- the weight of
the person, not the weight
of the input--
and so on.
And then the output here would be
a probability, because if I told you
to predict whether the person will have
a heart attack or not, and you
say +1 or -1, I think this will
be laughable, because there are
so many factors that affect it. You
will be correct very, very small
amount of the time, and it's very difficult
to tell that your predictions are
better than another one.
Both of you are wrong most
of the time.
What we are doing here, we are actually
predicting the probability of
a heart attack within
a time horizon.
Let's say that you take this data today,
and I'm asking: what is the
probability that you will get a heart
attack within the next 12 months?
That's the game.
You return a number, and that will be
reflected by the output of logistic
regression.
Now if you look at the signal that
goes into this thing, the signal
goes from minus infinity
to plus infinity.
And that's a linear sum of those guys,
that we take and process in order to
make it a probability.
Two things to observe.
First, this remains linear.
That is, you are actually
giving an importance--
I'm going to call it "importance"
because there's a weight here.
So you're going to give an importance
for the age, an importance for the
cholesterol level, an importance
for the other factor.
But from then on, all you do is just
give the importance weight, and
sum them up.
Now it's conceivable, obviously,
that this is bad, because
you look at the age.
In terms of risk, basically 40
is critical for these things.
So it's not really linear.
Above 40 or below 40 makes
a big difference.
So there is a non-linearity there.
Does this bother us?
No.
We know that we can study
the clean linear system.
And when the time comes to apply it,
we can always transform those to
relevant features, and we have the
same machinery in place.
The other aspect of the signal is
that this can be interpreted.
You can think of it as a risk
score, if you will.
Remember the credit score?
We have the credit score, and then
compare it to a threshold to decide
to extend credit, or
not to extend credit.
This is a risk score.
Although it's translated to probability
to make it meaningful, I
can tell you, you add this up, and you
are 700, you're in trouble.
You're minus 200, you're in
good shape, in general.
But obviously, in order to interpret
them in an operational way, you need
to put them through the logistic, in
order to get a probability which can
be interpreted.
This is the probability that someone
will get a heart attack within
a certain time horizon.
Now I'd like to make the point
that this is genuine probability.
What do I mean by that?
You have a hypothesis that
goes from 0 to 1.
I'm interpreting it as a probability.
But you could just think of it as
a function between 0 and 1.
If I give you examples-- here is x, and
here is the probability, which is
a number between 0 and 1--
I'm going to learn it.
And the fact that you are using it as
a probability is your business.
I'm just going to take two functions,
try to get the difference between
them, let's say mean squared
error, and learn.
The main point here is that the output
of the logistic regression is
treated genuinely as a probability,
even during learning.
Why is that?
This is because the data that is
given to you does not tell you the
probability.
I don't give you the first patient,
and here are the data.
And-- this is supervised learning,
right, so I have to give
you the label--
the probability of getting a heart
attack in 12 months is 25%.
How the heck would I know that?
I can only get whether someone
got a heart attack or
didn't get a heart attack.
Well, that is affected by the
probability, but I don't have access
to the probability.
So this is a noisy case, where the nature
of the example is that I give
you a binary output that is affected
by the probability.
This is generated by a noisy target,
so let's put the noisy target
in order to understand where the
examples are coming from.
It's the probability of y given x.
That is what noisy targets are.
And they have the form of a certain
probability that the person gets heart
attack, and a certain probability that
they don't get a heart attack, given
their data.
And this is generated by the target
that I want to learn.
So I'm going to call the probability
the target function itself.
The probability that someone
gets heart attack is f of x.
And the probability that they don't--
it's a binary thing-- has to be 1
minus f of x.
And I'm trying to learn f,
notwithstanding the fact that the
examples that I am getting are giving me
just sample values of y, that happen
to be generated by f.
I want to take the examples, and then
generate h that approximates the
hidden target function.
Understood the game?
That's why it's genuine probability.
It's not only 0,1, it's also that the
examples that I am given have already,
inherently, a probabilistic
interpretation.
So the target is from
the d-dimensional Euclidean space
to 0,1, the interval.
And it is interpreted
as a probability.
And now, you want to learn the final
hypothesis, which will be called g of
x, which happens to have the
form of logistic regression.
That's the model we are talking about.
So you are going to find the weights,
and then you're going to
dot-product it with x, and pass
it through the nonlinearity.
And the claim you are going to end
up saying is that this is
approximately f of x--
the real guy, the probability
here.
And you are going to try to make that as
true as possible, according to some
error measure that we
are going to define.
And what is under your control?
As always with linear models, what
is under your control are
the parameters.
You change the parameters in order
to get one hypothesis or another.
So the question now becomes, how do
I choose the weights such that the
logistic regression hypothesis reflects
the target function, knowing
that the target function is the way
the examples were generated?
That's the game.
So let's talk about
the error measure.
Now again, remember in error measures,
we had the proper way of generating
an error measure, and then we had plan B.
In the absence of very specific way of
paying a price--
if you predict a heart attack and
it doesn't happen, what is the cost?
The guy is alarmed, et cetera.
If you don't predict it, and it happens,
then maybe you should have
taken precautions and whatnot.
And you can put prices, and do
all of the analysis.
That is not done.
Now we are resorting to the case where
we use analytic properties,
something plausible that makes this
look like an error measure--
Yeah, if I actually minimize
this error measure, I'm
going to be doing well.
Or take something that will be friendly
to the optimizer, that after
I do it and pass it to the optimizer,
the optimizer will easy time
minimizing it.
Well, it turns out that in this case,
the error measure that I'm going to
describe has both properties.
It's plausible, and friendly.
So it's a very popular error measure.
So let's construct it.
For each point x and y-- and remember
that y is binary, +1 or -1,
that is generated by the
target function f.
We have the following plausible
error measure.
Here is the argument.
It is based on likelihood.
Likelihood is a very established
notion in statistics, not without
controversy.
But nonetheless, it's
very widely applied.
And the idea of it is that I'm going
to grade different hypotheses
according to the likelihood that they
are actually the target that
generated the data.
So let's be specific.
We assume that, at your current
hypothesis, let's say that this was
actually the target function,
just for the moment.
You have the data, right?
The data was generated by
the target function.
So you can ask: what is the probability
of generating this data if
your assumption is true?
If that probability is very small, then
your assumption must be poor.
And if that probability is high, then
your assumption has more plausibility.
So I can use this to build a comparative
way to saying that this is more
plausible hypothesis than another,
because the data becomes more likely
under a scenario of this hypothesis,
rather than this hypothesis, being the
actual target function.
This is the idea.
You ask yourself, how likely?
And the difference--
So I said about controversy.
The controversy is a bit subtle, related
to the controversy that I raised
early on in the course.
The thing you are really trying to
find, if you decided to use
a probabilistic approach, which is your
thing, for choosing the hypothesis.
What you're trying to find is, what
is the most probable hypothesis
given the data?
That would be completely clean.
Now here, you are asking, what is the
probability of the data given the
hypothesis, which is backwards.
It has plausibility. That's
why it's called likelihood.
It's not exactly the probability
we want.
And the people who don't like likelihood
would add a prior and use
a Bayesian approach, which looks
principled, but then there's a big
assumption in it.
So this is never a completely
clean thing.
It could be clean in terms of
derivation, but conceptually,
there's always a funny aspect to it.
But we will swallow that, because
it looks very reasonable that
if I choose a hypothesis under which having
that data is very plausible, it
looks like this hypothesis is likely,
hence the likelihood name.
So this is the probability
distribution we have, right?
This is the genuine probability
distribution for generating the y.
So under the assumption that h is f,
that probability would be-- if I used
h to generate it, that would be my
measure of the probability of the data
under this assumption.
This will be the way for you
to define the likelihood.
Assume it was generated by h, compute
this probability, and that will be the
likelihood of the hypothesis given
one data point x,y.
Now let's use this in order to derive
a full-fledged error measure.
What are you going to do?
You are going to take the
formula for likelihood--
this.
That is for one point.
And then you have a formula
for h of x.
You're using logistic regression.
So in this case, this thing happens
to be that formula.
It does depend on x, as
you expect it to.
And it does the dependency through
the choice of parameters w, and
passing through a nonlinearity theta.
Now I don't like the fact that
these are cases, because I
want something analytic.
This is a number that I'm going to take
and multiply, and take logarithms
of, and I don't want to keep
worrying about cases.
So now something comes handy here, which
is the following observation.
The sigmoid-- the logistic function--
happens to satisfy that theta of minus
s equals 1 minus theta of s.
Let's first look at it
pictorially, and then
see why this is useful.
Can you verify that?
Yeah.
We said that this is odd around half.
If you go theta of minus s, this
would be 1 minus this guy.
Very easy to verify, and you can
verify it from the formula,
straightforward.
The good thing about it is that 1 minus
theta looks like this fellow.
And I only add a minus sign in this
case, but the minus sign is readily
available, because this case
goes for y equals -1.
So it's already crying for a simplification,
and the simplification
would be that P of y given x, in
general, equals this.
What did I do?
For the case +1, I have it
straightforward, because this is +1.
Nothing changes.
And in the case -1, I have minus this,
which is 1 minus, and that gives
me this formula.
So it's summarized by this
very simply case.
So I have one example x and y, and I
want to get the likelihood of this w,
given a single example.
This would be the measure
for that likelihood.
That's good.
Now we have the likelihood
of the entire data set.
Someone gives you a bunch of
patients, and whether they had a heart
attack within 12 months
of the measurements--
and quite a number of them.
And now I would like to say,
what is the likelihood of
this entire data set?
The assumption, as always,
is the independence from
one example to another.
And therefore, if I want to get the
likelihood of the data set, I'm going
to simply--
let me magnify this--
this would be: I'm multiplying the
likelihood of individual ones from n
equals 1 to N, covering
the data set.
Now I need a formula for that. Well,
it's ready because I already have
a formula for P of y given x.
All I need to do is plug it.
And when I plug it, I end
up with this thing.
That's a very nice formula because
now you realize, I
have a bunch of examples.
They have different +1 or -1's that
come in here, different x_n's. The
same w of my hypothesis contributes
to all of these terms.
So now you can find that there
will be a compromise.
If I choose w to favor one example,
I'm messing up the others,
so I have to find a compromise.
And the compromise is likely to reflect
that I am catching something
for the underlying probability
distribution that generated these
examples in the first place.
Now let's go for what happens when
we maximize this likelihood.
We'll write it down, and then we'll
take it, and the maximizing of
likelihood will translate to the
minimizing of an error measure as we
know it, or as we have
been familiar with.
First thing, we're maximizing.
Remember, in the error measure,
we are minimizing.
So something will happen through this
slide that will make maximization go
into minimization.
That shouldn't be too difficult.
But let's look at what
we are maximizing.
We are maximizing the likelihood of
this hypothesis, under the data set
that we were given.
Given the data set, how likely
is this hypothesis?
Which means, what is the probability of
that data set under the assumption
that this hypothesis is
indeed the target?
And maximizing with respect to what?
To something that will turn purple.
That is our parameter.
We are maximizing this function
with respect to w.
Now I'm going to play with this.
We are maximizing this, right?
Can I maximize this instead?
Yeah.
First, it's legitimate to do.
This is the natural logarithm.
First, it's legitimate to take it,
because the quantity here is
non-negative, right?
theta, by nature, is positive.
So I'm not taking logarithm of
0, or logarithm of negatives--
things that are not allowed, so
first, I am allowed to take it.
Second part is that the logarithm happens
to be monotonically increasing of
its argument.
If you maximize it, you maximize
its argument, or vice versa.
So I am allowed to do that.
I like that, so let
me play it further.
Can I do this?
Yes.
That's just proportional.
The monotonicity
still goes.
But you can see where this
is going, right?
I'm trying to get an error measure,
error measure in the training set.
That used to be what?
1 over N summation of errors
on individual guys.
So you can see that this is shaping.
One final thing.
Can I do this?
No.
You are maximizing.
This is not--
but then all you need to do is, instead
of maximizing, you minimize.
We are cool.
So this is the problem.
Now let's see what it's--
Miraculously, the logarithm-- the product
becomes a sum of the logarithms.
and I do this, the minus takes
the guy, and the logarithm
puts it in the denominator.
And after all of this very sophisticated
algebra, we end up with
something that looks very
suspiciously familiar--
1 over N, summation from n
equals 1 to N.
Something that involves the value of the
example, and the parameters that
I'm trying to learn.
Anybody has seen something
like that before?
We're going to give it the proper
name in a moment, but
this is what we have.
Now I'd like to reduce this further,
so I'm going to remember what theta
was, because theta is a mysterious
quantity. I want to put it in terms
that I am completely familiar with.
So theta was this guy, which was e to
the s divided by e to the s plus 1.
Now I can reduce this by dividing both
the numerator and denominator by e to the
s, in which case this
will become this.
No surprise.
Why is this good?
Well, this is good because I have theta
here, so if I substitute it here, the
1 plus will go in the numerator.
Good things will happen.
So let me substitute and
see what happens.
Now because what I'm going to get is
very clean, and very close to the
formula, I'm going to officially declare
it the in-sample error of
logistic regression.
I am minimizing it, so it's legitimate,
and it looks like this.
This is simply substituting
in the above formula, I get this.
Now this is very nice.
I have this term, depending
on this example.
I'm summing them up, so I'm completely
within my rights, since I'm minimizing
this as my in-sample error,
to call this fellow what?
To call it the error measure.
Let me magnify it.
This is something that depends
on the particular example.
I'm going to call it the error measure
between my hypothesis, which depends
on w, applied to x_n, and the value you
gave me as a label for that example,
which is y_n.
That is the way we define error
measures on points.
So this is my formula for the error
measure, and under that, maximizing
the likelihood would be like minimizing
the in-sample error.
Now let me leave this for a moment,
just to mention a point.
There is an interesting
interpretation here.
If you look at w transposed x_n, this
is what we call the risk score.
If this is very positive, the guy
is likely to get a heart attack.
If it's very negative, the guy is very
unlikely to get a heart attack.
Now this one is whether that particular
person, that supplied the
data, ended up with a heart
attack or not.
Let's see agreement/disagreement,
and how they affect the
error measure.
If this signal is very positive,
and this guy is +1-- so the guy
actually, unfortunately,
got a heart attack--
then the result is that
this is minus a lot.
And therefore, this is a very small
number, and the contribution to the error
is small.
I'm already in good shape.
My predictions are right.
However, if the sign is different-- if
I say this is very positive, and this
ends up being -1, or if this is very
negative and this ends up
being +1,
the end result is this will be
a positive exponential, and the error
will be huge.
And I need to do something, in
order to knock it down.
So indeed, this is very intuitive
under that interpretation, that
this would be an error measure
that I would be trying to minimize.
What is this error measure called?
It is called the cross-entropy error.
And I am putting it between quotation,
because the way to get it strictly to
be cross-entropy is to interpret
a binary event as if it was
a probability, but we will accept that.
It's universally referred to as
cross-entropy.
And we will call this the cross-entropy,
basically between
supposedly h and f.
Not really h and f, but h and
a particular realization of f.
So this is what we want to do.
Now we have defined the model,
and we have defined the error measure.
The remaining order is to do
the learning algorithm.
I know the error measure.
I just want to minimize it.
How can I do that?
It's an easy question.
If you look at logistic regression,
we have just developed the
error measure for it.
So now I have this function,
and I want to minimize it with
respect to w.
Let's look at a previously tackled case,
in order to see how we went about that.
Remember linear regression?
We also had an error function that
was derived directly. We just said
mean squared, and wrote it down.
We didn't have to go through
this long derivation.
But then the in-sample error
ended up being this.
Very similar to this, except here we
penalize the difference, squared.
Here, we penalize it according
to this cross-entropy thing.
Now in the case of linear regression, if
we want to minimize this, we found
a very simple way to do it, because we
found a closed-form solution for the
minimum, that was the pseudo-inverse,
the one-step learning.
Unfortunately here, we're
out of luck.
If you use the derivative here and you
try to solve it, it is exponential
and things will come out, and you
sum it up, and you cannot find
a closed-form solution.
Well, in the absence of a closed-form
solution, we usually go for
an iterative solution.
We're not going to go for
the solution directly.
We're going to improve, improve,
improve, improve.
Finally, we'll get the good solution.
This is not a foreign concept to us.
This is what we did with perceptions,
although we didn't explicitly do it at
the time in terms of a declared
error function.
We went and tried to improve one example
at a time, and kept repeating
until we got what we want.
So that's what we're
going to do here.
But here, we are going to do it based on
calculus, and the method that will
be used for minimization can be applied
to any error measure, even
nonlinear and so on, as long as
there's some smoothness constraint.
And it will be the one that will be
applied to neural networks next time.
Very famous one.
It's a very simplistic one.
And there are more sophisticated
versions of it.
It's called gradient descent.
Let's see what is there.
First, let me show you what the
error measure for logistic
regression looks like.
As you vary the weight, the value of
the error differs, but it has this
great property that it
has one minimum.
And otherwise, it goes like that.
A function that goes like that--
it's called convex.
And it goes with convex optimization,
which is very easy, because obviously
wherever you start, you will go to
the same valley.
You can imagine a more
sophisticated nonlinear surface,
where you do this and that.
And then depending on where you start,
if you're sliding down, you will end
up in one minimum or another.
There are other issues that arise, and
we will only tackle them when we need
them, when we talk about the error
measure for neural networks.
Right now, we have a very friendly
guy, so we're going to describe
gradient descent in terms
of this friendly guy.
So what do you do with
gradient descent?
First, we admit that it's a general
method for nonlinear optimization.
And what you do, you
start at a point--
initialization, pretty much
like you initialize the perception.
And then you take a step, and you
try to make an improvement
using that step.
The step is to take the step
along the steepest slope.
The steepest slope is not an easy
notion to see in two dimensions,
because I either go right or left.
There aren't too many directions.
So let's do the following.
Let's say that I'm in
three dimensions.
And in this room, I have a very
nonlinear surface, going up and down,
up and down.
I'm going to assume one thing, that
it's twice differentiable.
That's what you need to invoke
gradient descent.
You can think of hills
and this and that.
Now I'm trying to get to the
minimum of that surface.
First thing to remember in optimization,
you don't get to see the
surface.
You don't have a bird's eye
view and you look at it--
That region looks good.
Let's go there.
That doesn't happen.
You only have local information
at the point you evaluated.
So the best thing to imagine is that
you are sitting on the surface, and
then you close your eyes.
And all you do is feel around you, and
then decide this is a more promising
direction than this.
That's all you do at one step.
And then when you go to the new point,
repeat, repeat, repeat until
you get to the minimum.
These are all the iterative method
that you're going to use.
So we go back, and we start at w(0).
And then we look at
a fixed step size.
I am at a point.
I am going to move in w space, by
a certain amount, and I'm going to take
it to be fixed and small.
The reason I'm doing that is because I
am going to apply local approximations
based on calculus, Taylor series.
And I know that this will apply well
if the move is not that big.
If I go very far, the higher-order terms
kick in, and I'm not sure that
the conclusion that I got locally will
apply if I just get a 1st order, or
a 2nd order as in the other methods.
So for the fixed step size, I'm going to
say, I'm moving in the w space.
I'm moving by a unit vector v.
v hat is a unit vector.
So this tells me just the direction.
Should I go this way, that way?
If I'm doing the sensing--
oh, this is steep, so I'm
going to go this way.
The unit vector in this direction
would be my v hat.
And I'm going to modulate the amount
of move by a step size, which I'm
going to call eta.
So this is the amount of move.
The only unknown I have is what is v.
I already decided on the size, but
I want to know which direction
to go.
And the formula would be: the next
weight, which is w(1), will be the
current weight plus the move.
And I already decided on the move.
So now under this condition, you're
trying to derive what is v hat?
That's the direction.
If you solve for it with one method
or another, that gives
you gradient descent.
In another method, it will give you
conjugate gradient, which has
2nd-order stuff in it, and so on.
So that is always the question.
Let's actually try to solve for it.
We said that we are going to go
into the direction of the steepest
descent, so we are really talking
about change in the
value of the error.
The change of the value of the error,
if I move from w(0) to w(1) would
be E_in at some point minus
E_in at another point.
Which two points?
It's w(0) and w(1).
That is OK.
If I decide to move to this guy,
this is the amount.
What I want to do, I want
this guy to be negative--
as negative as possible because
I want to go down,
by the proper choice of w(1).
But w(1) is not free.
It's dictated by the method, and it has
the very specific form that it is
the original guy plus the move I made.
So this is what I would like to make.
I would like to make this
as small as possible.
Now if I can write this down using
the Taylor series expansion with one
term, this is E of the original point
plus a move, minus the original point.
That will also be the derivative
times the difference, right?
So the derivative times the difference
here will be the gradient transposed
times the vector times eta.
And I just took eta outside
here, to make it here.
So this would be the move
according to the 1st-order
approximation of the surface.
If the surface was linear, this
would be exact, but the
surface is not linear.
And therefore, I have other terms
which are of the order
eta squared and up.
And the assumption for gradient descent
is that I'm going to neglect
this fellow, as if it
didn't exist.
When you go to conjugate gradient, you
will have the second guy, and you
will neglect the third.
And you can see the idea.
So now, how do I chose the direction
in order to make this
as negative as possible?
By simple observation, I realize
that this quantity, for any
choice of v hat, will be greater than
or equal to this fellow.
This guy is gone, right?
I'm only dealing with this guy.
So I'm taking the inner product
between a vector and
a unit vector.
The unit vector could be aligned with
that vector, or could be opposed
to that vector, or could be orthogonal
to that vector, but it doesn't
contribute magnitude.
Its magnitude is 1.
The most I can get is the norm of
this, and the least I can get is
negative the norm of this,
if they are opposed.
So this would be the least I can get,
and I inherit eta from here.
This will be true for
any choice of v hat.
Knowing that, if I choose the v hat
that achieves this, this will be my v hat,
because it gives me the most negative
value that I can get.
Not that difficult to do, because
this is a unit vector, so I'm
trying to get it.
Clearly what I want is a unit vector
opposed to the original guy.
So I end up with this fellow,
the formula for it.
The formula for it, I am getting
minus the gradient.
But this is a unit vector, and therefore
I have to normalize by that
in order to make it a unit vector.
So that's the solution.
And you can see now why it's called
gradient descent, because you descend
along the gradient of your error.
Now we have said it's a fixed
size, and that was a way for us to
make sure that the linear
approximation holds.
We're going to modulate
eta.
But you can see that there's
a compromise.
I can get close-to-perfect
approximation for linear, by taking the
size to be very small, but then
it will take me forever
to get to the minimum.
I will be moving [MAKING NOISES]
et cetera, or I could be taking bigger
step, which looks very promising.
But then, the linear approximation
may not apply.
So there is a compromise.
Let's look at how eta
affects the algorithm.
This is the case I talked about.
If eta is very small, you will get
there, but it will take you forever.
And in optimization, it's
a very simple game.
I charge you for two things:
the value you arrived at, and how
long it took you to get there.
I don't care how you do it.
Don't bother me.
If you gave me a beautiful thing-- I'm
computing the Hessian and taking the
inverse of it--
that's your business.
All I care about is how long it took you
to do that, and what is the value
you're going to deliver.
So just by this, this is not good,
because it took me forever.
Now I go to the other extreme and make
eta large, and all of sudden, I am
really doing this.
You can even do worse.
Let's say that eta is really large.
You start here, and our
next step is here.
You end up with the error
surface being up there.
So you went up instead of down,
obviously because the 2nd order and
3rd order dominate that.
So that is not good.
Pointer? OK.
If you look at it, you realize that,
the best compromise is to
have initially a large eta, because the
thing is very steep, and I want to
take advantage of it, and just become
more careful when I'm closer to the
minimum so that I don't bounce.
So a rule of thumb--
it's not like a mathematically
proved thing, it's
an observation in surfaces.
It looks like a very good idea,
instead of having a fixed step, to have
eta increase with the slope.
If I'm in a very high slope, I just go
a lot because I'm doing that.
And then, if I'm now close to the
minimum, I'd better be careful in order
not to miss the minimum and overshoot.
And because of this, here is an easy
implementation of this idea.
Instead of taking the direction,
which will not change--
here's the direction, and we're
going to eta, and this is
the formula for it.
This is what we have for fixed size.
Now, I'm going to try to make eta
proportional to the size of the
gradient, so it's bigger when
the slope is bigger.
That's very convenient, because
I have here the size of the
gradient sitting there.
So if I make eta proportional to the
size of our gradient, something
will nicely cancel out, and then
I will get another eta--
purple eta, which is the new constant.
And this guy completely canceled out,
and I have a very simple formula.
Now it's not a fixed step anymore, but
a fixed learning rate, eta now being
the learning rate.
You just compute the gradient, and use
that learning rate, and that will
take care of the previous
observation.
So that's what we have.
That's all I'm going to say about
gradient descent for this case.
And then we're going to go to the more
complicated issues of it, when we talk
about neural networks next time.
So this is how to minimize.
And now we have the logistic regression
algorithm, written in language.
You iterate, you start
by initializing at w(0).
You iterate for every step.
What do you do?
You compute the gradient.
How do I do that?
Oh, I have a formula for
the in-sample error.
All I need to do is to
differentiate it.
Differentiating it will not be difficult.
You're going to get this--
you can verify it.
And now, you are going to take the next
weight to be the current weight
minus your learning rate
times the gradient.
That's the formula we had.
And then, you go to the next iteration,
next iteration, until it's
time to stop.
And then we return
the final weight.
That is the algorithm.
Now let me spend two minutes
summarizing all the linear models in
one slide, and then we will be done
completely with that model.
We had three models, right?
We had the perceptron--
linear classification.
We had linear regression.
And we today added logistic
regression.
Let's take one application domain, which
is credit, and see how each of
them contributes.
We have credit analysis.
If you apply each of these to credit
analysis, what type of thing do
you implement?
For the linear classification, the
perceptron, you accept or deny. That
was our very first example, right?
If you use linear regression, you are
trying to decide the credit line.
We have seen that example as well.
If you're applying logistic regression,
you are computing the
probability of default-- just the
reliability, and then let the bank
decide what to do with it.
So this is from an application domain.
Let's look from tools point of view.
They had different error measures.
The perceptron had the binary
classification error, right?
Linear regression has squared error.
And finally, logistic regression
had cross-entropy error.
Different errors that had different
plausibility motivations to them.
And we have tackled all three of them.
And then there was the learning
algorithm that goes with them, that is
very dependent on the error
measure you choose.
For the case of the classification
error, which was a combinatorial
quantity, and we went for something like
the perceptron learning algorithm,
or the pocket version if the
thing is non-separable.
And there are other, more sophisticated
methods to do that.
How about squared error?
That was the easiest.
That was the one-step learning, where we
had the pseudo-inverse and you have
your solution.
And finally with the cross-entropy, we
had the gradient descent, which is
a very general method.
All we needed to do is that it's
a twice differentiable surface, and we
are ready to go with that.
And this was particularly friendly
because it happens to be convex, so it
avoids a lot of the traps that we will
see next time when we talk about
neural networks.
I'll stop here.
And then we will continue
after the short break.
Let's start the Q&amp;A.
MODERATOR: The first question is,
for the algorithm, the termination
time means the error does not change, or
what criterion do you usually use?
PROFESSOR: When I discuss
gradient descent, there are several
aspects to the algorithm that
need to be discussed.
There is the question of
the learning rate.
And this is what I focused on today,
because it's the most relevant to the
particular application, which
is logistic regression.
That has a very good-behaving one.
There are other questions.
One of them is the initialization.
For example, if you look at the top
here, I said set it to w(0).
What is w(0)?
How do I initialize?
That's a question.
It's not critical in logistic
regression.
If you initialize it to 0,
this will be fine.
And if you think, initializing it to 0
means that you initialize the probability
to a half, the most uncertainty about
any example before you learn anything.
So it looks like a reasonable
thing to start.
Then also, there is a question
of termination.
And termination is an issue here, but
it's less of an issue here than in
other cases, because of a reason
that I'm going to explain.
But in general, the termination
is tricky, and you have
a combination of criteria.
So what do I want?
I want to minimize the error.
So one of them is to say, if the
thing gets flat and flat to
the level where, when I move from one point
to another, I'm not really making
a lot of improvement, then I must
be close to the minimum and
should stop.
That turns out to be OK,
may be reasonable.
But sometimes--
not in the convex case-- but sometimes
you have a surface like this-- it goes
down, and then flattens,
and then goes down.
So if you do this criterion by itself,
you may stop prematurely.
And you may think this
is pathological.
It happens more often than you think.
So now you say, let me set a target
error. That is, not only that the
changes are small, but also if I didn't
get to the target error that I
want, I'm not going to stop.
Now that will get you over this hump,
until you get to the other guy,
and maybe that will achieve
your target error.
That's very nice, except for the problem
that if your target error
is not achievable, you will
continue forever.
So you patch this up and say, I'm
going to have a limit on the number of
iterations anyway.
I'm going to do this for
10,000 epochs,
regardless of what happens, and
then I'm going to stop.
In practice, some combination
of the above works.
But the main thing here is that termination,
as a properly analyzed thing, is a bit
tricky because of so many unknowns
in the error surface that
we are dealing with.
But it is something that will become
more of an issue in neural networks
than it is here.
And then another issue in gradient
descent, that I didn't talk about, is
the question of local minima
versus global minima.
When you do gradient descent, I said
you close your eyes, and you
roll down the surface.
And then when you get to the minimum,
you know you are at a minimum.
If you have a surface that goes like
this, then goes up, and then goes down
to a better minimum.
If you start at the original
one, you can go, go, go.
Once you get to that minimum, you have
absolutely no reason to leave,
according to the prescription of the
gradient descent, because you will be
going up a hill, and that looks
like a bad idea.
So you will be in a local minimum,
rather than a global minimum.
I didn't mention it this time, again
because I have a convex function,
so there's only one.
You will get there, and
everybody is happy.
When we get to neural networks,
this is an issue, and this should be
addressed.
So the short answer to the question:
termination is tricky.
A combination of criteria
is the best way.
And my coverage of gradient descent,
this one, only covers a part of it that
is most relevant to logistic
regression.
And the rest of the story will come up
when we talk about neural networks.
MODERATOR: There are questions about
why was gradient descent
picked? Isn't it usually very slow--
a slow method for convergence?
PROFESSOR: Think of it this way.
If I can see the surface, I obviously
can go for the minimum directly.
But I'm doing something here that
depends on 1st order.
Let's say that you're playing golf.
You want to get to the hole.
That's your minimum.
Gradient descent would be doing this--
take this, and just this one--
Nobody in their right
mind would do that.
When you go to the 2nd-order thing,
what you are doing actually-- your
first guy is a swing.
You may not land exactly at the
hole, but you will land close.
You have a 2nd-order approximation of
the surface, and you get close.
And then you try to get there.
Having said that, it is a remarkably
efficient algorithm to use, especially
the stochastic version of it--
gradient descent, that is.
That is, in many applications, you just
apply gradient descent in a very
simple way, and you often get
very, very good result.
And conjugate gradient, which is
the king of the derivative
based methods, is a very
attractive one.
And in some optimizations, it completely
trumps the alternatives.
On the other hand, in many ways, the
stochastic version of this, and the
simplicity of it, makes it the
algorithm of choice in many
applications.
MODERATOR: Although it's not the case for
this error function, what happens
for gradient descent if there
are local minima?
PROFESSOR: If there are local
minima, and you're applying the
algorithm faithfully, you are going to
get to the nearest local minimum to
where you started.
There is a huge amount of research
in optimization about local minima,
and how to do it, and there are
algorithms right and left.
From a practical point of view,
here is my experience.
Let's say I'm using neural networks, and
the local minima are abundant in
neural networks, and therefore
it looks, on face value,
like a serious problem.
If all you do is, do the learning
a number of times starting from
different initial conditions--
that is, do a session starting from
this point, do another session
starting for this point, et cetera.
So each of them will go to its
nearest local minimum.
If you do this enough times--
I'm not talking a million times.
Even a hundred times.
And then after all of these sessions,
you pick the one that gave you the
best minimum, and you know the best
minimum by evaluating the error which
is accessible to you.
That usually gets you what you want.
It will not get you the
global minimum.
Formally, you can prove that
getting to the global
minimum is NP-hard.
If you insist on getting to it in
every case, this is simply not
tractable in terms of
computational time.
But some very simple heuristic, as just
repeating from different points and
then picking the best, works actually
pretty good in most of the cases that
I've seen.
And if this becomes a real issue in your
application, there is no shortage of
methods in optimization that explicitly
deal with local minima.
The only thing to remember is that
avoiding local minima, versus not
avoiding them, has almost
nothing to do with the
order of your algorithm.
I could be using 1st order, 2nd order,
et cetera, and all of them will
be very happy when you get to the
minimum, even if it's local.
So this is an added layer that will make
you, in spite of the fact that
you are at the minimum,
you explore further.
Sometimes you have a temperature, and
you escape the local minimum to
a better one if it's a shallow
local minimum.
And there are others that
deliberately look for that.
So if your application calls for it,
there will be methods to help.
But there will be no method to actually
solve your problem, because
the problem is NP-hard.
MODERATOR: Can you quickly explain what
the stochastic gradient descent is?
PROFESSOR: I will do that at
the beginning of the next lecture.
It's basically, instead of taking the
whole training set at once, you take
one example at a time.
But I'll do that, because that will be
the part that is applicable to neural
networks in general.
MODERATOR: Can you explain a little
bit more the notion of cross-entropy?
PROFESSOR: The formal
definition of cross-entropy--
so entropy, you get a function based on
a probability, and it's basically
the expected value of logarithm
1 over the probability.
That will be your classical
definition of an entropy.
When you have two different
probabilities, you can get
a cross-entropy between them, by getting
the expected value with one-- the
expected value of, and you take a ratio
of them one way or the other.
And there are a number of them in the
literature, that have different
definitions and different scopes.
But basically, you are getting
a relationship between two probability
distributions, using a logarithmic,
and expected values.
That's the common thread.
The reason why I put this between
quotation is that, you really are
getting the cross-entropy between the
h that you're trying to learn, and
a binary event, so something like
a probability 1 or 0 at a time.
So it's a little bit of a loose thing,
because that's the way it's defined.
But again, it is referred
to as cross-entropy.
MODERATOR: A question is, why
a method like binary search wouldn't
work to find minima quickly?
PROFESSOR: OK.
Binary search works well once you
decide on the direction.
I am in a space, and you think of
binary search, that's very nice.
Let's talk about 1000 dimensional
space.
Where do I move?
If you decide on a direction, and
you say that it's very good to go
along this direction, then it
becomes a legitimate question.
That's the direction.
How far should I go?
We used very crude method, like
using a fixed step, or maybe by
looking at it closely,
maybe it shouldn't really be fixed.
It should be proportional to
the gradient, so we had the
fixed learning rate.
But one can become more sophisticated
and say, let me explore that
direction until I get to the minimum
along this direction.
And then there are binary search
methods for doing that.
Again, when you judge one method versus
the other in optimization, don't
be excited about the sophisticated
method, because you will be charged
for it.
If I have to evaluate a lot of
stuff, I have to show for it that I
got to a much better value.
If I evaluate many more values, and get
that much of a difference, then I
lose in the optimization game, because
I used CPU cycles, and I didn't
improve the error as much.
So whenever you are looking at a method,
it's a very practical question
whether it will work or not.
For example, 2nd-order methods.
Hands down, approximating the surface
as a 2nd order is better than the
1st order.
And the problem, why don't we do this?
Because if you approximate it as
2nd order, you have to compute the
2nd-order derivatives.
And that's a full matrix
called Hessian.
If I do that outright, I will get
a better minimum, and I will get it
quickly in terms of the number
of steps, but each step
becomes very expensive.
And conjugate gradient, that I mentioned
very quickly, is a way to do
the 2nd order without actually
explicitly computing the
Hessian, which is effective and
that's why it's a famous method.
So it is used, but be careful
where to use it.
MODERATOR: Can logistic regression be
applied for a multi-class setting?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Let's look at the full--
Now this is the linear model
as we covered it.
On the other hand, if you see
what type of functions
am I getting?
I seem to be getting either binary,
real-valued, or bounded real-valued,
specifically probability.
There are obviously other classes, but
in many cases, the other classes can be
derived in terms of those.
Let's look at, for example,
the multi-class, the thing
being asked about.
Remember recognizing the
digits, that we talked about.
How many digits did we have?
We had 10 digits--
0, 1, 2, up to 9 in the ZIP codes.
And we wanted to be able
to classify them.
What did we do for that?
We used perceptron.
Wait a minute, perceptron
does a binary thing.
How did we do that?
We did what we usually do for
multi-class problems.
Instead of taking 1 versus 2 versus 3
versus 4, et cetera, we either take
one versus one--
one class versus another class.
Like the 1 versus 5, and
2 versus 3, et cetera, and
then combine the decisions.
Or sometimes, you do one versus all.
So I want to recognize 1 from the rest,
2 from the rest, 3 from the
rest, et cetera.
And there are other methods.
So many of the multi-class approaches
deal with a tree, based on binary
decisions, and that is the
way it is applied.
But there are some others which--
ordinal regression, for example, where
there is a specific order to them,
it is dealt with differently.
So there are modifications to these guys
that accommodate other methods,
the easiest of which is multi-class,
because it's ready for us, and we have
seen an example of it.
MODERATOR: What other sigmoid functions
that can be used instead of that?
PROFESSOR: We will
use one next time.
I'm glad you asked.
So the logistic function
is between 0 and 1.
We are going to use the tanh
which will be between
-1 and +1.
And that will be the neuronal function
in neural networks next time.
And at that time, I will discuss it
a little bit, so you get a feel for it.
But it's also based on exponential-- the
tanh has an exponential in it.
It's very close to the sigmoid.
There is a scale and shift.
On the other hand, you can
use other functions.
It turns out that, from an analytic
point of view, using the exponential
based soft thresholds has
advantages, as we see.
So we got a number
of advantages here--
a simple formula for the error.
And also, the error measure that
resulted from it was convex.
That may not be guaranteed in every
choice, so therefore, there is
a criterion for choice.
It's not just a good-looking formula.
It's a formula that will go through
the chain of the processes that we go
through when we do the learning.
MODERATOR: There's a conceptual
question about how is eta derived?
It's not really derived.
PROFESSOR: The learning rate?
MODERATOR: Yeah.
PROFESSOR: The way I described it, I got the
zeroth order, which is fixed eta-- fixed step.
And then I got the 1st order, which
is to make the step proportional to
the gradient.
And then you got the fixed
the learning rate.
You can take that and make it more
sophisticated, and you have
an adaptive learning grade.
It's a very simple heuristic, that
you take a learning rate and
you do a step.
And if the step is successful, you
say maybe I can afford a bigger
learning rate, so you increase
the learning rate.
And you keep doing that until you hit
a point where-- oh, I actually used too
big a learning rate, because after
doing my minimization in one step, I
ended up with a bigger value,
so obviously I went too far.
And in that case, you shrink
the learning rate.
So you can do this adaptively.
And it does buy you time.
There are lots of heuristics that are
add-on's to the plain-vanilla gradient
descent, and one of them has to
do with the learning rate.
When you go to conjugate gradient,
which is a 2nd-order one, because
there is a 2nd-order thing, you can
look at it eventually, and interpret
it as if it was having a principled
direction, and
a principled learning rate.
This is one way to look at it.
But for the gradient descent, it's
really a heuristic that will choose
the learning rate.
I have a rule for it.
I'll mention it as a rule of thumb.
There are certain values that
work in many cases.
And in the case of eta, there is
a particular value that works.
I'm going to mention it.
But again, this is just a practical
observation, and other people may have
different experience.
MODERATOR: Going back to the first
part of the lecture, and a few
lectures back, you made the example of
character recognition, and you chose
features like symmetry and I don't
remember something else.
But how much are you charged in terms
of d_VC for getting those features?
PROFESSOR: I'm glad
this question was asked.
This was the nonlinear transformation.
And we called the space Z the feature
space, and these guys are features.
And there are basically
two types of features.
Here, I'm trying to find just
generically more sophisticated
surface, because I realize that the
points will not be linearly separable.
so I cannot do it here.
And the other one is along the lines we
started with, which are meaningful
features, like symmetry in the case
of the digits, and in the
case of, let's say, years
in residence--
if you want this as an input to the
credit, you may not want it as
a linear thing, but you say: am
I bigger than five years or
less than five years?
So those are meaningful features.
The key distinction you need to
make in your mind is that, did I
choose the feature by understanding
the problem, or did I choose the
feature by looking at the specific
data set that was given to me?
The latter is the problem.
If I look at the data and then choose
features, then I am doing the learning
myself-- at least the first stage of it--
and therefore, I have a bigger
hypothesis set than what I'm
going to end up with.
And therefore, as I said, the VC
warranty is forfeited in this case.
If you look at the problem, and then
derive features that are meaningful,
but that's not depending on the data set
that you're going to learn from--
depending on general understanding.
We look at the credit.
Looks like years in residence are fine,
but I don't think it's just
proportional to these guys,
without looking at data.
I think the thresholds are five years
for stability, less than one year for
not so much stability, and so on.
So I'm going to derive those.
You're absolutely charged
nothing for doing that.
More power to you.
You may have helped the learning
algorithm by taking properties of the
learning problem that you're working
on, and got a better representation
for it. And this is an art-- purely
an art, and it depends on
the application domain.
The thing I warned about, very explicitly,
is to try to derive
features from looking at the data.
And the warning is not absolute.
Try do derive features based on the
data, and still think that the final
hypothesis set you ended up with
is what will dictate the
generalization behavior.
That is where the fallacy lies.
MODERATOR: There's a question.
Is it possible to choose parameters
automatically?
I'm guessing they're referring
to the learning rate.
PROFESSOR: OK--
MODERATOR: Oh, no wait, sorry.
They corrected it.
How to select the features
automatically, so it's back to--
PROFESSOR: It's selected
automatically, that's what
we are in business for.
It's machine learning.
Things are automatic.
But then, this becomes
part of learning.
Now here, we had an explicit
nonlinear transformation.
When we go to neural networks, we'll
find out that they choose
features automatically.
But that is part of learning,
and you are charged for it
in terms of VC dimension.
So probably, the question will be
better answered and understood in the
context when I talk about neural networks
and hidden layers, and then
we'll see what that means.
MODERATOR: I think that's it.
PROFESSOR: Very good.
Then we'll see you on Thursday.