ANNOUNCER: The following program
is brought to you by Caltech.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Welcome back.
Last time, we talked about
linear models.
And linear models share what we
would refer to as the signal,
which is this formula.
It's a linear sum involving the input
variables and weights, that can be put
in vector form.
And all linear models, in one form or
another, have that as their basic
building block.
And you can have a classification linear
system, like the perceptron,
that uses that signal and takes the
sign of it to make a decision,
+1 or -1.
Or you can take something like
regression, which is real-valued, that
takes the signal as it is
and has that as output.
We looked at the linear regression
algorithm, which was a particularly
easy algorithm.
All it does, it takes the inputs and
puts them in a particular matrix form,
and so the outputs. That's the inputs
and outputs of the data set.
And then, by computing this very simple
formula, in one shot, it can
get you the optimal value
of the weight vector.
If you look at linear models, you can
think of them as an economy car.
They get you where you want to go, and
they don't consume a lot of gas.
You may not be very proud of them,
but they actually do the job.
If you want a luxury car, wait
until we get to support
vector machines.
And you have to pay the
price for that.
However, for linear models, it
is remarkable how often they
succeed on their own.
And they are sufficient to get
you the learning performance
that you want.
So I urge you to give linear models
in general more attention than you
would otherwise give.
And try to use them when you face
a learning problem first, and see if they
will actually achieve what you want.
To strengthen linear models even
further, we introduced nonlinear
transformation.
And the idea behind it is that the
signal is not only linear in x, which
is what you would think of as the reason
we call these linear systems.
But actually, they're linear
in w, the vector.
And the reason this is important is
because learning actually modifies w
in the learning process until it gets to
the optimal one, while x, which you
usually think of as a variable, is
actually a bunch of constants, which
are the data set that
are handed to you.
So the linearity in w
is the key point.
And if you take x and transform it in
any way you form to another vector z,
in a very nonlinear way if you want,
this will still preserve this
linearity, the linearity in w.
Obviously, it will not be linear in x.
And that's all that matters for you to
apply the machinery that we got
here, like the simple linear
regression algorithm.
And we took an example where we had the
two variables x_1 and x_2, and we
transformed them nonlinearly to
x_1 squared and x_2 squared.
And we found that this case, the
transformation helps us separate the
data, where if we worked in
the original space, we
would not be able to.
This time, I'm going to talk
about error and noise.
And these are practical considerations
that we have to take, when we consider
real-life problems.
And we're going to modify the learning
diagram that we have, by incorporating
the notion of error and
the notion of noise.
And I will do that for the
bulk of the lecture.
However, my starting point will be to
wrap up the nonlinear transformation
that we started last time.
So let's look at what
we had last time.
We had this space.
Let me magnify it a little bit.
This space is the original X space.
And the origin is in the middle.
And you have these points,
which are your data set.
And each point belongs to that space.
And as you realize, there is really no
way of separating the blue from the
red using a line, which is
what linear models do.
And the idea for us was: let's
do a nonlinear transformation.
We called it phi.
And if you look at what happened here--
let's look at both of them at
the same time--
this is where you took x_1 squared.
So this is x_1, and this is x_2.
And that transformation
here was x_1 squared.
So this would be x_1 squared, and this
is x2 squared, which we're going
to label as z.
So the transformation is you take every
point in the sample space x_n,
you put it through a transformation
phi, and you get the
corresponding point z_n.
And now, you are working in the feature
space, or the nonlinear space
Z.
When we did this, we realized that a data
set like this can become linearly
separable in the new space.
And that allows us to apply the
linear model algorithm here.
And when you do that, you will get
a separating boundary here.
And that separating boundary is applied
by applying your simple linear
model, like linear regression-- in this
case, linear classification, the
perceptron--
to the data in the Z space.
So that's what we get.
But we are not working in the Z space.
When I give you a test
point, it will be x.
And you have managed to separate
things in the Z space.
Well, the way you do it is you
go back to the input space.
And as you realize, I'm
using the "inverse",
between quotation,
transformation.
Because the transformation, in principle,
may not have an inverse.
There are some points in the Z space
that may not be a mapping of any point
in X, and some points in the Z space
which may be the mapping of
more than one point.
And therefore, in spite of the fact that
phi is a mapping, a function,
phi -1, as we call it, is not.
But when you apply this, figuratively,
what you're going to get is
a separating surface in the X
space, that is not linear.
And that was obtained by applying
purely linear methods.
And therefore, you can classify a new
point by applying g of x, which would
be the hypothesis that's defined here,
the linear one, which happens to have
that formula.
So you look at the diagram
all together.
And this is basically the cycle you have,
when you're doing the nonlinear
transformation.
You take the data set, transform it,
classify it, and interpret it.
In reality, when you get the new x, what
you're going to do, you are going
to take the new x, wherever
it might be.
You're going to transform it.
And then look here where it lies,
and classify it accordingly.
It's a very simple procedure.
And as you can see, although we are
illustrating it here in a case where
you're going from two-dimensional
to two-dimensional, you could in
principle go from two-dimensional to 100
dimensional, with highly nonlinear
coordinates, and the same
principle will apply.
You will be classifying here, with
a hyperplane in that case.
And then, this surface would
be very, very complicated--
could be completely jagged
and whatnot.
And that enables you to implement
a lot of sophisticated surfaces.
So let's look at the nonlinear
transformation and ask ourselves, what
transforms to what, to make sure
that all the notions are clear.
The first thing is the input point x.
This is a single point that is
represented by its coordinates x_1 up
to x_d, together with the mandatory
constant x_0 which equals 1 that
takes care of the threshold term.
This is a general representation
of a point in the X space.
What does this transform to?
I'd like you to think before
I give the answer.
Well, it transforms to a z.
That is a vector.
Each of these coordinates,
let's say, z_1,
is a nonlinear function, potentially
nonlinear function, of all of the x's,
so of the entire vector x.
For example, this could
be x_1 x_2 e to the x_3.
The next one would be 1 over
x_2 times x_3 cubed.
Whatever it is.
And you can go on and on and on,
and there is really no limit.
So if we thought of linear methods
here as an economy car,
this could be a truck.
This could be actually an 18-wheeler.
And we must be proud of that, because
with such a simple method, we are able
to create such a strong machine.
But be careful, because you may
not be able to drive it.
And if you do the wrong transformation,
you will end up crashing--
in this case, generalization-wise
crashing.
That is, although you did everything
right, and you did this
transformation, and this is a powerful
machine, you don't know how to drive
the powerful machine, and you end up
with very poor generalization.
And we need the theory in order to get
our driver's license. That will tell us
what to do in order to be able
to drive this machine.
So that is x.
Now, what do x_1 up to x_N go to?
Remember, this is the data set,
the inputs of the data set.
Each of these guys, by itself, is a full
vector x that has all of these
coordinates.
So this is the data set we have.
What does it transform to?
Not surprisingly, z_1 up to z_N.
So you end up with the same
number of points.
That is obvious.
And each of them is a vector.
And each vector can be very
long, according to the
transformation you chose.
Next one--
the labels.
The data set comes with inputs
and outputs, right?
So the inputs I did
the transformation--
what do y_1 up to y_N transform to?
Well, they transform to y_1 up to y_N.
These are untouched.
These are the values.
They are not touched.
And these are the ones we learn.
If it's classification, they are +1
or -1, exactly the same way
they were there before.
How about the weights?
When we use linear models,
we have a weight vector.
So when we are in the X space here,
what are the weights?
The answer is that there are no weights
in the X space when you do
a nonlinear transformation.
The weights are done in the Z space.
And I labeled the weights
here as w tilde.
And I'm using tilde as nonlinear,
so that you remember
it's a nonlinear space.
And everything here is tilde.
So this is w tilde.
And if you look here
at the dimension--
you may have not seen it.
Let me magnify it.
The dimensionality here
is also d tilde.
So whenever we need to distinguish
between z and x, we will add tilde to
the z counterpart, so that you are not
confused about which is which.
So we have those weights.
And finally, you ask yourself:
I've done all of this machinery.
Could you please tell me, what
is the hypothesis that I'm
delivering to my customer?
We're still calling it g of
x, the final hypothesis of
your learning process.
And it happens to be exactly the
same way, except in Z space.
You take the linear form here, and
take the sign, and that would be your
hypothesis.
Except it's a little bit annoying,
because this is g of x, and you're
telling me this is w tilde transposed
times z.
Where is x?
Don't worry. Here is x.
What z is, is the transformation of x.
When you want to evaluate this for
any x, all you need to do is plug into
this formula, and you are ready to go.
That's the entire story of the
nonlinear transformation.
Now, with that out of the way, let's go
to the main topic of the day, which
are error measures and noisy targets.
When we face a real learning problem,
we will realize that there
are components, practical components in
real life, that we have not fully
taken into consideration.
And what I'm going to do, I'm going to
take the learning diagram, which we
introduced in the first lecture.
And then, I'm going to adjust it
according to these practical components,
until we get the final general form of
the supervised learning diagram.
That will take us through both topics,
which are the error measures and the
noisy targets.
Here is the learning diagram in
case you forgot what it was.
That's where we left it.
Let's see what it looks like.
Remember, it's a pretty
simple diagram.
And we built it from scratch.
I need to rebuild it, in order for
you to realize that I'm not just
flashing a jungle on you.
It has a sense.
This is what we're trying to learn.
It's an unknown target function,
represented to
us by training examples.
We have a learning algorithm that will
take these examples and produce the
final hypothesis.
All of this is nice.
We said that the learning algorithm
is picking the hypothesis from the
hypothesis set.
And we said that this is a convenient
technicality that has no loss of
generality.
So we accepted that we will always
have a hypothesis set.
And then, we went into the
feasibility of learning.
And we realized that for that to
happen, we need to introduce
a probability distribution on X, any
probability distribution, and generate
the points x_1 up to x_N, which constitute
the inputs to the training
examples, using this probability
distribution independently.
Once you do that, you get the
benefit of Hoeffding.
And you can make a statement that
you're going to do something
out-of-sample that is reflected
by the in-sample.
That's where we stood.
So this is the diagram we are going
to be modifying piece by piece.
Let's talk about error measures,
the first notion.
Error measures try to answer
the following question:
what does it mean for h
to approximate f?
You have two functions.
And you say, this is a good
approximation, this is a bad
approximation.
Is it a qualitative statement,
or is it quantitative?
It is quantitative.
And because it's quantitative, we are
going to define an error measure that
measures how well, or how
badly, h approximates f.
So the error measure will
be defined as E of two guys.
And these will be h and f.
It returns a number for any
two functions you plug in.
One of them will be the
target function.
One of them will be a hypothesis
of interest.
And you ask yourself, how well, or
how badly in this case, does
h approximate f?
And you get an error.
If the error is 0, then h perfectly
reflects f, and you're home free.
If there's an error, then maybe you need
to look for another h that has
smaller error.
So that formalizes the question of
search, of the learning algorithm, into
minimizing an error function.
We call it error function.
And we call this error measure. It is
neither a measure in the measure
theoretic sense, or a function--
this is actually a functional.
But we are not worrying about that.
We just take these objects
and return a number.
And we refer to it as a function.
And we talk about error measure in the
sense of the English word "measure",
not the mathematical "measure".
So the error function, in principle,
returns a number
for a pair of functions.
But it is almost always defined
in terms of difference on
a particular point.
And then, you put these
points together.
That's the pointwise definition.
In this case, you define a small e
that goes with a capital E that also
takes two arguments.
And these two arguments are the value
of h at a particular point, and the
value of f at the same point.
That makes sense.
I'm trying to compare functions.
I want them to be the same
on the same point.
Therefore, if I compare them for every
point this way, then I will get
something meaningful.
And then, I will need to do something
about the different e's, small e's,
that will get me the big E.
Although this is not strictly
required by the definition-- you could
have a crazy error function that does
not reduce to corresponding points.
But invariably, this is what
you're going to do.
Have we seen this before?
Yes, we have.
Remember the squared error?
How do we formalize it in this sense?
We can say that the error in this case
is h of x minus f of x squared.
That's what we did, and that is indeed
an error function that measures the
difference between the two.
And indeed, if the error is 0, it means
that h of x equals f of x, and
we have exactly what we want.
We also saw it before, although we
didn't explicitly talk about it in
those terms, when we talked
about binary error.
When we had perceptrons, every point
could be either right or wrong.
And that doesn't look like
a quantitative error function.
It's binary.
However, you can also put it
in those terms as follows.
We agreed this notion-- let
me magnify it for you.
This notation, which is the funny
bracket, means that you return 1 if
the statement enclosed here is true.
And you return 0 if it is false.
That's a standard notation.
So if you take this as your error
function, what will happen?
If h of x equals f of x, then this
statement is false, and you return 0.
So the error is 0, good.
And if this statement is
true, you return 1.
And indeed, in that case,
you're making an error.
So it's a binary error
because of this.
And if you take it as a formal error, and
do the rest of the development to
get the other one, the big E for the
global function, you will find that
this is exactly what we did when we were
talking about frequency of error
and probability of error.
That will become clear in a moment.
Now, let's move from
the pointwise--
you define it on one
point in the space--
to define the error function,
capital E, on the entire space.
The way it is done is that the
overall error, which has this
notation, will always be the average
of pointwise errors.
So you take these pointwise
errors and average them.
And all we need to do is articulate
what we mean by "average" in
order to get that.
So let's look at the in-sample error.
When we have the in-sample error,
this is the formula for it.
And now, you think of in-sample error as
the in-sample version of this.
Because now, we are going to use the
pointwise error that goes with that
error function, or that error measure,
in defining the in-sample error.
If you take a single point from your
training set, you would be having
n going from 1 to N, so one of them
generically is n.
And I'm putting it in red, because
that's what we are going to average
with respect to.
You compute this error measure
whatever it may be, squared error,
binary error, any other error
you can think of.
And now, you get the average.
And average in that case will be the
simple average, which is 1 over N over
that, over the sum.
This is indeed consistent with what
we thought of as the training error.
And if you go back to the binary error,
which is the funny error, and
you look at what this formula will
return, it will return exactly the
frequency of error in
the sample, correct?
Now let's go for
out-of-sample error.
Again, the out-of-sample error is
the out-of-sample version of this
error measure.
Now, in this case, the point is
a general point in the space.
So we are labeling it as x in general,
without any label.
This could be any point in the space
that is picked from
X, which is the input space.
And in order to get an average in that
case, what you do is you get the
expected value, in this case
with respect to x.
So that is the average for
the out-of-sample case.
And again, if you take the binary error,
and you take the expected value
of this, this would be identically the
probability of error overall.
And we are using the probability
distribution over the input space X, in
order to compute this quantity.
That's how we get from a definition
that you invoke on a single point, to
the in-sample and out-of-sample
versions.
Now let's revise the learning
diagram with this added component.
Here is the learning diagram.
There's nothing that changed here except
that now, this is the standard
color, because we already
got used to it.
The red stuff is the new stuff.
So you have here, and you want
to add the error measure.
I'd like you to think for a moment
what we are going to do.
We're going to do it in two steps.
The first one is to realize that
we are defining the error
measure on a point.
So here's the addition.
The addition is that in deciding whether
g is close to f, which is the
goal of learning, we test
this with a point x.
And the criterion for deciding whether g
of x is approximately the same as f
of x is our pointwise error measure.
Furthermore, this x is created
from the space using
something very specific.
And that is, it comes from the same
probability distribution.
It comes from the same probability
distribution that generated those
points.
This was implicit when we
talked about the bin.
mu was the probability distribution
in the bin.
And nu was the sample distribution
in the sample that you pick.
When you test the system that you
trained using a certain probability
distribution, I ask you to test it
with points drawn from the same
distribution.
That's the only requirement in order
to invoke Hoeffding, or the
counterparts of Hoeffding for more
elaborate type of functions.
Now, if you do that, then
you have the guarantee.
And it does make sense that
with the benign assumption
that P can be an unknown--
any probability distribution--
all you're asked to do in order to get
the guarantees that we talked about is:
use it to generate the examples, and
use it to test the hypothesis.
So that is what we have.
Now we come to the question--
I understand where the role is.
I'm going to define the error
measure on point by point.
I know how to move from a point to the
in-sample, on to the out-of-sample.
Now, we come to the crux
of the question.
How do I define the error measure?
What is the number that I should return
for h differing from f on
a particular point?
I will give you an example
to make the point.
And my example will be fingerprint
verification.
You declare yourself.
And you want to authenticate yourself.
So you put your finger, and the system
will decide whether it's you and
return +1, or it's an intruder
and return -1.
That's what the system does.
And we would like to see how to define
an error measure in this case.
There are two types of error
that you can make when you have
a system like this.
One of them is called
false accept.
I think it's self-explanatory.
False accept meaning that someone who
shouldn't be there was accepted, was
falsely accepted.
So the intruder got in.
That's an error.
The other type is false reject.
You, the owner of the system, the one
who paid for it, you put your finger,
and you are rejected.
And you're mad at them.
That's a false reject.
Now, in defining an error measure,
I'd like to get this case,
because there is a great intuition
about what is going on.
So if we can come up with a meaningful
error measure here, that captures
both the false accept and false reject,
we will have a handle on what
the error measures are all about.
So how do we penalize each type?
That's what you do.
When you give an error, you penalize
it such that the error is large.
So you move away from that hypothesis,
to get a better hypothesis that
doesn't penalize it as much.
Now, we can put it in
a matrix form.
This is the target.
This is the perfect system.
This returns +1 whenever it's you,
returns -1 whenever it's
an intruder.
That's our dream system.
We don't have that.
We're going to use machine
learning using examples.
And we are going to come
up with a hypothesis.
This may not be the
final hypothesis.
We are talking about a general
hypothesis here.
When it becomes the final hypothesis,
we are going to call it g.
So h could be +1 or -1.
And +1 means you are accepted,
or the person is accepted,
whoever he may be.
And -1 means they are rejected.
Now, let's try to put under the
four possibilities here what the
errors would be.
First, the easy one--
the diagonal corresponds to no error.
And I'm putting it in faint color,
because in that case, it's clear that
you're going to make zero error.
It's you, and you were accepted.
It's not you, and you were rejected.
That's fine.
What's interesting are these two.
So we need to get a number for the
false accept, which means it's
an intruder but they were accepted, or
the false reject, which means it's you
but you were rejected.
If I can come up with four numbers here,
two of which I already know,
then I have the answer.
The key message I'm conveying with this
discussion is that there is no
inherent merit to choosing one
error function over another.
It's not an analytic question.
It's an application-domain question.
And I'm going to argue for that.
Let's look at the error measure for
this problem, for the important
application of supermarkets.
What happens with supermarkets?
Well, supermarkets decide
to become fancy.
And when you go and you want the
discount for your special program, you
not only declare yourself, they
need to verify that it's you.
Because they have recently too many
people just claim any number to get
the discount.
They want to control it a little bit.
So on the checkout, you
identify yourself.
And then, you put your finger.
And then, the system will verify you or
decide that you're an intruder.
Now, given this application, let's try
to see false accepts and false rejects
and how to penalize them.
The false reject in this case
actually is costly.
Think of it this way.
You are a customer, you go out, and you
have this huge bag of stuff, $100
worth of stuff, and you think you're
an important customer to the
supermarket.
You put your finger, you are rejected.
You put your finger again, you're
rejected, put your finger again,
you're rejected.
You're embarrassed in front of the
entire queue, and in your mind, you
say, the heck with this supermarket.
I'm going to go to the competitor.
So when they have a false reject, they
run the risk of losing a customer--
customer gets annoyed.
False accept is not that
big of a deal.
Someone comes in and claims they're
you, and the system passes them.
What is the downside?
They got a discount.
OK, one more discount--
for business, it's not that important.
And furthermore, if you think about it,
that must be a very brave person.
Because they are an intruder, and they
left their fingerprint on the system.
That's part of the deal.
All to get a discount--
I think really they are in trouble.
So we really shouldn't penalize the
false positives that much, if that will
help us with the false negatives.
If you look at a matrix that
fits this situation, this
one qualifies.
I'm going to penalize false rejects.
That's not a question.
But I'm going to penalize
them just by 1.
When it comes to the other one,
which are the false accepts--
let me try again.
This is the false reject.
It's you, and you were rejected, and
you are penalized dearly.
And this one is the false accept.
It's not you, and you were accepted,
and therefore, you
give it less weight.
So this looks like a reasonable
matrix for that case.
Now, let's look at the
exact same system.
You are given training examples, you are
told that the target function is
fingerprint verification, and
you go about your machine
learning algorithm.
Now, one of them is for a supermarket.
And the other one is for the CIA.
Let's see the situation here.
Now, what is the CIA going
to use the system for?
It uses it for security--
identity verification, that you are
an authentic person authorized to do
something, could be entering
the building, could be
looking at a document.
So you put your fingerprint first.
Now, let's look at the false
accept and false reject.
You have to agree with me that false
accept in this case is an unmitigated
disaster.
Someone got authority to something that
they're not authorized in, and
national security is at stake.
That's a no-no.
False reject in this case
can be tolerated.
Why?
You are not a customer.
You are an employee.
It's you, but the system rejected you.
Just try again and
again and again.
Because you're paid to be here.
Just take the inconvenience and do
this, in order to save the false
accepts.
So in this case, it makes sense that
we are going to put the weights in
exactly the opposite way,
even more extreme.
And you will have a matrix
that looks like this.
If you are the wrong person, and you are
accepted, that's a false accept.
That's a huge penalty.
The other one, you put
a meager penalty.
If you're really cruel with your
employees, you put this 0.1 or 0.001,
and then have them really go for this
thing for 20 times until they're
accepted.
But in general, you can see that this
has to be a much bigger number than
this, whereas in the supermarket case,
this was a bigger number than that.
So the take-home lesson is that, when
you're dealing with a practical
learning problem, the error measure
should be specified by the user.
You are going to deliver
a system to them.
The system is not perfect.
They want the target function, and you
give them a hypothesis instead.
You should ask them, how much does it
cost you to use my imperfect system in
place of the perfect system?
That is their decision to make.
And if they articulate that as
a quantitative error function, this is
the error function you
should work with.
However, this does not always happen.
People may not have the formalization
that will capture the error measure
in reality.
And sometimes, they capture it, but
it's very difficult to optimize.
There are other considerations.
So now, what I'm going to talk about are
the alternatives to this approach.
And the alternatives are
a compromise.
They are very common and popular
compromises, and
people indulge on them.
I don't mind indulging on them, because
actually, there are some nice
properties to them.
But always remember, this
is a second choice.
If we knew what the error measure that
needs to be used by the user is, we
would use that.
So here are the two alternatives--
you don't have the user-specified
error measure.
Then, you resort to plausible measures,
measures that you can argue
analytically that they have merit.
Usually, the analytic argument starts
with an assumption that is usually
a loaded assumption.
And from there, the going
is very smooth.
But nonetheless, that is
in the absence of
a meritorious error measure,
we might as well resort to that.
We have seen example of that,
which is squared error.
If you look at squared error, you can
say that if the noise is Gaussian--
I didn't do that in the lecture,
but it's not
a difficult thing to imagine--
that the corresponding error measure in
this case would be squared error.
So that is the plausibility of it.
And you can take other cases, for
example, the binary error.
You can go and get cross-entropy type
of error corresponding to the binary
error and whatnot.
So these guys have an error measure
that goes with them.
The other approach is not to have
a plausible measure, but to have
a friendly measure. You are
not justifying that this is
a meritorious measure.
You're just using it because
it's easy to use.
And we have also seen that.
For example, we can get closed-form
solution if we choose a particular
error measure.
Linear regression comes to mind.
If you didn't use a squared error in
that case, you would not have gotten
the very easy formula that we started
the lecture with.
And also, even if you can't get
a closed-form solution, you might be
able to use optimization
that is favorable.
For example, the cross entropy that I
referred to ends up, in a case of
a linear model, the logistic regression,
being convex which means that
optimization is efficient.
In that case, you get a global
minimum and all of that.
So now, you resort to either
a conceptual appeal, the plausibility,
or practical appeal, which is
the friendly aspect, to
choose the error measure.
This is completely legitimate, because
in many cases, you're not going to
have the user-specified error measure.
Now, let us modify the learning
diagram once more to introduce the
error measure as we defined it.
So here is--
and I'd like to ask you to look at this
for maybe 15 seconds, and tell me
where you think the error measure
will fit in this diagram-- the
error measure itself.
What does it affect?
What does it take from?
What exactly--
I can put the error measure,
for example, here.
That's an option!
I can put it inside the unknown
target function.
What does the error have to do
with the target function?
So you can think, where
would it be?
It's not difficult to realize that
that's where it belongs.
It has two roles.
One of them is to evaluate
this statement.
This statement is qualitative.
The output, the final hypothesis,
approximates the target function.
This is what gives it a number.
This gives it a grade.
And you use the error measure to
quantify this approximate thing.
The other thing is that you have
to feed the error measure to
the learning algorithm.
Because what does the learning
algorithm do when you
have an error measure?
It minimizes the in-sample error,
let's say, in this case.
And the in-sample error depends
on your error measure.
If you're minimizing squared error,
that's different from minimizing
another type of error.
So the error measure feeds
into those two.
Now we go for the next guy, which
is the noisy targets--
new topic, another addition
to the learning diagram.
The noisy targets are actually
very important.
Because in reality, these are the only
types you're going to encounter in the
problems in life.
Very seldom, you get a very
clean target function.
The first statement is, the target
function is not always a function.
Why are we calling it target function
if it's not a function?
Well, function is a mathematical
notion.
You have to return a unique value
for every point in the domain.
That's what qualifies it
as a function.
We used it here a little
bit liberally.
So far, we dealt with it as if
it was really a function.
But let's take the example we started
with, the credit example.
You consider credit card approval, and
here is the historical record.
This is an input.
Isn't it possible that two identical
customers have these fields, and one
of them ended up being good credit,
and one of them ended
up being bad credit?
Sure-- this doesn't capture all
the information in the world.
There's information that is not given
that contributes noise, if you will.
And there are circumstances that the
people will go through that will make
it probabilistic whether they'll
be good credit or bad credit.
So we come to realize that
two identical customers,
in the sense that their input
representation is the same,
can have two different behaviors.
And having this-- this is one point
mapping to two values, so it is
not a function.
What do we do about that?
Well, we use a target distribution,
as in probability distribution.
So instead of having y equals f of x--
you tell me what x is, and I'm going
to tell you what the value
y is for sure.
You use a target distribution.
And the notation for that is
probability of y given x.
So again, it depends on x.
But its dependence is probabilistic.
Some y's are more likely than
others in this case.
Here, one y was possible, and the
rest were impossible.
Now, we make it a little bit
more accommodating.
Now, we have a target distribution
instead of a target function.
Let's follow it through.
x used to be generated by the input
probability distribution.
It will still be generated
by that distribution.
This is an artifact that we introduced
in order to get the benefit of the
Hoeffding-type inequalities.
Nothing has changed.
But what will change now is that, instead
of y being deterministic of x,
once you generate x, y is also
probabilistic-- generated by this
fellow.
So you can think now of x,y as a pair
being generated by the joint
distribution, which is P of x times
P of y given x, assuming
independence.
So in this case-- there's no assumption
of independence once
you put it this way.
But the assumption here is that the
P of y you are given is actually
conditional on x.
Now you get noisy targets.
What is the noisy target
in this case?
Well, a noisy target can be posed as
a deterministic target, like the one we
had before, plus noise.
This applies to any numerical
target function.
So if y is a real number, or binary, or
something numerical, you can always
pose the question of a target
distribution as if it was
a deterministic target function
proper, plus noise.
This is just a convenience, to show
you that this is not far from
what we have already.
And why is that?
Because if you define now a target
function to be the expected value-- the
conditional expected value of y given
x, that's a function.
Although P of y given x gives you
different values, you take the
expected value-- that's a number, and
you call this the value of the
function, f of x.
Then, whatever is left out,
you call the noise.
It's a nice trick.
You've got the bulk of it.
And then, you go here, and you
call the rest the noise.
And that is usually the
form it is given.
So you think that you are really
trying to learn the
target function still.
But there is this annoying noise, and
you're trying to make your algorithm
pick this pattern.
And there's nothing it can do
about the remaining noise,
which averages to 0.
Now, by the same token, there is
no loss of generality when we talk
about probability distributions.
If you actually have a proper function,
which happens once in a blue
moon, you can still pose this as
a probability distribution.
How do you do that?
You get here P of y given x.
And you define it to be identically 0
unless y equals f of x that you have
in mind.
So if we were talking about finite
domains, you put all the probability 1
on this value.
And you put the probability
0 for all other values.
If it happens to be continuous, which is
almost always the case, you put all
the mass on the point, you put a delta
function there, and you let the other
ones be identically 0.
In this case, the target function
is a probability distribution.
Therefore, if we decide that the target
is always a distribution, there
is no loss of generality.
Now, let's do the final installment
of the learning diagram.
Once we are done with this,
we will freeze it forever.
This will be the general learning
diagram for supervised learning.
And here is what we have.
We're going to include the
noisy targets.
This is what we had so far.
It's getting crowded, isn't it?
And we are going to make
it more crowded.
And in this case, we are including
the noisy targets.
So obviously, the modification
will happen here.
And what you do is you replace this
with a target distribution.
Let me magnify it.
So the unknown target function became
unknown target distribution.
You define it as a conditional probability
distribution of y given x.
And you can think of this as if it was
a target function, which is the expected
value that I talked about, plus noise,
which is the remaining part.
But as a target, it is
a distribution.
And I'd like to look at this, and
appreciate the time we spent to build
the blocks here.
In spite of the fact this looks like
a complete jungle, you can go back and
understand every single
component here.
Every component has a reason.
This is to accommodate a practical
consideration, which is the fact that
we are learning something
that is noisy.
This is because a specification of the
penalty, or the cost you pay for not
being perfect, needs to be
specified by the user.
This is our artificial addition to the
problem in order to make learning
feasible, and so on and so forth.
So that is the final diagram
for supervised learning.
Now, I'd like to make one final
point about noisy targets, which is
the distinction between the two
probabilities that we have.
We have probability of x, which
we artificially introduced
to accommodate Hoeffding.
And then, this was introduced in
a completely different context. That is
to accommodate the fact that
genuine functions that you
encounter in practice are not
functions-- are actually noisy
distributions.
So let's look at this.
They look very much related.
They both pour into the
training examples.
That's how the training examples
are generated.
This guy passes on the probability
of y given x.
This guy passes on the
probability of x.
When this guy gets it, it generates
those guys according to the joint
distribution-- multiplies these, if you
will, and then uses it as a way to
generate the pair x,y.
So they look like-- they belong
to the same category.
Both of them are unknown.
This one is unknown so that my machine
learning statement can be as general
as I can afford.
You're learning something.
You don't know what it is.
So that's good to have.
This one is unknown, because it is the
most assumption we could afford in
order to get Hoeffding.
We needed a probability distribution,
but we didn't need to make any
assumptions about it.
So we left it to be an arbitrary
one, and unknown, and we don't
want to know it.
So these are the similarities.
Now, let's look at the differences.
Both have probabilistic aspects.
We have seen that.
Now, the target distribution is
what you are trying to learn.
You are not trying to learn
the input distribution.
As a matter of fact, when you are done,
you will not know what the input
distribution is.
The input distribution is merely playing
the role of quantifying the
relative importance of the point x.
Let me give you an example.
Let's say you are approving
credit again.
The target distribution
is the probability of
creditworthiness given the input.
Let's simplify the input and
say it's the salary.
So I give you the salary, you decide
what is the risk of this person
defaulting, and then you decide--
output is +1, approve credit
with probability 0.9, and disapprove
credit with probability 0.1.
That is the target distribution.
And that is what you're
trying to learn.
You're going to approximate it
to a hard decision probably.
Or you can actually learn the
probability distribution, as
we'll see later on.
The input distribution just tells you
the distribution of salaries in the
general population.
How many people make $100,000,
how many people make
$10,000, et cetera.
So in spite of the fact that the
probability distribution over the
input matters in the sense that: let's
say that you encounter a population
where the salaries are very high, so P
of x is tilted very much towards the
high salaries, and let's conjecture that
high salaries correspond to high
creditworthiness. In this case, the same
system that you trained that will
take any salary, low or high, and then
decide whether to approve credit or
not, will be tested mostly in the very
comfortable region of high salaries.
So it will be returning: yes approve,
yes approve, yes approve, with very
small probability of error.
And if you go and put the mass of
probability around the borderline
cases, the cases where the decision is
difficult, the same system that you
learned will probably perform worse,
just because there are so many points
that are borderline.
So it does give the weight that will
finally grade your hypothesis.
But you're not trying to learn
that distribution.
And when you put them together
analytically, which you're allowed to
do, you can merge them
as P of x and y.
And that's what you will
find in the literature.
It's very nice and pleasant, and you
generate the example using that joint
distribution.
However, you just need to remember that
this merging mixes two concepts
that are inherently different.
Definitely, P of x and y is
not a target distribution
for supervised learning.
The target distribution, the one you're
actually trying to learn, is
this fellow.
And the other component is just
a catalyst in the process.
That covers the error and noise,
and we have arrived at the final
statement of the learning problem.
So now, let me spend the rest of the
lecture trying to prepare you for the
coming two weeks, which will consider
the theory of learning.
It's a very important theory, and I
encourage everyone to bite the bullet
and go through it.
I will do my best to make
it user-friendly.
However, it's important not just because
of the mathematical derivation.
The insight, and the secondary
tools you are going to get,
are extremely important.
It's worth two weeks-- not a full two
weeks, but four hours' worth
of listening to a lecture and actually
trying to study the material well.
So that's my pitch.
Let me give you the preamble
to the theory.
Let's see what we know so far
in order to put the theory in
perspective.
We know that learning is feasible
in a probabilistic sense.
And the way we did this is by stating
that it is likely that the
out-of-sample performance is close
to the in-sample performance.
That, in our mind, corresponded to
the feasibility of learning.
And I'm going to test this premise now
and ask: is this really learning?
Is this condition the condition that
captures what we mean by learning?
Let's raise some doubt.
Well, learning means that you
got the hypothesis right.
You give it to your customer,
and it behaves well--
as close as possible to the
target function, right?
That's success.
That means that the condition for
learning is really that g
approximates f.
And now, we are sophisticated people.
We know what "approximates" means.
This condition is not really
this condition, right?
What is this condition in terms of
the E_in and E_out and stuff?
Very simple--
that's what it means.
It means that the out-of-sample
error for g is close to 0.
Because the out-of-sample
error measures what?
It measures how far you are, that is g,
from the target function over the
entire space.
And therefore, the statement that you
are close means that the out-of-sample
error is small.
So this is what we want.
And this is what we have.
Now, what was that?
If it's not learning, what was it?
Well, this was actually
good generalization.
And it's an important building block.
Because you never will
have access to this.
If I gave you this as the condition,
then you say:
A quantity that I will never
know is close to 0.
Thank you very much!
But now, with the theory, I was able to
tell you: you have a window on E_out
by dealing with E_in, if you have the
right checks in place that we
developed vaguely as the number
of hypotheses is not too big.
And we will define it very, very
accurately when we get
to the theory part.
So if you have that, all of a sudden,
E_in is an important quantity.
Because now, it acts as a proxy
for E_out that you don't know.
So this is not a total waste, but
it's only half the story.
The full story of learning
has two questions.
And if you look at this slide, and
remember that this is always the
case the learning problem is posed,
you will dismiss a lot of misconceptions
of-- learning is
impossible, learning is possible.
You'll find all kinds of results
over the literature.
So here's the deal.
This quantity patently
is: we learned well.
That's what it means, right?
So now, we are going to achieve
this through two conditions.
The first condition is the one
we developed using Hoeffding.
E_in is close to E_out.
The second condition is: E_in is small.
You put them together, and
you have the learning.
And you can see the difference
between the two.
This is a theoretical result.
This is a practical result.
E_in,
I know E_in.
I can try to use linear regression, or
something else, to knock this down and
get it as close to 0 as possible.
And indeed, if you look at where we
handled these questions, we didn't
explicitly say the questions
in this form.
But we already covered
them in two lectures.
This was the subject of
Lecture 2, right?
Hoeffding was all about the fact
that E_in is close to E_out.
This was the subject of Lecture 3.
We had data, and we wanted to get
the in-sample error to be small.
And we looked for techniques
to do that.
So now, because this is important,
let's put it in a box.
Learning reduces to two questions.
First question:
can we make sure that the out-of-sample
performance is close
enough to the in-sample performance?
This is a theoretical question, and we
are going to spend two weeks answering
this question.
Second one:
can we make the in-sample
error small enough?
This is a practical question, and we're
going to spend four weeks doing
this one.
And then, by the way, at the end, we'll
have one week to reflect.
And it's always sweet to reflect
when you have a concrete
ground to stand on.
We can do all the philosophy in the
world, and we will have very concrete
mathematics, very concrete algorithms,
and very concrete results on real
data, to know that what we're talking
about means something.
That's the plan.
Now, let me just make a small
comment about this one.
Small enough has been
close to 0 so far.
There is a very important class of
applications where there is no way
under the sun that you'll get
an out-of-sample performance close to 0,
anywhere near 0.
And by proxy, simply, E_in
will not also be 0.
And I'll give you a very
simple example.
Let's say that you're doing financial
forecasting, trying to detect whether
the market's going up or down.
Under idealized conditions,
this is impossible.
That data is purely noisy, and
there's nothing to learn.
The fact that the conditions are not
ideal makes hedge funds make money
because of that.
They exploit a little
bit of inefficiency.
But they don't get it right
100% of the time.
They don't get it right
70% of the time.
They will be very, very happy if they
get it right 53% of the time,
consistently.
Under those conditions, you
will make a lot of money.
So the out-of-sample error here,
that we're trying to do, is
very close to a half.
It's 47% If you get
an out-of-sample error,
so the correct is 53%,
the error is 47%.
So you can get as small as possible, in
some applications, to be not really
near 0 at all, but actually
closer to the half.
As long as you know for a fact, or at
least have the theoretical guarantee,
that what you're seeing in-sample, when
you add the Hoeffding allowance,
if you will, that the out-of-sample will
be comfortably-- error smaller than
a half consistently, you
are in business.
If you don't have the Hoeffding
guarantee, then you
are so happy in-sample.
You get the stock market
right 75% of the time.
You think you're going to make money.
And then, when you look at the jump from
E_in to E_out, you find that the
error bar is that big, and
you are in trouble.
Let me talk about what the theory that
we're going to cover in the next two
weeks will achieve, and
then I will stop.
This is a typical figure that
you are going to get.
Theory deals with in-sample error
and out-of-sample error.
Let me actually magnify it.
OK.
We will see the behavior of in-sample
error as you get the model
to be more and more elaborate, which
will be measured by a quantity which
we are going to call the VC dimension.
You will find that there are certain
behaviors of the in-sample, and the
out-of-sample, and
the model complexity.
And all of the things that appear
in this figure will get a formal
definition, and an ability to evaluate
them when we get the theory.
So it is worthwhile.
But if you summarize what the theory
does, there are two steps that are the
most important.
The first one, which is the most
remarkable result in the theory of
learning, is that we are going to
characterize the feasibility of
learning for the case where--
infinite M, remember what M was?
M was the number of hypotheses.
We worked with a finite hypothesis set,
in order to be able to work with
simple Hoeffding.
And we realized that the bigger
M is, the looser the bound.
And if M goes too big, the
bound is meaningless.
So if M is infinity, we are toast.
So now, we would like to be able to find
a counterpart to able to take
an infinite hypothesis set, like every
hypothesis set we have seen so far--
perceptron, the linear
regression model.
All of these are infinite
hypotheses.
And we are going to try to find a way
to deal with infinite hypotheses.
This is the bulk of the development.
And that is, we'll end up-- we are
going to measure the model not by the
number of hypotheses, but by a single
parameter which tells us the
sophistication of the model.
And that sophistication will reflect
the out-of-sample performance as it
relates to the in-sample performance.
Once we do this, lots of doors open.
So we're going to characterize
a tradeoff that we observed on and off
as we went through the lectures.
We realized that we would like our
model, the hypothesis set, to be
elaborate, in order to be
able to fit the data.
The more parameters you have, the more
likely you are going to fit the data
and get here.
So the E_in goes down if you
use more complex models.
We also suspected that, if you make the
model more complex-- the same
direction, the discrepancy between E_out
and E_in gets worse and worse.
E_in tracks E_out much more loosely
than it used to.
Now, the good news from the theory is
that this will be pinned down so
concretely that we are going to derive
techniques from this that will make
a lot of difference in the
practical learning.
Regularization is a direct
result of this.
And without regularization, you
basically cannot do machine learning,
other than extremely naively.
So this will set the foundation for
a practical method that is used in
almost every machine learning
problem you will have.
So it's worth really knowing.
Now, I will stop here.
And we'll take questions.
And we'll start the theory next time.
Please, get ready.
Do your exercise, and get ready for two
weeks' worth of very interesting
derivation.
Now, let's go to questions.
MODERATOR: How does P of x impact
the learning algorithm?
So does it matter if P of x is different in
the training and the real data set?
PROFESSOR: There is the
absolute impact of P of x.
And then, there's the relative impact.
You're asking about
the relative impact.
Let's say that I pick the training
points according to one distribution,
and then test the system
using another.
Let's answer that question first.
There is a correction to the theory
that takes into consideration the
difference between the two probability
distributions, assuming that they are
not extreme.
For example, if one probability
distribution completely vanishes, then
obviously there's a problem.
Because the points in that part of the
space will never happen, and you
shouldn't be hoping to learn
at all from that.
But there are modifications to the
theory, where you get a correction term
based on the difference between
the two probabilities.
The absolute version--
I don't know whether this was asked,
but let me address it anyway--
how does P of x affect the
learning algorithm?
Well, the emphasis that P of x gives
on certain parts of the space over
others will affect the choice
of the learning examples.
And if you have a limited resource
in your hypothesis set--
which you always have to have,
otherwise the model is too
complicated--
then there's always a compromise about
which part of the space should I try
to get better than the other?
You don't think of this explicitly,
but that's what the algorithm does
when it tries to satisfy
a number of examples.
Therefore, if you change the
probability distribution--
even if it's the same for both of them--
then you will end up with
a slightly different hypothesis that takes
into consideration the emphasis
of the new one.
Nonetheless, you are not learning
that input distribution.
It's just affecting your choices.
MODERATOR: In this discussion,
you introduced a probability of y
given x and probability of x.
Will probability of x given
y ever play a role?
PROFESSOR: I can imagine cases
where it plays a role,
where you have P of x and y,
and you ask yourself: if I get this
output, what is the likely input?
This is a role.
I don't know whether it's a machine
learning role or not.
But in general, the merging of P of x
and P of y given x in the same quantity,
although it's mathematically convenient,
as I mentioned, it's
a little bit--
not misleading.
Misleading is a strong word.
What you're really looking at, you
always think, I have P of y given x.
That's the genuine thing that
I'm trying to learn.
And that is an integral part
of the learning problem.
On the other hand, P of x plays a technical
role-- a technical role
that is fairly negligible.
It's essential for it to exist, but
it's not nearly as important as
P of y given x.
MODERATOR: In the case of considering the
target function as a probability
distribution, then what
is better to have--
N pairs of x and y or N y's per x?
PROFESSOR: I don't have
a theoretical proof for it.
It seems to me obvious that if you get
all the outputs corresponding to one
input, you are dealing with a very
specific part of the input space, and
you're unlikely to infer anything
about the rest of the space.
So the answer to the question
is that intuitively--
and I think it would probably be
not that difficult to prove--
that you get them independently rather
than get them for the same input.
Also, by the argument we mentioned
before, you should be choosing the
inputs according to the probability
distribution, the input probability
distribution P of x, independently.
So if you get all the examples according
to the same x, this really
means that P of x that you're using
is a delta function on that x.
So if you live up to the expectations,
and use the same probability
distribution to generate the output,
then you are in good shape.
But if you change the game on me, and
generate all the examples according to
this delta function, and then when you
want to test it, you go out and give
me points that I haven't seen
before, then I'm in trouble.
MODERATOR: Can you clarify what
you mean by poor generalization?
It's a common question.
PROFESSOR: This will be
part of the theory.
There will be a very specific quantity
we measure, which is the discrepancy
between E_out and E_in.
And we are going to call this the
generalization error.
And that will quantify poor
generalization or good generalization.
MODERATOR: Going back to
slide 11 and 12--
PROFESSOR: Ah, the
supermarket and the CIA.
MODERATOR: Yes, so you chose the numbers
1 and 10, or 1000 and 1.
Is there a principled way
of choosing these numbers?
PROFESSOR: The principled way
is to estimate the cost of this
occurrence, and then translate
it into those.
This was only an illustration.
And I wasn't really interested
in the 1 or 10.
I was only interested in making the
point crisp, that the error measure is
different between two application
domains for exactly the same system--
the same system as in machine learning
system, same training data, same
target function.
But the error measure can be
different depending on the
application domain.
So in this case, indeed, we can actually
go and see, for example,
the loss of revenue by giving
an unwarranted discount for the
supermarket, and the probability that
the customer will be annoyed, and
lost revenue because of the customer,
and actually come up with the right
balance between false accept and false
reject for the supermarket.
It may not be 10, but it will be--
definitely, the number that is 10
here would be bigger than the
number that is 1 here.
Similarly, for the CIA, you can go and
ask yourself, what is the risk and how
much does it cost, versus the lost time
for the employees by trying the system
again, and then come up with a more
principled way of doing it.
But that was not really the crux
of what I'm doing here.
I was only making the point that
they are different, that's all.
MODERATOR: Once the theory is
explained, will it quantify the errors
that result from not knowing parts of P
of x, especially if P of x has maybe
long tails and things like that?
PROFESSOR: P of x has
been assumed to be
an unknown function.
And I only used it as a utility to
invoke a probabilistic setup.
There are no assumptions about P of x.
As long as you pick the points from the
same distribution to train as to
test, everything that I said, and
I will say during the theory
part, will be valid.
If it's a long tail, it's a long tail
for training and for testing.
The probability of getting
something from--
let's say if it's a heavy tail and I get
something that is outlier, I will
get a certain error.
I will get an in-sample error and
I'll get an out-of-sample error.
I basically don't worry about the
structure of P of x, because I'm
assuming it's unknown.
And I'm assuming that, in the course
of supervised learning, I'm not
going to learn it.
MODERATOR: What happens in the case
that both the false positives and
negatives have higher values?
PROFESSOR: If you scale both
of them up, it makes no
difference whatsoever.
Then, the error measure is scaled
up, and you're minimizing it.
So it's just a constant
multiplied by it.
If they are scaled relative to each
other, then obviously the emphasis on
the system changes,
trying to get more false positives and
less false negatives, or vice versa.
And that's what happens between
these two examples.
For the supermarket, here we are
trying not to reject customers.
And in the CIA case, we are trying not
to accept people who are intruders.
MODERATOR: There's also a question of
reiterating the relation of P of x
to Hoeffding Inequality.
PROFESSOR: The Hoeffding
Inequality was based on the bin.
The bin had marbles, and we picked them
according to some probability
which we labeled as--
it's a Bernoulli trail, so
it's a binary outcome.
And the probability was mu.
The bin became the input space.
The input space, when we started talking
about machine learning, did not
have a probability distribution.
It was just a set.
So in order to be able to invoke the
probabilistic aspect, we needed to put
a probability distribution over the
input space, such that when you
you create green and red
marbles according to
agreement/disagreement, and the input
space becomes a bin, there is
a probability that goes with it for
picking red versus green marbles.
It doesn't matter, because any
probability you put will
correspond to some mu.
And then, you have the rest of it.
And we know that the Hoeffding
Inequality is independent of the--
the bound on the right-hand side is
independent of the value of mu.
So any old probability will
do-- will do what?
Will do the legitimization of the
learning problem as far as the
probabilistic approach is concerned.
Obviously, we can enter a discussion
about the probability being
concentrated or spread out, or
parts of the space being 0.
All of that is good and valid, except
that it doesn't affect the basic
question, which is to make sure
that learning is feasible in
a probabilistic sense.
Any P of x will achieve that.
MODERATOR: A clarification--
some people are asking to simplify
the case of a squared error measure
and the closed-form solution.
PROFESSOR: This actually
goes to the review.
Let me go to the review one, because
this is from last lecture.
There is an algorithm that we
derived for linear regression.
And the algorithm was based on
minimizing squared error.
Remember that we took a gradient, and
we took advantage of the form being
squared error in order for the thing
to be differentiable, and for the
derivative to have a simple form.
And that simple form is what ended up
in getting the formula for w at the
bottom, which is X transposed X, inverse
of that, times X transposed y,
as a simple closed-form solution for
the final hypothesis of linear
regression.
So in that case, it is the squared
error measure, that defines linear
regression, that enabled us to
find such a simple solution.
If you take another measure, you may
or may not get a simple solution.
But for sure, in this case, we got it.
And there are definitely error measures
that you can put, where you
cannot find a simple solution
like this one.
MODERATOR: Going back to the problem
of the CIA and the supermarket, if the
probability of y equals +1, and y equals
-1, is not balanced, should
you do something regarding P of x to
have a correct estimate of your error?
PROFESSOR: Probability of
y, in the absolute, depends on two
things-- probability of y given
x and probability of x.
So if you put them together, and you get
an imbalance in the probability of
y, this means that the building
quantities, which is P of x and P of y
given x, are what affected that.
And those quantities will definitely
affect the learning process.
So the answer-- if you want to answer
what happens when y is not
balanced, go back and see
what gave rise to it.
And then, you will be able to find the
answer more directly linked through
the quantities that directly affect
the learning process.
MODERATOR: And again, on these costs, is
there ever a case where you can use
rewards instead of costs, as in
assigning negative values to--
PROFESSOR: Yeah, they
are equivalent, indeed.
You are just maximizing the reward
or minimizing the punishment.
I think it's just two ways of
looking at the same thing.
MODERATOR: A question--
In the example of the bins, when you
say there's a bin that becomes the
input space, does the input space
include just the training data points,
or does input space include
all possible points?
PROFESSOR: The input space
includes all possible points, but
includes only the input parts
of those possible points.
If you look at the examples, the
training data, there is x and y.
And the input space deals
only with the x part.
When you talk about the input space in
general, it covers all possible x's.
When you talk about the training data,
you are talking about the x's that
were picked as a training
set, N of them.
MODERATOR: Regarding the
transformation, what relation does phi
have to something like principal
component analysis?
PROFESSOR: This is
a different subject.
So there is a subject of processing
the input, in order to make it more
compact, in order to get rid of
irrelevant parts and whatnot.
And that is a legitimate processing
step, but it's not what I
was alluding to here.
What I was alluding to here, in the
nonlinear transformation, is an ability
to implement more sophisticated
hypotheses using the same simple
method, which is the
linear method.
And therefore, the transformation
is with a view to that.
Not with a view to getting rid of
some of the artifacts
of the input.
However, feature extraction
is feature extraction.
You can think of the nonlinear
transformation as feature extraction.
You can also think of other methods for
processing the input, and getting
rid of some of the irrelevances,
also as feature extraction.
And if you think of the example of the
handwritten digits that we talked
about, we started with the full image,
which I think was 257 bits' worth,
counting the constant 1.
And then, we ended up with only
two features plus the 1.
The two features where symmetry
and intensity.
And in some sense, these are
informative features.
And in that case, you lost some
information about the input.
But hopefully what you lost
is not relevant.
The principal component analysis, and
other methods, are fairly systematic to
detect that without attaching meaning.
So you don't really study the subject.
You just apply a standard method that
will pick the most informative
directions in the input space, in
the input representation space.
And that will be your goal.
So it's a different subject.
It's not related to nonlinear
transformation, per se.
MODERATOR: Regarding the error measures,
so the squared error measure is used
mainly for mathematical convenience.
Do we lose too much by replacing it for
something like just an absolute value?
PROFESSOR: You
lose the optimization.
Squared error is this way.
And that is nice and smooth, and
has all kinds of properties.
You take the absolute value,
and you have this guy.
And the edge is really bad news.
All of a sudden, it becomes combinatorial
optimization instead of
a smooth function.
So yes, you lose in terms
of optimization.
If you have a specific merit for using
the absolute value-- that is, the guy
tells you that this is my function, and
I want to make sure that this is
what you minimize--
then we have to bite the bullet
and work through it.
But if you're making an analytic choice
just for the heck of it, you
might as well pick something that is
friendly either to the concept or to
the optimizer.
MODERATOR: So this question regarding
the use of a linear model,
when you have P of y given x,
that represents f of x.
And then, f of x would be the
result of w transposed--
hello?
OK, so if this is the case, then when
you subtract y by f of x, does it mean
you have a P of y of x shape?
PROFESSOR: The target is f of x.
The target is not w transposed x.
w transposed x is the final hypothesis
that is my attempt to approximate
the target function.
So I was talking about target function
versus target distribution, even
without any learning taking place.
Someone has a target function.
It's noisy.
I'm telling them that they
can model it this way--
take the expected value, assuming it's
a numerical function-- the expected
value under the probability
distribution.
You will get the average
y given a particular x.
That's a function.
So your call this f of x.
The remaining part, which is the value
of y minus that, will be pure noise in
the sense that it averages around 0.
So this was just a way
of looking at it.
But definitely, it does not touch
at all on linear models
or any other models.
It's a characterization of the target
function versus target distribution.
MODERATOR: There's a tradeoff
between complexity and the
performance.
Is there a way to simultaneously
improve the generalization as well as
minimize error?
PROFESSOR: If you sit through
the next four lectures very,
very attentively, you'll get the answer
to that at the end of the four
lectures.
I'm half joking, but that's
the reality of it.
You'll have enough tools to be able
to answer questions like that.
MODERATOR: I think that's it.
PROFESSOR: OK, that's it.
Thank you, and we'll see you next week.