ANNOUNCER: The following program
is brought to you by Caltech.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Welcome back.
Last time, we talked about three learning
principles that, if you're in
the business of machine learning, you
should be aware of in order to avoid
the very common pitfalls in
applying machine learning.
The first one is Occam's razor, which
says simpler is better-- and better in
terms of the performance.
And therefore, you should use a razor
in order to trim the explanation of
the data-- the hypothesis, or the
complexity of the hypothesis set in
this case-- in order to get to the bare
minimum that is consistent with the
data that you have.
Now, in making this a specific statement
that is justified, we had
simply two arguments that are
interesting in their own right.
One of them is the fact that a complexity
of an object corresponds to
the complexity of a class of objects.
So this correspondence was one.
The other one is that if you have
an unlikely event, then when it does
happen, that is more significant than if
it was a likely event to begin with.
And when we put them together, we get
the proofs of Occam's razor under
different assumptions.
The second principle had to do with
sampling bias, which reminds you of
the fact that we said that the training
data comes from the same
distribution as the test data.
That was the basic assumption in all
of our theoretical analysis.
And when it doesn't, then
there is a bias.
And since your learning algorithm learns
only from the training data, it
is going to inherit whatever it is
that is in the training data as
a distribution.
And therefore, the result will
be accordingly biased.
If the mismatch is nice and continuous,
at least nonzero for all
the points, then there is a way to
compensate for the sampling bias, by
trying to make the sample look as
if it was coming from the other
distribution.
But if the training data doesn't
represent a particular part of the
space, so that space has a probability
0 as far as the training
is concerned.
But it has a positive probability for
the test, then there is really nothing
that can be done to replicate the
behavior of the target function over
that part of the space.
And therefore, you get something
that is inherently biased.
The last principle had to do with data
snooping, which is the most important
in terms of being a trap
that you fall into.
And the idea here is that when you
use a data set in the training,
in any capacity--
it could be very light capacity.
And we saw an example, where the only way
the data was used was in order to
derive normalization constants for
the inputs, something very light.
Nonetheless, the fact that you used
the data means that you cannot
call it test set after that, and
trust the performance that is
suggested by that data set.
And indeed, we took a case where we
allowed snooping, and we ended up with
very optimistic view
when in reality, the performance
was very poor.
And of course, if you go for the real
out-of-sample, you hand the system to
your customer and they test it.
They will see the real out of
sample, not the optimistic
performance that you had.
Today's lecture is the final lecture.
And I am going to use it in order to
give the big picture of machine
learning, and try to fit the
stuff that we covered
within the big picture.
And then, tie up a couple of loose
ends that are relevant to that.
So here is the outline.
First, I'm going to talk about the map
of machine learning, because machine
learning is pretty diverse
as you will see.
And we will see what we covered and
how you can pursue it further, and
what topics I would recommend
that you read about.
And then we'll take two topics--
I'll explain why we picked these
two topics, and talk about
them in some detail.
Not in very technical detail like we covered
the topics of this course, but at
least to give you some background about
where these topics stand as far
as machine learning is concerned.
So that if you decide to pursue
them, you have a head start.
And finally, I'm going to acknowledge
the people who have contributed
greatly to this course.
Well, when it comes to machine learning,
it's a jungle out there.
And it's interesting that if you buy two
books on machine learning, and you
look at them, you will feel that you
are reading about two completely
different subjects.
If one of them is theoretical, and
particular theory-- there are a bunch
of theories-- and one of them is
practical, or one of them is
emphasizing a particular technique,
they just have nothing in common.
Not even the jargon.
So if you go out on your own and just
look at what happens in machine
learning, pretty much this is
the picture you will get.
Not a pretty picture.
And you can see buzzwords galore,
and people will get excited about one
thing and tell you that this is God's
gift to humanity.
And the other thing-- people
will be very opinionated.
It's just all over the place.
So I'm not going to attempt
to be complete.
Because being complete here is fatal.
Trying to cover everything so that
everybody is happy that you covered
the results they got, I don't think
this is a good strategy.
I preached Occam's razor
last time.
Remember Occam's razor?
You should have a razor, and then you
should trim, trim, trim, until you get
the essential part.
This is pretty much what
I tried to do here.
Because I believe that if you understand
the fundamentals, inside
out, you can pursue things completely
on your own from then on.
You are not going to be intimidated
by grandiose statements of
one nature or another.
You will know where things
lie, and whatnot.
So my task was to get the
foundation right.
And in the course of doing that, I
had to omit many, many topics.
So now I'm going to give you the map
of the whole thing, what we covered
and what can be pursued, in
order just to have a good
outlook on the situation.
So here is the map.
There is theory.
And theory means that you mathematically
model what happens in
reality, and then try to do mathematical
derivation in order to
arrive at results that are
not otherwise obvious.
That's what theory is in general.
And there are usually two aspects when
you look at a theory: what assumptions
they made, and then what the deviation
is in order to get to the results.
I hardly ever saw a situation
where there's a problem
with the second part.
People are very competent
mathematicians.
They are not going to make
a mistake in derivation.
So the chances are, when they make
a statement mathematically, they
actually mean it and they proved it.
So that is not our concern.
The biggest pitfall in theory is that
people make assumptions that make what
they are solving really divorced from
the practice that you are going to see
when you use machine learning.
And when I picked a theory,
I picked it with a view to
relevance to practice.
I wanted to get something.
It has to obviously be mathematical,
and it has to be proved,
and all of that.
But then when you see the
result, you can use it.
And I will go through other alternatives
that have succeeded in
that to different degrees.
Then there are techniques, and that is
really the bulk of machine learning.
We covered some techniques, but I'm
going to categorize techniques into
two sets and give you samples.
And then you'll understand from what we
have done where it lies and how you
can pursue it further.
And finally, there are paradigms.
And paradigms mean different
assumptions about
the learning situation.
Not mathematical assumptions, but
different assumptions that deal with
different learning situations, like
for example, supervised learning
versus reinforcement learning.
And when you make these assumptions,
the problems you are solving are
sufficiently different that you end up
with really a different body of
knowledge that you have to study.
And therefore, we call them
different paradigms.
So these are basically the categories.
Let me start with the paradigms first,
because it's the higher level,
and then go to the other ones.
We covered supervised learning.
That was almost the exclusive
topic of the course.
And it is, by far, the most popular
and the most useful
form of machine learning.
So if you cover just that, you
are already very much ahead.
The other topics are interesting and
they have applications, and they
should be studied, but definitely not
in the league of supervised learning
in terms of impact on practice.
We touched on unsupervised learning
with a single algorithm we had.
But we at least got the idea
that clustering is the key.
And indeed, clustering is the key.
And with unsupervised, there are
also variations of that.
There are semi-supervised.
Everything I say here has a bunch
of variations already there.
So I'm just giving you the center
of mass of these paradigms.
Then there is reinforcement learning
that I described in the first lecture
very briefly, but we didn't
cover at all.
And the reason is justified.
Because the main problem in supervised
learning was the question of
information.
Do I have enough information in the
data in order to get the target
function and generalize, right?
When you go to reinforcement
learning-- remember what
reinforcement learning was.
You don't have the target
value on the examples.
You just take an action,
which is an output, not
necessarily the target output,
and then something comes to tell
you that you did well or
you didn't do well.
So it's reinforcement of good
actions, and elimination of bad
actions, that will make you eventually
converge to a good solution.
And we said that it applies to games.
Let's say you're trying
to learn backgammon.
And what you do, you just play against
yourself, generating at will examples
as you want.
Here is a situation.
What do I do?
I'll do something.
I can generate that.
The only question is, after you do that,
how do you take the feedback of
winning and losing and go back and
adjust your strategy, such that you
converge to a good strategy?
So the issue here is completely
different from supervised learning.
It's not a question of information.
It's the question of the algorithm that
will take all of these tons of
examples that you can generate at will,
and produce a way to converge to
a solution from one strategy to a better
strategy to a better strategy.
So it's a completely
different paradigm.
And if there's one topic in this
entire viewgraph that I would
encourage you to pursue, read
about reinforcement learning.
It's a very sweet subject.
Finally, there are many paradigms--
active learning.
So active learning, it could be active
reinforcement or active supervised.
Active learning means that, instead of
someone giving you the data set, you
query about the value at
a particular point.
So you give me the input and you ask
for the output if it's supervised.
Or, you give me the input and expect
a reward or punishment if it's
reinforcement learning.
So it's an adjustment, and there are
some interesting results there.
And the other mini-paradigm
is online learning.
And this is purely computational
consideration.
So take any form of learning.
And instead of giving you the full data
set, and allowing you to work with
it any way you want, I am streaming
the data set to you.
So you take something and you try to
modify your current hypothesis,
and then you take the other guy.
And you cannot store everything.
If you could store everything,
you have the whole data set.
So there are limitations on
storage and computation.
And under those constraints, you ask
yourself, how can I learn and how
close can I get to the optimal as
if I had the whole data set, and
whatnot.
So, these are the most
famous paradigms.
There are other paradigms.
I'm not trying to be exhaustive here.
Now, let's go for the theory.
The main theory in machine learning
is the Vapnik-Chervonenkis theory.
And it is the one that I covered
in great detail in this
course, as you realize.
And the reason is very
straightforward.
It's relevant.
You do the math.
You go through the proofs, and then
you get the VC dimension.
You equate it to the number of
parameters in some cases.
And when you go to practice, even if
you are taking bounds and treating
them as if they were equalities,
that leap of faith works
very well in practice.
So it's not that the theory was
there, and we decided that
this is a good one.
The theory was there, and then we tried
to take wisdom from the theory and
apply it in practice, and it worked.
This is the value added by choosing
a topic and putting it here.
You know that there is
a reason why it's here.
And the reason here is that it is
actually relevant to practice.
Then, there is bias-variance.
Well, bias-variance is
a sweet little theory.
And it gave us some intuition
about this.
And indeed, it was included.
It was low cost to include it,
and it does lead to some
understandings, like
the learning curves.
There are theories that I didn't
describe, although they are very
substantial in the literature.
One of them is based on
computational complexity.
It basically treats machine learning
as a branch of computational
complexity, with an emphasis
on asymptotic results.
So it's the question of can I
do this in polynomial time or not?
And it's a very respectable
body of work.
And the only question for including it
or not including it is whether these
particular results correspond to
something that I face in practice.
So when I look at it, should I do the
computational complexity part of it,
or should I do the generalization
part of it?
The generalization part of it won hands
down, because it's the one that
is the bottleneck when I practice
machine learning.
And finally, there is the famous
Bayesian approach.
Now, this treats machine learning
as a branch of probability.
So you have a problem.
We can always put a probability
distribution.
And by the time you put the full joint
probability distribution, you can
answer all questions.
And it's a very sweet theory, because
you can ask any question you want
and you will find a very concrete,
rigorous mathematical answer to that
question, if you have the setup of
the joint probability distribution.
Now, let's go for the techniques.
There are other theories, again.
I just gave you the biggest players.
When you look at techniques, you
should separate models, as in
hypothesis sets and algorithms
that go with them.
That's one category.
And then, the high-level methods, like
regularization for example, that
doesn't restrict itself to a particular
model, but is super-imposed
on anything you use.
So I will look at members
of those categories.
So we looked at the models.
Linear we emphasized a lot.
It is not usually emphasized in regular
machine learning courses.
They usually go for other models.
It's emphasized very much in
statistics, for example.
And I find it to be very
underrepresented in machine learning.
It's a very important model.
With a nonlinear transform, you
can cover a lot of territory.
And it's very low cost, and it should
be tried in many learning problems.
Then we went on to neural networks.
You have seen that.
Support vector machines, and
the kernel methods.
We covered quite a bit of territory.
Nearest neighbors, I alluded to very
quickly when I talked about RBF.
It's a very standard method.
Not much to say about it, except
that it's a good benchmark.
If you have a data set, why don't you
categorize everything according to the
nearest neighbor?
And this will give you a performance,
and then you can compare
other methods to that.
It's not that difficult to implement.
We looked at RBF and its relation to
many things in machine learning.
And then there is Gaussian processes,
which some people are completely fond
of, which is great.
And it really has the same
spirit of Bayesian.
It's a full probability distribution.
So a process here means
a random process.
A random process is nothing
but a random function.
If a random variable is
a random number, a random
process is a random function.
So we have probability distribution over
different functions that can come out.
And the assumption here is that they are
Gaussian, which means that if you
take any finite number of points, the
probability distribution of the
y-coordinate is jointly Gaussian
for those guys.
So if you have a full description of
that probability distribution, you can
solve anything you want.
Because you can say, if I have this data
point, then I am conditioning on
that Gaussian variable
being equal to that.
And I'm asking myself, what is now
the conditional distribution
of the other guys?
And for Gaussian, this is completely
solved and you have nice matrices to
just multiply out and
get that solution.
So it's very good to use.
And if you are modeling something that
happens to a Gaussian process, then
obviously you win greatly because
you are actually matching that.
There is SVD, which is the singular
value decomposition, used figuratively
in this case.
This is the factor analysis we used
in the Netflix problem, where we
represented the user as a bunch of
factors, and the movie as a bunch of
factors, and we tried to match.
When you put this, you find that
it's as if you are decomposing the
ratings matrix, the entire ratings
matrix into two matrices.
And this would be similar to singular
value decomposition in mathematics.
So we have seen part of that.
Finally, there is graphical models.
And graphical models is almost
a different paradigm in its own right.
What are graphical models?
They are a model where the target
is a joint probability distribution.
That's what you're trying to learn.
And the key here is that the joint
probability distribution between
a very large number of variables
becomes very difficult to manage
computationally, because the number of
possibilities would be exponential in
the number of variables.
So the bulk of work in graphical models
is trying to find a simple way,
or an efficient way, in order to get
answers about that joint probability
distribution, and to learn it.
So it is mostly computational.
And it's based on graph algorithms.
And the main aspect of putting it in
a graph is to use the properties, that
happen to be conditional independence,
as a way to simplify the graph.
So if you look at the things I showed so
far, probably there would be a full
course in graphical models, which
is completely justified.
If you are in the business of modeling
joint probability distributions, and
computation is a consideration,
this is the thing to learn.
There is no question about that.
It's specialized, but it's very
helpful in that case.
And the other one I mentioned was
reinforcement learning, usually taught
together with active learning because
there are a lot of commonalities.
Now, we go for the methods.
And the methods are very important,
because they cover a lot of territory
regardless of the model you have.
We used regularization.
Can you think of other methods,
at the same level, that we used?
Regularization and?
We used validation, right?
These were all methods overall.
There are things we didn't cover.
And one of them is aggregation, putting
together different solutions.
And the last one we didn't cover
was input processing.
This is something you do regardless
of the model you are going to use.
And I find that input processing is best
taught within a projects course.
It's a very practical matter.
And when you teach a projects course
and people will have to deal
with the real data, it's a good thing
to start by telling them, here is
the principal component analysis in
order to normalize and de-correlate the
inputs, and whatnot.
And this is the value.
And then they can try it.
There is little intellectual
value to input processing.
It's a practical matter.
And therefore, it is best taught when
you are teaching a practical course.
Now, from all of this, I am going
to talk about two topics today.
One of them is Bayesian, and
the other one is aggregation.
I'm not going to talk
about them in-depth.
I'm actually going to try to make
a point, particularly about Bayesian.
And you say, you just told
us about the razor.
And you trimmed it, and you
got the solution right.
Why are you now adding up stuff
to the minimal possible?
There is a good reason.
The Bayesian is the elephant
in the room.
If I don't talk about it, you will
hear about it a lot and you will
wonder, why in the world
didn't I talk about it?
Looks great when you look
at the results.
So I need to put it in perspective.
And that's what I'm going
to try to do.
I'm not going to cover the
scope of Bayesian.
I'm going to cover the foundations of
the Bayesian approach, and make a point
about when is it valid?
When can you use it?
What are the drawbacks?
The other one is aggregation.
I would say that aggregation was the
runner-up topic in this course.
I would have normally included it.
If I had more time and I had
a natural position for it.
Because it's a fairly simple technique
and covers a lot of territory, and has
been successful.
So I'm going to try to cover it in some
level of detail that will make
you at least able to read it, and
understand what you are reading and
where it lies.
So this is the plan.
With that, let's go to the two topics.
Bayesian learning first, and then I'm
going to talk about aggregation methods.
Bayesian learning is
trying to get a full
probabilistic approach to learning.
The first thing to do is to remind
you of the learning diagram.
Let me magnify it a little bit.
We are not going to go through
the details of it.
We are just going to concentrate
on the probabilistic aspect.
There are many probabilistic components.
One of them is inherent, which is the
fact that the target could be noisy.
And therefore, we model the target not
as a function but as a probability
distribution.
Think of the case, for example,
we dealt with as trying to
predict heart attacks.
Getting a heart attack or not
getting a heart attack is
a probabilistic aspect.
And if we have our target as the
probability of getting a heart attack
given certain conditions within
a certain amount of time, then the
examples I'm going to give you don't
give you that value of the target
function, but give you realizations
from that probability distribution
that are noisy.
And therefore, I give you that
probability distribution
P of y given x.
So that one is built-in, in terms
of the functions or the noisy
functions we are trying to learn.
The other probability distribution
we had was the input probability
distribution, and that was admittedly
an artificial addition to the problem,
in order to be able to
get the theory going.
And in spite of the fact that it is
an assumption, it's a very benign
assumption for the very simple reason
of the world 'unknown'. I wanted
a probability distribution just to get
the machinery of probability going.
And I'm making no assumptions about
the probability distribution.
You can pick any one you want.
And I don't even want to know it.
So this is very light
as assumptions go.
Now, when it comes to the Bayesian
approach, what you want to do is you
want to extend the probabilistic
role completely.
So that everything is just a big joint
probability distribution of all the
notions involved.
And if you get that going, then you
will obviously be able to derive
anything, in terms of that joint
probability distribution.
So when you do this, let's
think of something.
In the prediction of the heart attack
case, remember that we did use
probability in order to derive the
algorithm for picking a hypothesis.
What did we do?
We said you have a data set.
What is the data set?
A bunch of patients with their
attributes, and whether or not they got
a heart attack within a year of
getting these measurements.
That was the data set.
And you were trying to say that I am
going to pick the hypothesis that, if
this hypothesis truly reflected the
probability of getting a heart attack
within that time frame, then the
probability of getting that data set,
which actually took place,
would be higher.
That was our approach.
And we called this the likelihood.
Remember?
So it's not we are picking the
highest-probability hypothesis.
We don't have the luxury to do that, for
a reason that will become clear.
We are picking the hypothesis that
will make the data that actually
happened highest possible
probability--
maximum likelihood.
So we already used the probabilistic
approach here.
Now the only difference, when you go to
the Bayesian approach, is that you
actually go for the real quantity.
The data already happened, why are
you maximizing the probability?
Well, maximize the probability-- if
what happened is likely given
a scenario, then
that scenario is likely.
That's why you call it likelihood.
But a more principled approach would be
to actually try to use the probability
that this is the correct hypothesis
given the data.
That is the bottom line.
I give you the data.
This is given.
And you have a bunch of hypotheses.
You ask yourself, is it this hypothesis,
or this hypothesis, or
this hypothesis that reflects
the target function.
Well, you look for which one
is the most probable to be,
and you declare that.
And that would be the
Bayesian approach.
If you go to statistics, there is always
a school that loves Bayesian and
there is a school that hates Bayesian.
And there is sort of an ongoing
struggle between them.
And it's funny, because you think this is
mathematics, people shouldn't have
just-- tastes like that.
But the problem is that Bayesian
depends on something that I will
describe here, and the controversy
all comes from that assumption.
But it came to the level in statistics
where they describe a person, as, oh,
this is a Bayesian person versus
no, I'm not a Bayesian.
It's almost like it was
a religion or something.
But that's the reality of the field.
And you will understand why it evolved
into that, when I describe the
components.
The main component that raises
the controversy is the prior.
So let's look at what that is.
We want the probability of a hypothesis
being the correct target
function, given the data.
And if you want to compute that, and
even if you have the model for the
noise and the model for the input
probability distribution--
all of the stuff that we had
in the learning diagram is
already taken for granted.
You still need one more
probability distribution in
order to complete this.
And the way to discover it is
just-- let's write it down.
This probability.
And you apply Bayes' rule, hence the
word 'Bayesian', in order to get this
from the quantities we know.
So we know this one.
We know the probability of the data
given that-- if this hypothesis.
was faithful description of how people
got heart attack, then the probability
of getting that data is--
you just compute how much noise in
each point, according to this
being f.
And you get it, which we got in logistic
regression, and resulted in
the error measure over there.
So that was given.
The part that we need that
is not given is this one.
When you multiply them, you get the
joint probability distribution.
And when you divide by the probability
of D, you get the conditional-- the
other direction which you want.
Now, there is no sweat in
getting this.
Because if I have the joint probability
distribution, I just
integrate out whatever I don't want,
and I end up with the marginal.
So there is no difficulty in this.
And in fact, if your job is to just
pick h according to this criterion,
then this fellow doesn't matter because
it doesn't depend on h.
It scales all of them up or down.
So if you are picking between two
hypotheses according to this
probability, you might as well forget
about this and take the numerator as
your indicator, and pick the one that
gives you the bigger numerator.
So you think of this as
proportional to this.
And this is what I'm going to use.
Now, this is the mystery quantity, so
let's put it down and describe it.
What does that mean?
It's not conditioned on anything.
I'm asking you, here's
the hypothesis set.
It's a perceptron.
It has a bunch of weights.
Could you please tell me, what is the
probability that this particular
combination of weights will actually
give you the target function?
How in the world are you
going to know that?
So what you are doing here is assuming
that there is a probability
distribution for that.
You're going to put a probability
distribution over the hypothesis set,
the last component in the diagram that
didn't really have a probability.
The probability reflecting the statement
that this hypothesis is,
indeed, the target function.
And any discrepancy between the data
set and the hypothesis, which is
supposed to be the target function,
is attributed to the fact
that the data is noisy.
The data does not reflect
the target function.
The data deviates by added noise.
So this one is called the prior.
Prior because it is your belief
about the hypothesis set
before you got any data.
Before.
After you got the data, you can modify
this and you get the probability of h
given the data.
That's now more informed.
You get the specific data from the
target function, and then you are
going to zoom in and make a better
choice among the hypotheses that you
have for which one qualifies
as the target.
And this one is called the posterior.
It happens after the fact.
Now, if you are given the
prior-- let's say that I
actually give you a problem.
I don't know the target function, but
I know quite a bit about it in terms
of probabilities.
And here is the way I'm going
to formalize that.
I am going to give you a full
probability distribution over the
entire hypothesis set that tells you the
relative probability of different
hypotheses being the correct
target function.
That's my prior.
If you have that, you have the joint
probability distribution.
And if you have the joint probability
distribution, you
can answer any question.
So that's a very attractive
route to follow.
You can get anything.
And because of that, it's important
to look at the prior.
That is the center of the idea
of a Bayesian approach.
So the main point I'm making, the only
point I'm making in fact, in this
particular section, is the fact
that prior is an assumption.
So before I get to that, let
me give you an example of
a prior to make it concrete--
the one I referred to.
So let's say that you are
having a perceptron.
So your perceptron model.
What is a perceptron model?
It's hyperplanes in some
space, d-dimensional.
So I have weights w_0 up to w_d that
tell me the slope and the offset.
And this will tell me what
is the separating plane.
And I'm going to use this as a hypothesis
in order to separate some
data points generated from a target.
And I'm going to assume that
the target is there--
let's say, even you can take a linear
target if you want, and added noise.
After you generate the points from that
target, you flip the labels of
some of the guys according
to some noise.
So 10% of the points are flipped, so
this is your contribution of the
noise. Just to have something concrete
in your mind to imagine.
So you have a perceptron.
h is specified by the weights.
Perceptron is-- you call it h
because it's a full function.
But in reality, you just tell me what
the parameters are and I know what is
the function, because I know what
is the separating plane.
So here is a prior-- I suggest
a possible prior.
The prior, now, I'm going to give
it in terms of the weights.
So I'm going to tell you which weights
are more likely than others.
And what I'm going to try to do, I'm
going to try to make the assumption as
benign as possible.
Because I really don't know.
When I say which weights are
more likely than others, I'm not
saying which weights are more
likely to come out.
I'm asking, which weights are likely
to actually reflect what the target
function is, the target function
that we said was unknown.
So I'm making some assumptions.
I'm trying to reduce the level of
crimes that I'm doing, and trying to
give you something that is fairly
vague so I am not making a big
commitment.
Knowing that for the perceptrons,
the magnitude of the
weights doesn't matter--
if you scale all the w's by any
positive number up or down, you get
the same surface.
Because it is just classifying +1
or -1. You care about the signal
being positive or negative.
So I'm going to take w's in a limited
range, and I'm going to take them to be
uniform, independently.
So each weight is between -1
and +1 independently
from the other weight.
That is my prior.
And my hope in putting that prior is
that I didn't make a big assumption.
'hope' is the operative word here.
So what does that mean?
It means that, if I get the
probability distribution over all the
weights, then I can see which weights
contribute to a particular hypothesis.
And then I have the prior over
h, which is the one I want.
So I have the probability
of h, given nothing.
And when I am given the data, I mix
now my prior belief about which
hypothesis is the target function
according to this, which seems to be
completely uniform.
And then take the data, and the data
will tell me that some guys are more
possible than others.
If I pick something that will require my
interpretation of the noise to say
that 90% of the points had to flip in
order for this to be the correct
target, then this is very unlikely
because the flipped was only 10%.
And therefore, this will get demoted
among hypotheses according to the
evidence coming from the data.
And you compute the probability of the
data given h, and then you multiply
them and you get what you want,
which is the posterior.
And the posterior is the product--
at least proportional to the
product of the two.
So this is a concrete example
if you want to apply this.
Now, we make the main statement
about the prior.
And the main statement is that the
prior is, indeed, an assumption.
Let's look at it.
Let me take a very simple case.
It doesn't have to do with learning
in particular, to make the point.
Let's say that I take the most neutral
prior to describe something unknown.
You have something that is unknown,
like a target function.
In this case, it will be a number.
So I have an unknown number.
And all I know about it is that it's
between -1 and +1.
And someone decides that it will be
convenient to have a probability
distribution over x, notwithstanding
the fact that x is not really
probabilistic.
I'm not running any experiment and
generating x's repeatedly.
x is just a number sitting out
there that I don't know.
I don't know, not in a probabilistic
sense that it's a random variable.
I don't know-- it's
an unknown parameter.
So you ask yourself, would this
be equivalent to x being
random in some setting?
Can you model this with probability?
And invariably, people will tell
you, you look at this.
I don't know what x is.
So let me model this using a uniform
probability distribution
from -1 to +1.
On face value, this looks completely
innocent and credible.
Because here you didn't
make any commitment.
It is as likely to be this,
as this, as this, as this.
This one is unknown, so it seems that
you captured what the meaning is.
I would like to argue that it doesn't.
It actually makes a huge assumption.
Now, you are not saying
that you don't know x.
You're saying that, I know that
x came from this distribution.
So if you know that, here are a bunch of
stuff that I know, that actually I
didn't know here.
If you generate a bunch of x's and take
their average, the chances are
you will be around 0.
If you look at a bunch of x's here and
you average, I have no clue what
you're going to get.
If you do this, I can tell you even
not only that the average will be
close to 0.
I can tell you how close it
is, in terms of variance.
Here, I could be all over the place.
So you realize that, innocent as this
may be, this is a different problem
than this one.
And if you insist on modeling x as
a probability, and you want to capture
the statement here exactly, without
adding any assumptions, you can
definitely do that.
Although, it looks much less
attractive than this one.
This is not equivalent.
And if you want the true equivalent in
terms of probability of this fellow,
this is what you're going to have.
So here, x is unknown.
Here, x is random, and
the probability
density function of that happens to be
a delta function centered around
a point 'a' that I don't know.
That would be strictly modeling this.
This does not model it.
And the fact that people take the
liberty of doing that, results in many
cases in really a huge building
based on a false premise.
In some cases, you get away with it.
But in some cases, you don't.
So this is the key point, that when
you put a prior, you are actually
making a huge assumption.
Think of it this way.
We took great pains to say, the
target function is unknown.
It could be anything.
I'm not going to make assumptions about
it. Because in reality, when you
are in machine learning, if someone
knocks on my door and they say they
want to learn a function, I really
don't know what the function is.
So you go to your hypothesis set, which
you picked out of your hat.
I'm going to use neural networks,
or I'm going to use linear--
whatever it is.
And then you say, now, here is the
probability that for each of these
points, I'm going to specify very
specifically the probability that this
is exactly the target function.
And people do that with great
ease, and then build on it.
All I'm asking for you to realize--
I'm not saying don't do that.
I'm just making the statement: realize
that you are making an assumption.
And it's a big assumption.
So let's see the ramifications
of that.
If you actually knew the prior, you
would be in fantastic shape.
Why is that?
Because you can compute the posterior
for every point in
your hypothesis set.
For every hypothesis, I know now what is
the probability of it given D. Mind
you, this is h equals f over
the entire space.
That is, this is really out-of-sample.
I am taking D which is in-sample, and
I'm making a statement about the
probability for every hypothesis
to be, out-of-sample.
I don't worry about regularization
and VC bounds.
This is it.
You know the prior.
You give the data set.
You have a model for it.
You can compute this explicitly.
And based on this probability
distribution, you can
get a bunch of stuff.
For example, you can pick the
most probable hypothesis.
Without any dispute, this is
the most probable hypothesis.
You can even go further.
Well, I picked a hypothesis set, and this
is the probability that each of
them is the target function.
And now that I have the evidence from
the data, I have a better picture of
it, which is the posterior.
I can now actually ask myself, I can
derive the expected value of h because
for every h, there's a probability.
Instead of picking just the highest
probability and sticking with it, why
don't I get the benefit of the entire
probability distribution?
Well, the target function could be this
one, could be this one, could be
this one, with these probabilities.
If you want a good estimate of the value
of the target function at any
point x, why don't you take the value of
h of x for every hypothesis in your
set, and put them together as expected
value because you have the probability
distribution?
And then you get a very
good estimate of that.
And you can even get an estimate
for the error bar.
After you get the estimate--
this is my estimate for this--
I can tell you, what are the
chances that I'm wrong?
Think of the possibilities.
I'm predicting the stock market.
And I learned using this
Bayesian learning.
And I have the inputs for today.
And I want to predict the output, which
is what will happen tomorrow.
Now, I can tell you the
price movement.
What is the expected value
of the price movement,
very specifically on that
x, which I care about.
And I can also tell you,
what is the error bar.
So if I tell you that the expected value
is positive, and the error bar is
small, then the chances are
overwhelming that I will move
positively, and I would be putting my
money in going in that direction.
If the error bar is huge,
then I'm not so sure.
And I'm not sure it's worthwhile
betting on it.
That's a good situation to be in.
And also, you can derive anything
you can imagine.
You have a joint
probability distribution.
You can really put any events, and you
just plug in and collect the points
that constitute that event.
And you get the probability, and
you have an answer for that.
Now, let me make a statement
about the approach so far.
We have been struggling with VC bounds,
and loose bounds, and then we have to
use regularization, and we use
a heuristic for the regularizer.
And then we have to the set aside
a validation set, and we wonder about the
independence of the cross-validation.
we really have a tough life.
So in this approach, it looks like
they are doing much better.
All they need to do is plug in the
quantities, and they get the answer.
And they know that the
answer is correct.
They don't worry about
any of the stuff.
So the way I think about
it is the following.
When you are following this ideology,
it's as if you want to have a good
life, and this is your approach
to getting the good life.
First, you rob a bank.
Then, you live righteously ever after.
Well, you can live righteously
ever after.
You can afford it.
The other guys are struggling
with this and that, with
regularization and whatnot.
The problem here obviously,
is the first step.
And the first step here is
sugarcoated greatly.
It's a benign prior.
It's just uniform.
We didn't do anything.
Because obviously, it's very
attractive afterwards.
But you are standing on
very shaky ground.
And you should ask yourself, when
is this actually justified?
If you do it in general without any
justification, then it's a nice
theory built on an assumption that
doesn't necessarily hold.
On the other hand, it can be very
valuable, and it can be justified in
basically two cases.
One of them is that the
prior is valid.
And the other one is that
the prior is irrelevant.
What do I mean?
Prior is valid is that for some reason
that I really don't know, you put
a prior and this is, indeed, the
probability that a particular
hypothesis equals the target function.
That is a fact.
In which case, I concede.
You are doing better than me, I can
go with all my approximations, and
heuristics, and this and that.
And I'm not going to do nearly
as good as you do.
So in this case, this trumps all
the cases if you know that the
assumption is valid.
So if there are cases where the
assumption is valid, I highly
recommend that you follow
this approach.
It may be computationally expensive
because for example, when you get
expected value with respect to the
posterior in a high-dimensional space,
that's not an easy task.
On the other hand, since this is the
ultimate performance, it may be worth
the effort.
"The prior is irrelevant" is
a more interesting aspect.
The idea is the following.
When you put a prior, if you get more
and more data and you look at the
posterior, you realize that the
posterior is affected largely by the
data set, and less and
less by the prior.
If you start from another prior and
another prior and another prior, as
long as you don't take extremes.
You don't put it to zero
at certain points.
You just get something reasonable.
It basically gets factored out, as
you get more and more data.
And because of that, if you have enough
data that the prior doesn't
matter, then you can think of the prior
not as a conceptual addition.
It's just a catalyst for
the computation.
And there is a particular approach to
this where you think, let me pick
a prior just because of its
analytic properties.
I have no reason whatsoever to believe
that this is a valid prior.
But it happens to be that when I have
this prior, and you give me a data
point and I compute the posterior,
that computation is easy.
These are called conjugate priors, where
you don't have to recompute the
posterior for the entire function.
You parameterize the thing, and you find
that all you need to do is change
the parameters when you
get new data points.
So this is completely valid if you are
going to do is this enough that by the
time you arrive, it didn't matter
what you started with.
Then what you are really doing, you
are putting a system in your
computation such that you arrive at
the correct result, and it doesn't
matter what your assumption was.
That's all I'm going to say.
So you can take a full of course on
Bayesian learning, and the techniques
are really wonderful.
I'm not doubting any of that.
Just be careful where to apply them,
because there is an assumption, and the
assumption is stronger than it
seems to the uninitiated.
Let's move to aggregation methods.
So I am talking about aggregation
methods, as I mentioned, because they
are really useful and they are not
that difficult to understand.
So I'll give you the big picture,
and then you can pursue different
algorithms.
So first, what is aggregation?
It's a method that applies
to all models, as we said.
The idea here is that you combine
different solutions.
Let's say that I give a homework problem
to the class that requires you
to develop machine learning--
you develop the machine
learning algorithm.
You get a final hypothesis.
Everyone gets a final hypothesis.
And now I want to get the final
hypothesis of each of you guys and put
them together, and combine
them into a solution.
Hopefully better, because it got
the wisdom of everybody here.
That is the idea.
So what you have, you have
a bunch of hypotheses.
I would have called them g, as
a final hypothesis, because
that's what they are.
They are the outcome
from full training.
So each of them comes from training
on the entire D, with certain
specifications.
But I'm still calling them h. Because
I'm using aggregation, the final
hypothesis will really be
a combination of those guys.
So they remain the h notation,
not the final hypothesis.
The picture that goes with that--
Here is the system that you got.
Here is the system that the guy
next to you got, et cetera.
So I have all of those guys.
Now I want to put them together,
and get one solution.
Very easy concept to have.
So one example is the
example that I gave.
People already solved it, and I want
to combine the solutions.
Another one is interesting, and
is particularly interesting
for computer vision.
In many cases, let's say that
you want detect a face.
Now, this is a very complicated task.
So you could do very simple detections
that are related to being a face.
You can try to detect,
is there an eye?
And you will get it right 51% of
the time, 52% of the time.
Is there a nose?
Are the positions relative
to each other?
Is the lighting consistent?
Whatever. Just put stuff,
and it doesn't have to
have that great meaning.
You can just have simple masks that
look at the picture, and extract
a feature that you think is
related to being a face.
If you take any single feature, and you
try to decide whether this is a face
based on it, you will do horribly.
The error will be huge.
Now, if you put them all together and
think of them as different ways of
looking at it, and then you combine them
correctly, then the decision all
of a sudden is reliable.
This is important in computer vision
because in computer vision, the
computation is a big deal.
You need to do things quickly, because
you are trying to be either real-time
or close to real-time.
So using very simple features, as they're
called in this case, and then
combining them, then that is
a good application for it.
So let's talk about
what is combining.
Well, combining is very simple.
There are many ways of combining.
The most common is that if it's
a regression problem, these are guys
giving you real numbers.
Take an average.
If you are doing classification,
so everybody is deciding yes
or no, take a vote.
Could be weighted average and weighted
vote, but that's basically
the essence of it.
And there are other ways
of combining them.
Now, there are many names
for aggregation.
You can see it as ensemble learning.
Boosting is definitely one of them.
Mixture of experts is another.
There are lots of methods that
belong to that category.
Now, let me make the point that it is
different to do aggregation than to
just do a two-layer learning.
What do I mean by that?
If you have a two-layer model--
so there are a bunch of
features followed by--
you have seen that already,
like a neural network.
Neurons in the hidden layer feeding
into the output, and you
are trying to learn.
The learning is joint.
You learn all of the units at once.
So you look at this--
let me magnify it.
These are your units.
What your learning algorithm does, it takes the
data and simultaneously adjusts all of
these guys, in order to get
the right solution.
This could be backpropagation,
for example.
And in that case, any one of them is
not necessarily trying to replicate
the function.
It's just trying to contribute
positively to the function.
So at the final layer, you could
be taking the difference between
these two units.
And that is the important thing that
affects you in the output.
So the guys here are not trying to get
it right. They are just trying to be
good soldiers and good
features in that.
And the reason you do that because you
are doing it all at once, and you are
trying to minimize the error.
So whatever combination
happens, happens.
So this is what we have done before.
Now, in the case of aggregation,
the units learn independently.
Each one learns as if it
was the only unit.
So you are actually trying to learn
the function, and then
you combine them.
So you look at this picture.
And in this case, the learning algorithm
looks at one at a time.
Maybe it's different learning algorithms,
but at least it considers one at a time,
and then gets you what that is.
And this guy is actually trying
to replicate the function.
And this one is also trying to replicate
the function, et cetera.
And finally, when you have all of
these guys that are trying to
replicate the function, you combine
them and you get the output.
So that is the difference.
Now, there are two types
of aggregation.
And I'm going to call them certain
names for lack of a better word.
But they are really different categories,
and I wanted to emphasize
this point.
One of them I call "after the fact".
What does that mean?
It means that you already
have solutions.
Remember the Netflix guys?
So you have the crowd-sourcing, and
you let the problem out.
Everybody tries hard, and
then gets a solution.
Now you would like to combine
these solutions.
These solutions exist.
They were developed with a view
to performance individually.
Nobody was thinking about
putting them together.
If you are thinking about putting them
together, you may have other
considerations.
For example, you may decide, this
is going to go into a blend, which is
the word that goes with it.
And therefore, I'd better get something
that is different from what the other
guys are having, in order to
be able to contribute.
So there are other considerations.
But in this case, you just get the
solutions, and then you combine them.
So that's one approach.
The other one, which is the
boosting approach, is--
I'm calling it "before the fact" to
contrast-- which is the fact that you
are developing the solutions with
a view to the fact that
they will be blended.
So you get one guy.
And then when you go to the other guy,
you are trying to develop a guy that
will blend well with the
first guy, et cetera.
So you are not trying to get it to
perform well in its own right.
You are trying to make it
a good part of a blend.
And we saw an example of that in one
of the Q&amp;A sessions, which was
a question of Bagging.
Where I give you the data set, and
let's say that I want to give the
class the problem, but I want
to combine at the end.
And they are going to
work independently.
So I want to do something to make sure
that they are fairly independent.
So what I do, I re-sample D, and give
everybody a different sample from D--
a bootstrap sample.
So because of that, I introduce some
independence in the information you
are getting.
So when you get something, I am hoping
then when I put them together, I will
get the benefit of that independence.
So in this case, this is what I am
doing for the case of bagging.
I'm actually giving everyone of
them a different data set.
But it's independent from the other
guys, and then I'm going to combine
what they have.
Now, this leads to the boosting
algorithms, which are very successful
algorithms.
And the idea here is that instead of
leaving the de-correlation to chance,
I'm going to enforce it.
So I am building one hypothesis,
and the next one.
And I am making sure that whatever I
am getting in the new hypothesis is
novel-- was not covered
by the previous guys.
That, obviously, improves my
chances of getting a good mix.
So what you do, you create the
hypotheses sequentially.
So you do one, two, three, four.
And then, given the four that you have
so far, what is the best fifth that I
can add to the mix?
And you make it good by making it
de-correlated with the other guys.
So the picture here is
rather interesting.
It's not quite independent,
but it's not as bad as doing
all of them at once.
What you do--
you have already done those, so
this is a recursive procedure.
Now, you read off from these and
you realize how they perform.
And based on that, you do something such
that the data set you pass onto
the new guy makes it develop something
that is fairly independent from the
previous guys.
And now this is frozen, and
it contributes here.
And then, this guy is trying to be
independent of all the previous guys.
So every time you have one,
you get something new.
Therefore, by the time you put them
in the mix, you get something
interesting.
So this is the idea.
And the way to do the independence
is rather interesting.
Let's say that so far, I have
60% correct and 40% wrong.
That's what I have achieved
using the first few guys.
So when I put them together,
that's what I get.
60% and 40% means that 60% of the
examples I got right, if it's
classification, and 40% I got wrong.
So here is an idea to make the new guy
fairly independent of those guys.
Let's say that I emphasize the
guys that I did badly on.
I give them bigger weights
in the training.
And de-emphasize the guys that I got
right, such that as far as the new
distribution is concerned-- the new
emphasis I have-- it looks that what I
have so far is 50/50.
It's random.
So what I have is not random,
because it deals with the
training set as it is.
But if I give it different weights,
and I ask myself, what is the
weighted error now?
And the weighted error is 50%, it means
that as far as the previous
guys are concerned, it's as
if it's a random guess.
So if I take that distribution and learn
on it and get something better
than 50%, then the new guy I
am getting is adding value
to what I had before.
This is the general principle.
And when you plug in this, you get
a very specific algorithm.
You do this recursively, and you get
not only how you emphasize the
examples given the old ones.
You also derive the different
weights of the mix.
So some of the guys will be successful
in training, and some of them will not
be successful.
And you are going to have weights
according to that.
The most famous algorithm here, which
is a very specific prescription for
how you do the emphasis, and how you do
the weighting, is called adaptive
boosting, AdaBoost.
And it is the one that is used in the
computer vision example that I gave.
And indeed, in that case, what you are
doing, instead of working with just
error trying to make it 50/50, you are
actually working with something
similar to the margin
that we had before.
Remember, when we had support vector
machines, we weren't settling
for getting it right.
We want to get it right with
a margin of safety.
So the AdaBoost algorithm defines
a cost function that has to do with
violation of a margin, and then tries
to improve that margin as you go.
And the weights, both for emphasizing
the examples and for picking the
combination of the hypotheses
you have, are with a view to
maximizing that margin.
And it's a very successful
algorithm in practice.
Now let me,
in the final technical slide,
talk about blending after the fact
because it was applied to Netflix with
great success.
And I want your attention because I'm
going to give you a puzzle.
Last puzzle of the course, I guess.
Here is the deal.
Now, I don't have the benefit of
de-correlation or anything.
I don't have a choice.
I just give the data to people.
They came up with solutions.
And now, we want to put them together.
Think of yourself in the last month
of Netflix, and you want to win.
The other teams are getting together,
and getting good result.
So you look for other guys
that look promising.
They have good solutions.
They already have the solutions.
You are not going to ask them, let's redo
the whole thing with a view to de-correlation.
There is no time.
So what you want to do is, you want to
take their solutions and put them
together, and get the answer.
So you want this and your plan
is, let me do this.
It's a regression problem.
You are trying to get a rating.
And therefore, what I'm going to do, I
am going to combine the solutions that
I have, using some coefficients
from t equals 1 to T.
And now my job is to
pick the alpha's optimally.
The best combination for the solution,
so that I get a good performance.
Now, you can think of this as a very
simple training at a higher level.
Now, you take the solutions as if they
were the inputs and you are trying to
predict the output, which
is the same output.
So what you are going to do, you are
going to have a principled choice of
alpha's, using now not a training set,
not a test set, not a validation set,
but an aggregation set.
So you set aside some points
that were not used in the
development of these guys.
And then you use those just to decide,
what are the best coefficients you
have for these solutions, such that the
error on that aggregation set is the
best possible?
Now if you do this, if you use mean
squared error, what will your
algorithm be for choosing alpha's?
It's the good old pseudo-inverse
again.
You do this and you minimize it.
Now, it's important to realize here
that I really need a clean set.
If I use the training set that these
guys used, then the guy that got the
best training error will have
a big weight.
And obviously, that's a problem
because we know that having
a small training error is
not indicated.
But if these guys are frozen and I take
a fresh set, and then I get the
combination, it's completely valid.
And then I get those guys,
and get the solution.
Now comes an interesting thing.
Let's say that I do this in class,
which I actually did.
There was a time we had the Netflix
data, and people would come
up with solutions with
a view to aggregation.
That's when the competition
was still alive.
So people came up with a solution.
Now I want to combine them.
So, imagine you work on this.
You have your solution.
Your solution is supposed
to predict the rating.
And the other guy is
predicting the rating.
And then I am putting them in.
So you think, maybe the guy that
has a big alpha has a good solution,
because its solution is affecting
the output a lot.
Now, can you imagine what happens
if your alpha is negative?
You worked hard.
You got a solution.
And then when you put that solution
together with the best solutions, the
best possible outcome we can
get is by subtracting your
solution from the total.
That was completely
devastating to people.
But please, don't lose your
self-esteem because of this.
The size of the weights is not the
criterion, or the sign of the weights
is not the criterion for your
solution being valuable.
Because it could be that you are so
correlated with other solutions, that
what the system is trying to do is
trying to combine those in order to
get the signal part right,
and eliminate the noise.
So depending on the noise in your
solution, you could be negative.
You are contributing to that mix.
So although it looks on face value
that negative-- oh my god.
If I did nothing, I would've gotten
a weight 0 and now I have--
no, that's not the case.
So the question is, how do you evaluate
which of those solutions is
the most valuable in the blend?
I had that practical problem, because
I wanted to reward people.
And I don't want people--
when I give this problem,
everybody's trying to do the same
thing, because it gives them
the best performance.
So I would like to reward someone who
did something adventurous, and
therefore got a different angle on it.
And therefore, contributed
to the blend.
Whereas the other guys are all doing the
same thing, everybody will get
a small share so it's not a big deal.
So I wanted to have an objective
criterion for doing that.
What would you do in order
to evaluate that?
By the way, this actually was used in the
competition as well when, eventually
there was one team that decided
to have an open announcement.
Anybody can join.
Give us your solution, and we
will see how useful it is.
And then we'll give you stocks in the
prize according to how much you
contributed.
And actually, that team ended up in
second place, so it's not a bad idea.
So the idea here is that if you really
want to know the value of a particular
hypothesis, here's what you do.
You take it out.
You evaluate all, without
your solution.
You get a performance.
And then evaluate with your solution,
and you get another performance.
The difference is the contribution
of your solution.
So one of the ramifications of that
is that if two people are doing
identically the same thing, then
obviously each of them is useless.
Because when you take it out, the
other guy will hold the day.
But those guys who did something
completely fringy--
I ask you, what is your performance?
Oh, I got 6%.
Towards 10%.
And what is your performance?
I got only 3 and 1/2 %
But then when I look at their
contribution to the final thing, when
I put them together I get a total
performance, let's say, of 8%.
If I take the 3 and 1/2 % out, the
8% drops to 7 and 1/2 %.
So they contributed half a percent.
If I take the guy who had 6% and take it
out, the 8% percent goes to 7.95%.
Who cares?
So this was the way in order to be
able to reward your actual
contribution to a mix.
Now, there will be no Q&amp;A session
today, but I will be happy to answer
questions on the forum.
What I'm going to do now, I am going to
do acknowledgements for people who
contributed to the course, before
I close on a personal note.
The first acknowledgment goes to
my colleagues, Professor Malik
Magdon-Ismail and Professor
Hsuan-Tien Lin.
All I can say is that they are as
responsible for the content of this
course as I am.
Enough said.
Now, I'd like to acknowledge
the course staff.
There are many people who helped.
I am singling out the people
who contributed the most.
Carlos, Ron, Costis, and Doris have
contributed to everything you can
imagine about the course.
From suggestions about the format, even
getting the right slide system,
designing the homework, writing the
registration and online system from
scratch, everything you can imagine.
And they filled in to other tasks when
it was needed, and they ended up
working far more than
they are paid for!
So I'm really grateful to them.
And the head TA, who is Carlos,
happens to be familiar to you.
You heard his voice in every lecture.
He's the voice of the Q&amp;A session.
And I suspect that people are curious
to see what the guy looks like.
They heard his voice.
So let me ask Carlos to come
to the podium and say hello
to the online audience.
[APPLAUSE]
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: So here's Carlos.
CARLOS GONZALEZ: Hi! You know
my voice. Now, you know my face.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: OK, you are exempt
from the Q&amp;A session today.
Fair enough?
Thank you so much.
CARLOS GONZALEZ: It's an honor
to work with Yaser.
It's really great to work with him.
So thank you, Yaser.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Thank you.
Very good.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: OK.
Now, most of the people have seen this
course, and everybody after that will
see this course, through the tapes.
And the medium that resulted in
those tapes are the AMT staff.
Leslie Maxfield being the director.
And I would like to acknowledge
them in very passionate terms.
They have done an enormous job.
It was great amount of work for them.
And they are all here, obviously
with the cameras and that.
And I'm really grateful
to their contribution.
I'm also grateful to the computing
support staff, and Rich in particular.
Not only because of providing the
infrastructure for having this course,
but also for supporting the idea of the
course very early, before we even
raised the money.
So we had a head start on this.
And we started talking to
people and doing that.
And we weren't sure even
that it will happen.
So I appreciate the fact that there was
confidence that this might be
a good idea, in order to put
that to begin with.
Now, this course cost money.
And I was insistent, and Caltech was
insistent, that this will be
perpetuity free for everyone.
That was the whole idea.
We wanted to give a Caltech-quality
course to anybody who has the
discipline to follow such course,
without costing them a penny.
And we succeeded in that.
And in order to succeed in that,
you actually need the money.
If we didn't raise the money, this
would not have happened.
And I'd like to acknowledge the sources
of the money, and the people
who drove the money raising.
The Information Science and Technology
Initiative, the Engineering and
Applied Science Division, and
the Provost's Office.
Mathieu, in particular, took the
lead in raising the money,
in getting the publicity--
He just took an interest in this,
and was incredibly invaluable in
getting this going.
And at the Division, both Ares and Mani
were very helpful and supportive.
And believe me, if you do something that
intensive, you need the support
of everybody.
Otherwise, you lose heart
in the middle.
And that was very instrumental
in getting this going.
And at the Provost's Office, both Ed and
Melany reached for the educational
funds and got the money, so we didn't
have to worry about it.
So it's not only financial support, it's
also moral support and confidence
that this will be something good.
Now, there are many people that I will
have forgotten to acknowledge, so I'm
going to give a general
acknowledgment.
And I apologize for any particular
person that contributed and I forgot
to give them their due reward.
The TA's, other than the ones I
mentioned, have contributed greatly
and they took a load off my agenda by
answering questions to the students,
and taking care of the homework.
And there are many staff members, at
the division level and at the
departmental level, who helped
in all kinds of ways.
The Caltech alumni were
absolutely great.
I got an incredible support from the
Caltech alumni who are genuinely
a family, spread around the world.
And the Alumni Association, that helped get
the word out, was very instrumental in
getting the publicity right.
And I had incredible support from
colleagues all over the world.
I usually don't like my email because
70% is spam and 20% are scams, and
then 10% are relevant.
But it was worth going through all of
this, in order to hear the wonderful
words of support that I'm getting from
the four corners of the world.
Now on a personal note, allow me to
dedicate the course to the best friend
I have ever had.
Well, I learned a lot from her,
and learning is precious.
And my hope is that this course
was a positive learning
experience for everyone.
And in particular, I thank my Caltech
students for really putting up with
the inconvenience of cameras,
regimented lecture format, and
whatnot, in order to share
this learning experience
with the whole world.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]