ANNOUNCER: The following program
is brought to you by Caltech.
YASER ABU-MOSTAFA: Welcome back.
Last time, we introduced the main result
in learning theory, and there
were two parts.
The first part is to get a handle on the
growth function m_H of N, which
characterizes the hypothesis set H. And
the way we got a handle on it is
by introducing the idea of a break
point, and then bounding the growth
function in terms of a formula that
depends on that break point.
There was a simple recursion that
you recall by this figure.
And then we finally found the formula
that upper-bounds the growth function,
given that it has a break point k.
And it's a combinatorial formula that
is fairly easy to understand.
And the most important aspect about it,
as far as the theory is concerned,
is that this is polynomial.
It is bounded above by a polynomial
in N, since k is a constant.
And if you look at this, this is indeed
a polynomial, and the maximum
power you have in this expression
is N to the k minus 1.
So not only is it polynomial, but also
the order of the polynomial depends on
the break point.
We were interested in the growth function,
because it was our way of
characterizing the redundancy that we
need to understand, in order to be able
to switch from the Hoeffding inequality
to the VC inequality.
And the VC inequality will be the case
that handles the learning proper.
And in order to do that, we looked
at the bad events that are
characterized by a small area
according to Hoeffding.
And then we went here, and looked at the
redundancy that results from the
fact that the different hypotheses
have, by and large,
overlapping bad regions.
And the way to characterize this
was through the growth function.
And after an argument that took the
redundancy and related it to the growth
function, and then got rid of a technical
problem with E_out, if you
recall that one, we ended up switching
completely from the Hoeffding
inequality, which is the top one, into
the VC inequality, which is the final
theoretical result in machine learning--
the characterization of
generalization.
And they are very similar except for
a fundamental difference, which is here,
and technical differences, which
are in the constants.
So as you go through the proof, you will
have to change 2's into 4's, and
epsilon into a smaller
epsilon, and whatnot.
But the main thing is that instead of
the number of hypotheses M, we
were able to replace it
by the growth function.
And we had a final technical finesse,
because we took the growth function not
on N points, in spite of the fact that
we have only N points in the sample.
We needed to have 2N in order to have
another sample and carry the argument,
not for the single sample that we have,
but for the difference between
two samples.
And that got rid of the technicality
that we alluded to, which is the role
of E_out that really destroys the
utility of the growth function, because
the growth function depends on
dichotomies, and the E_out depends on
the full hypothesis itself.
So this is where we stand.
In today's lecture, I am going to put
this together in the main notion
of the theory, which is
the VC dimension.
It will not be a new notion for you.
It's very much related
to the break point.
But it is the quantity that you are
going to remember from all of this
after a while.
So you may forget about the recursion.
You may forget about
the growth function.
But you will remember
the VC dimension.
And when you are in a learning
situation, you ask yourself, what is
the VC dimension?
Is it 7 or 10?
And then you say, oh, this guy is
using a hypothesis set with VC
dimension 5000.
He must be crazy. And so on.
So this will be the currency we use out
of the theory, in order to use in
a real learning situation.
The topics for today, first I'm going
to give the definition, this
will be an easy definition.
And I'm going to discuss it a little
bit, to make sure that everybody
understands it.
And then we are going to spend some
time getting the VC dimension of
perceptrons.
We will be able to compute the VC
dimension exactly for perceptrons, in
any-dimensional space.
It doesn't have to be two-dimensional
space, like the one we
did before.
You take any dimension, and we will get
the value of the VC dimension exactly.
This is a rare case.
Because usually, when we get the VC
dimension, we get a bound on the VC
dimension, just out of the practicality
of the situation.
But here, we'll be able
to get it exactly.
And that will help us
going through the
interpretation of the VC dimension.
We'll ask ourselves.
Now we understand it, and we compute
it for a complete case that we are
familiar with.
Then, we would like to understand,
what does it signify?
How do we apply it in practice?
And this will be the subject
of the interpretation.
Finally, I will spend the last few
minutes of the lecture transforming
the theory into a form that is
extremely simple, and it's
very easy to remember.
And this is the one that will survive
with us for the rest of the course, and
we'll be able to relate it
to different theories and
techniques as we go.
So let's start with the definition.
The VC dimension is a quantity that
is defined for a hypothesis set.
You give me hypothesis set, I return
a number which I call the VC dimension.
And the notation for it will be d,
as in dimension, sub VC as in
Vapnik-Chervonenkis.
And it is applied to H. And every
now and then, we will drop the
dependency on H, where it
is clear from the context.
So we don't have to carry
this long notation.
We will just say d_VC,
and we'll understand that
this is the VC dimension.
What is it?
In words, it is the most
points you can shatter.
That is not a foreign notion for us.
So if you can shatter 20 points, and that
is the most you can do, then the
VC dimension is 20.
In terms of the technical quantities we
defined, this will be the largest
value of N such that the growth function
is 2 to the N. So if you go
one above, the 2 to the
N will be broken.
You can think, if VC dimension
is the maximum, next one
must be a break point.
And that is, indeed, the case.
The most important thing to realize is
that we are talking about the most
points you can shatter.
It doesn't guarantee that every N
points-- let's say that the VC
dimension is N. It doesn't say that
every N points can be shattered.
All you need is one set of N points that
can be shattered, in order to say
that you can shatter N points.
That has always been the
case in our analysis.
Let's try to take this definition
and interpret it.
Let's say that I computed
the VC dimension.
I told you the VC dimension
in this case is 15.
Now, what can you say about N which is
at most 15, in terms of the ability to
shatter or not?
You can say that if N is at most 15, the
VC dimension, then H is guaranteed to
be able to shatter N points.
Which N points I haven't said, but there
has to be N points which the
hypothesis set can shatter.
Why is that?
It's simply because, since the VC
dimension is this number, there will
be that many points that
can be shattered.
Well, any subset of them will have
to be shattered as well.
Therefore, a smaller number
will also be shattered.
Which means that if N is smaller,
you can shatter it.
The other direction is
also meaningful.
If N is greater than the VC dimension,
now the statement is strong-- N is
a break point.
You cannot shatter any set
of that many points.
Because by definition, the VC
dimension was the maximum.
And although I called it N here,
we used to call it small k.
So anything above the VC dimension is
a break point, and anything below, you
can shatter.
Very simple notion.
If you look at the growth function in
terms of the VC dimension, when we
had the break points, in terms of this k,
we were able to find the bound that
I showed in the review.
So we know that the growth function is
bounded above by this formula, and k
appears here for the index of summation,
which gives us the maximum
power of this formula.
Now, in terms of the VC dimension, it's
not a big deal because the smallest
break point is 1 above
the VC dimension.
So all you need to do is substitute,
and you will get this formula
involving the VC dimension.
The VC dimension is unique,
because it's the maximum.
So you get that number.
And now you can say that the growth
function, for any hypothesis set that
has VC dimension d_VC, is
bounded above by this.
A nicer formula than this,
because it doesn't have
the annoying 1.
And furthermore, when you look at the
maximum power in this polynomial, the
maximum power happens to be
N to the VC dimension.
So the VC dimension will also serve as
the order of the polynomial, that
bounds the growth function
of a hypothesis set
that has that VC dimension.
All of this is very simple.
Now, let's take examples in order to
get the VC dimension in some cases.
And you have seen this before.
Remember positive rays?
How many points can positive
rays shatter?
Just one point, right?
This is where you can get
all possible patterns.
If you get two, it's a break point.
Remember that argument?
Therefore, VC dimension here is 1.
Good.
How about 2D perceptrons?
How many can we shatter?
We remember that constellation.
If we have three points in that
position, then we can get
all possible patterns.
And 4 is a break point,
so we cannot go up.
Therefore, the VC dimension is 3.
Convex sets.
What is the VC dimension of convex sets
in two dimensions, the example
that we gave before?
We had this funny construction where,
if you choose your points on the
perimeter of a circle, you can
shatter any number of points. Right?
Therefore, what would be the
VC dimension in this case?
It will be infinite.
There is no maximum.
Now, we said before that this one is
particularly pessimistic, which indeed
it is, because this is a very specific
way of getting the points.
And in all of the analysis, you will
find that using the VC dimension
always gives an upper
bound-- worst case.
You cannot violate it, but you
can do better at times.
Here, for example, you can do better if
you choose the points, let's say,
uniformly over a space.
Therefore, some of them will
be internal points.
And therefore, the corresponding growth
function, which can be defined
in this case, will not be 2 to the N,
and you may be able to learn.
Now, let's look at the VC dimension
as it relates to learning.
This is an important viewgraph.
When we talk about learning, we
have to go back to our friend, the
learning diagram.
And in case you forgot it, let
me magnify it a little bit.
There are different components.
And we have studied the matter
so well, that we now can
relate more to this.
Remember, this is the target function,
gives me the examples.
Learning algorithm picks the hypothesis,
puts it as the final one.
We hope that the final hypothesis
approximates this guy.
And we introduced this thing, in order
to get the probabilistic analysis.
We have seen this before.
Now, let's look at this diagram, and
see what the VC dimension says.
The main result is that if the VC
dimension is finite-- that's all you
are asking-- then,
now the green final hypothesis
will generalize.
That we have established
by the theory.
So you don't even need
to know its value.
You just need to know it's finite, and then
you can say the g will generalize.
That we have in the bag.
Now, I'd like to understand the rest
of the diagram, in terms of the VC
dimension. We can understand
the green part.
Here, we'll generalize to
the target function, for
better or for worse.
It could be doing very poorly in the
in-sample, and that will generalize.
Or could be doing great in the
We are only talking about
generalization here.
Now, this statement is independent
of the learning algorithm.
Why is that?
Because the learning algorithm here, if
it picks a hypothesis, it will have
to pick it from the hypothesis set.
We have gone through all of this trouble,
in order to guarantee that
generalization will happen, uniformly,
regardless of which
hypothesis you pick.
Therefore, you can find the craziest
learning algorithm, and it can pick
anything you want, and you still can
make the statement about the final
hypothesis.
So the learning algorithm
doesn't matter, as far as
generalization is concerned.
Let's punish it by graying it out.
Now, it's also independent of
the input distribution.
This is the box.
This was technically introduced
in order to get Hoeffding.
And obviously, it has to survive in
order to get the VC inequality.
The reason I am talking about the
independence here is because of
an interesting point.
We mentioned that when we define the
growth function or the VC dimension, I
give you the budget N and then you
choose the points any way you want,
with a view to maximizing
the dichotomies, right?
So now there is no probability
distribution that can beat you.
I can pick the weirdest probability
distribution that has preferences for
funny points, and your choice
of the points will be fine,
because you chose the points
that maximize.
So whatever the probability
distribution does, you
will be doing more.
And therefore, your bound will hold.
Therefore, we don't have to worry
about probability distributions.
The learning statement, that this guy
will generalize, will hold for any
probability distribution.
So another guy bites the dust.
Now, you look at this and then there
is a third guy which is an obvious
one, which is the target function.
All of this analysis, the target
function didn't matter at all as far
as generalization is concerned.
We are generalizing to it, but
we don't care what it is.
As long as it generates the examples we
learn from, and then we test on it,
that's all we care about.
The generalization statement
will hold.
So it also goes.
So now as far as the VC theory
is concerned, we
really have three blocks.
The first one is the hypothesis.
That is the one that we are claiming
the generalization with respect to.
That's number one.
The hypothesis set is where we
define the VC dimension.
And if you remember very early on, I
told you that the hypothesis set is
a little bit of an artificial notion
to introduce as part of
the learning diagram.
And I said that we are
going to introduce it
because there is no downside.
There is no loss of generality,
which is true.
And there is an upside for the theory.
Now, you can see the upside.
The entire VC theory deals with
the hypothesis set by itself.
That's what's has a VC dimension, and
that's what will tell you, you are able to
generalize.
The rest of the guys that are more
intuitive, that disappeared here, are not
relevant to that theory.
Now, that training examples are left,
because the statement that involves
the VC dimension is a probabilistic
statement.
It says that, with high probability,
you will generalize.
With high probability with
respect to what?
It's with respect to generating
the data.
You may get a very unlucky data set,
for which you are not going to
generalize.
The guarantee is that this happens
with a very small probability.
So this remains here, just because
it is part of the statement.
And this triangle is where
the VC inequality lives.
Now we go into a fun thing of
computing the VC dimension for the
perceptrons.
There are two goals for doing this.
We'll do it exactly.
We'll get exact formula for it.
One thing is to test your
understanding of the definition.
The definition is a little bit tricky
because I give you N. You choose the
points any which way.
You maximize this.
This is a bound, so what is minimum,
what is maximum, and whatnot, may be
a little bit fuzzy.
And trying to get the number for
a particular case will seal the deal.
So that's number one.
Number two is that, because we understand
the perceptron model so
well, we will be able to get the result,
which is the VC dimension of
perceptrons.
And that will give us insight into
what the VC dimension signifies.
And that will set the stage, when we go
to interpreting the VC dimension.
So this is an important part, that will
take a little bit of analysis.
For the two-dimensional perceptron,
we already have done the exercise, and
we got the VC dimension to be 3.
Right?
Now, if you go for the general case and
you have d-dimensional space, you
expect the VC dimension to be more.
Because even if you just go to three
dimensions, the troublesome case
of four points, that we had before, is
very easily shattered in this case.
Just pick the points not on a plane.
And remember the problem with those guys
is that if you want these guys to
be -1 and these guys to be +1,
it was a problem for the plane.
Now, you can very easily separate any
two points from the other two points
and you can shatter four points.
So the VC dimension went up for sure.
And we ask ourselves:
how much did it go up?
Well, it turns out to be
a very simple formula.
The VC dimension of perceptrons
is exactly d plus 1.
Now we need to prove that.
And we are going to prove it in two
stages, very simple stages.
One of them is that we are going to
show that the VC dimension is
at most d plus 1.
Then, we are going to show that the
VC dimension is at least d plus 1.
And that leaves the single possibility
that the VC dimension is d plus 1.
So let's go.
Here is one direction.
And by the way, pay attention because
I am going to give you a quiz in the
middle of the argument, to make sure
that you are paying attention.
This is for real.
And for the online audience as well.
Here is the first direction.
I am going to construct a specific set
of N points, and that N in this case
is d plus 1, because that's the number
of points I want to shatter.
And I am going to construct them
in the d-dimensional Euclidean
space, R to the d.
I am going to construct them with a view
to being able to shatter them.
So I get to choose the points,
which is my privilege.
As long as I can shatter
them, we are OK.
So what are these points?
I am going to construct
them using a matrix.
And you have seen this matrix before.
Remember our old friend
linear regression?
We actually set the input points in
linear regression this way, in order to
get the algorithm, the pseudo-inverse,
and all of that.
And in the case of linear regression,
this was a very tall matrix where this
is one data point, which means that it's
d plus 1 dimensional vector.
The 1 dimension is the constant x_0,
which is the constant +1 we add to
take care of the threshold.
And then the rest of the dimensions,
from 1 to d, are actually the
coordinates of the point.
So we put these.
And this is one data point.
This is the second.
This is the third.
And usually, since we have many, many
more points than dimensions, this is
a tall matrix.
In this case, I am choosing
N to be exactly d plus 1.
And since we already established
that this is d plus 1, this is
actually a square matrix in this case.
But that's all I need for the purpose
that I am after here.
I need to give you the
identity of these guys.
What are these guys?
These guys look like this.
This is no mystery.
See, if you look at the first
column, it's all 1's.
Well, it has to be.
That's dictated.
That is the constant coordinate.
It has to be +1.
If I want a legitimate point in this
representation, the d plus 1
dimensional representation, the
first coordinate has to be 1.
The rest of the guys, I chose the
simplest possible form I can imagine.
You have basically a diagonal matrix
here, and I added all 0's here.
So these are the guys that
are my data set.
Now, you can see that I chose them such
that X is invertible, because
that is the technique I'm going to use
in order to be able to shatter them.
You will see in a moment.
Do I know that this is invertible?
Yes, the determinant is 1, actually.
And that means it's invertible.
Can you compute the determinant?
This is 1.
And then every time you have this guy,
you have the 0 term wiping out
everything.
So I get a 1.
So this is an invertible matrix.
Why am I interested in
an invertible matrix?
Because we can shatter the data set.
This is how we are going to do it.
Look at any set of labels you want.
So this is a dichotomy.
This is the value at the first one, +1
or -1, +1 or -1, and
+1 or -1, on the x points
that I just showed you.
All of these could be any pattern
of +1 or -1's.
I would like to tell you that any
dichotomy you pick from this--
+1, +1, -1, -1, +1, et cetera,
I can find a perceptron
that realizes this dichotomy.
If I do that, then I have showed
you that I can shatter the set.
Let us look for the
w that satisfies--
and what does it satisfy?
It satisfies this condition.
This computes the signal for all the
points at once, in vector form.
You take the sign of that.
And you would like the sign of that to
agree with the particular y you chose.
So you give me y, I am supposed to come
up with w, such that this holds.
If I can do that for every choice of
y you give me, then I am done.
I have shattered your set.
Or, my set, the set I chose.
How am I going to do that?
Oh, it's pretty easy.
What I am going to do, I am going
to do even better than this.
I am going to actually have X w
numerically equal y, even before
taking the sign.
So when you multiply the matrix X by w,
you are going to get specifically
a pattern of +1 or -1's.
Well, if you get +1 or -1, guess
what happens when you take the
sign of that?
You'll get the same thing,
+1 or -1.
So that will satisfy that.
But that is easy to handle, because now
I have algebra working for me.
Remember that X was invertible.
That's pretty easy.
So all you do is just solve for it.
w would be the inverse of X times y.
And you have a solution that realizes
any dichotomy you can think of.
That's wonderful.
So we were able to shatter
d plus 1 points.
Now comes the quiz.
We can shatter these points.
Wonderful.
But we are not really interested
in shattering for its own sake.
We were trying to establish the
value of the VC dimension.
So let's see what we have established.
I showed you particular
d plus 1 points.
I showed you that we can shatter them.
What is the conclusion?
Is it: oh, we have established the
VC dimension is d plus 1?
Thank you.
Or, oh, we only established that it's
greater than or equal to d plus 1?
Wait a minute.
We actually established that it is
less than or equal to d plus 1.
Or maybe we didn't establish anything
at all, as far as the
value of the VC dimension.
I ask you to think about it, and tell
me which of those can we conclude?
And I'd like the online audience to
text a, b, c, or d, as if you are
solving a homework.
And tell me, which of these choices
is a valid conclusion given
what we have argued?
So let's say by shouting.
You just shout a or b or c or d.
And I hope that there is enough
signal that I will be able to
decipher the majority.
Shout.
AUDIENCE: b.
PROFESSOR: OK.
You guys are a tough crowd!
Well, why is that?
We were able to shatter
d plus 1 points.
So we are guaranteed that, for at least
d plus 1 points, we are OK.
It is conceivable that we can
shatter a bigger set.
We haven't argued that yet.
But if we even fail, at least we
have the VC dimension to be at
least d plus 1.
If we shatter a higher set,
it will be even bigger.
If we cannot, it will be equal.
So that is what we have established.
Since you are very good at this,
let's do another quiz.
So I have now greater than
or equal to d plus 1.
Now I need to show that the
VC dimension is less than or
equal to d plus 1.
I wonder what I need to do,
in order to achieve that.
We need to show that--
one of several choices.
Oh, I need to show that there are
some points, a set of d
plus 1 points, that we cannot shatter.
No, no.
I need to show that there
is a set of d plus 2 points
that I cannot shatter.
Oh. No, no.
Maybe we need to show that we cannot
shatter any set of d plus 1 points.
Or, was it d plus 2?
I'm confused now.
What among those guys will
establish the premise?
The premise that we are trying to
establish is that the VC dimension is
at most d plus 1.
Which of these statements
will establish that?
Again, think about it.
And similarly, for the online audience
to text the result.
I'll give you 10 seconds.
And then, we'll also
answer by shouting.
OK, shout.
AUDIENCE: d.
PROFESSOR: I like this.
How about the online audience? d, OK.
So everybody gets the idea.
Now, we know what we want to prove.
Let's go ahead and prove it.
Now it's a question of
any d plus 2 points.
So I don't get to choose the points,
you get to choose them.
So I tell you, choose them please.
And give them to me.
When you give me your points, I am
going to make a statement about the
points you chose.
Well, how can I make a statement?
You chose them any which way.
I'm going to make a statement.
I am going to say that, for those
particular points that you chose,
which I really don't know what they
are, I can say that you have more
points than dimensions.
Why is that?
Each of these guys still comes from
a d plus 1 vector, right?
Because it's a d-dimensional space
plus the added coordinate.
So each one is d plus 1 dimensions.
And I asked you to give me d plus 2.
So obviously, d plus 2 is
bigger than d plus 1.
What do you know when you have
more vectors than dimensions?
Oh, I know that they must
be linearly dependent.
Therefore, we must have that one of
them will be a linear combination from
the rest of the guys.
So you take j, whichever it might be,
and this will be equal to the sum over
the rest of the guys of some
coefficients that I don't know, times
those guys.
This will apply to any set you choose.
And this is the property that I am
actually going to use, in order to
establish what I want.
Furthermore, I can actually
make something about the a_i's.
The a_i's could be anything for
this statement to hold.
But I'm going to claim that not all
of them are zeroes, in this case.
At least some of the a_i's are nonzero.
How do I know that?
This is not part of the
linear dependence.
This is actually because of the
particular form of these guys, where
the first coordinate of all
of these guys is always 1.
So when you look at this and apply it
to the first coordinate, 1 equals--
well, these cannot all be zeroes
because it has to add up to 1.
Therefore, some of the a_i's
will be nonzero.
That's all I need.
I need this to hold.
I need some of the a_i's not to be 0.
Everybody buys that this is the case?
That's all I need.
And then we go and show the dichotomy
that you cannot implement.
We have that, right?
Consider the following dichotomy.
I am going to take the x_i's
corresponding to nonzero a_i's.
Some of the a_i's are
nonzero for sure.
Maybe some of them are zeroes.
I am going to focus only
on the nonzero guys.
I don't care what you do with the
terms that have a_i equals 0.
Do whatever you want.
Give them any +1 or -1.
Let's not look at them.
I'm looking at those guys, and I am
now constructing a dichotomy that I am
going to show you that you cannot
implement using a perceptron.
So for the x_i's with the nonzero a_i,
I am going to give the label, which
happens to be the sign
of that coefficient.
That is a nonzero number.
It's positive or negative.
So I will give it +1 or -1
according to whether
it's positive or negative.
And I will do that for every
nonzero term here.
Everybody sees that?
And now I'm going to complete the
dichotomy, by telling you what will
happen with x_j.
I'm going to require that
x_j goes to -1.
Now, all you need to realize is
that this is a dichotomy.
These are values of +1 or -1
on specific points.
The other guys, which happened to be
0, give them any +1 or -1.
You choose.
And for the final guy which is sitting
here, I am going to it -1.
This is a legitimate dichotomy.
And I'm going to show you that you
cannot implement this particular one.
How is that?
Because I really don't
know your points.
So I must be using just that algebraic
property, in order to find this.
And the idea is very simple.
This is the form we have, x_j happens
to be the linear sum of these guys.
I am going to multiply by any w.
For any w--
the perceptrons, you multiply by w.
That is what makes it a perceptron.
So I'm going to multiply by it.
And then I realize that
w transposed times x_j,
which would actually be the
signal for the last guy,
is actually the sum of the signals
for the different guys, with these
coefficients. That has to happen.
So what is the problem?
The problem is that, when you take this
as your perceptron, then by definition
the label is the sign
of this quantity.
For the guys where a_i is nonzero, we
force this quantity, which is the
value y_i, to be the sign of a_i.
That's what we constructed.
What can you conclude given that the
sign of this fellow is the same as the
sign of this fellow?
It must be that these
guys agree in sign.
They are either both positive,
or both negative, right?
Therefore, I can conclude that
if you multiply them, you
get something positive.
That is for sure.
So now I have a handle on this term.
This forces the sum of these
guys to be greater than 0.
Why is that?
Because this happens for
every nonzero a_i.
For zero a_i's, they don't contribute
anything here.
So if I add up a bunch of positive
numbers and zeroes, I am going to get
a positive number.
What is this quantity?
Do I see it anywhere
else on the slide?
Oh, yeah, I can see it here.
This actually is the signal
on the outstanding point.
So I know that the signal on the
outstanding point is positive.
What does this force the value of the
perceptron, your perceptron, the one
you had here, to be?
It will have to be +1.
Therefore, it's impossible to get that
to be -1, if you chose this.
This is a choice that is legitimate.
It is a dichotomy.
And now if you pick those guys, pick the
rest of the zero-coefficient guys
any way you want, you are forbidden
from having this as -1.
Therefore, you cannot shatter your
set, for any set you choose.
Therefore, you cannot shatter
any set of d plus 2 points.
And I have the result.
So let's put it together.
First, we showed that the VC dimension
is at most d plus 1.
And then we showed that
it's at least d plus 1.
Or actually, did we do it this
way, or the other way around?
That's another quiz.
No, it's not another quiz!
The conclusion is that the VC
dimension is d plus 1.
And now, d-dimensional perceptron--
the VC dimension is d plus 1.
Let's ask ourselves the simple question:
what is exactly d plus 1 in
a d-dimensional perceptron?
It's one above the dimensions.
You can find many interpretations
for it.
But the interpretation of interest to
us will be the fact that this is
actually the number of parameters
in the perceptron model.
What are the parameters in
the perceptron model?
We used to call it the vector w.
Let's spell it out, in order to count.
This happens to be w.
w_0, this is the one for
the threshold, w_1 up to w_d.
These are the parameters you are free
to choose, and that we have been
choosing through this argument.
And how many of them there
are? d plus 1.
Why am I attaching the VC dimension
to the number of parameters?
The VC dimension gives
me the maximum number of
points I can shatter.
So now I can do any which way.
The reason I can do any which way,
because I have a bunch of parameters
that I can set one way or the other,
in order to achieve that.
So it stands to logic that when I have
more parameters, I will have a higher
VC dimension.
And that will be the basic part
of the interpretation that we
are going to go into.
So let's do now the interpretation
of the VC dimension.
Look at this--
we are going to prove two things.
No, not prove, but show two things
in terms of the interpretation.
One of them, we understand
the mathematical
definition of the VC dimension.
What does it signify?
That's number one.
And it will relate to the number
of parameters.
And we'll get it a little
bit more elaborately.
The second one, I know
what it signifies.
Is it at all useful for me?
I am a learning person.
I went through the theory, just because
you asked us to do that.
But when all is said and done, I just
care about the result and how I'm
going to use it in practice.
How can we apply the value of
the VC dimension in practice?
That's number two.
These are the two parts
of the interpretation.
The main idea of understanding what
the VC dimension signifies, is to look
at the degrees of freedom.
What is that?
When you have a model, the model is
characterized by a set of hypotheses.
You get one hypothesis or another, by
setting the set of parameters one way
or another.
So the parameters give you degrees
of freedom, in order to create one
hypothesis or another hypothesis.
So think of this picture.
Think of the parameters as knobs.
So this is w_0, w_1, w_2, et cetera.
When you are actually having
a hypothesis set, you are given this.
And you are able to set the
knobs any way you want.
Increase the volume, decrease
this, et cetera.
Just do this, and you get a setting that
tells you what the hypothesis is.
These are, obviously, degrees of freedom.
And it actually has a pleasant thing.
Because let's say you are buying
a big-time audio system.
Usually, if you are not very much into
stereo and stuff, you want a couple of
knobs, and you'll adjust
them and get it right.
If I give you 17 channels and this and
that, and I give you this panel,
that's great, if you know
how to use it.
If you don't know how to use it--
ah.
What?
I can't.
So now the problem that we are
facing is actually here.
Because now, the specification that
is needed in order to get you to
pick the right hypothesis,
is pretty elaborate.
You need a lot of examples here.
That is the relation
we are going to see.
Now, the parameters happen to be
analog degrees of freedom.
When I talk about w_0, w_0 can
assume a continuous value
from R, and it matters--
if you pick a different threshold, you
will get to a different perceptron.
It will return different values
for parts of the space.
So this is, genuinely, degrees of freedom
that happen to be analog.
The great thing about the VC dimension
is that, it translated those into
binary, if you will, degrees
of freedom.
Because all you are trying
to do is get a dichotomy.
So I am asking myself: when am I
free to get any dichotomy I want?
For any point, I can get the +1
or I can get -1,
independently of the second point. I
get +1 or -1 all the way.
So you can keep adding the points, and
see how far you can get away.
And the maximum you can get
is the VC dimension.
So by the time you get there, you have
that number, which is the VC dimension--
degrees of freedom.
But they are binary degrees
of freedom,
which is what matters here, because
inside the box that tells you it's
a perceptron or a neural network or
something like that, there may be
parameters playing around,
and whatnot.
As far as I am concerned, all
I'm interested in, how
expressive is this model?
How many different things
I can actually get.
So the VC dimension now abstracts
whatever the mathematics that goes
inside, et cetera.
You go outside.
And if I can shatter 20
points, that's good.
If someone else can shatter 30 points,
they have more degrees of freedom to
be able to do that, regardless
of where this came from.
So now, let's look at the usual suspects,
and see if the correspondence
between degrees of freedom
and VC dimension holds.
Who are the usual suspects?
I think this is the last lecture where
we're going to see the positive rays
and the rest of the gang.
So don't despair!
So, positive rays.
What are positive rays?
What is the VC dimension?
That was 1.
I can shatter at most one point.
What were positive rays
in the first place?
Oh, yeah, that was the diagram.
We had this thing, and I present +1
here, and we take -1 here.
And what determines one hypothesis
versus the other within this model is
the choice of 'a'.
Oh, the choice of 'a'?
One parameter, one degree of freedom
corresponds to VC dimension equals 1.
That's nice.
Let's see if this survives.
Positive intervals.
OK, the positive intervals.
The VC dimension was 2.
That is the most I can shatter.
What do they look like?
Oh, in this case.
I have this guy, the small blue guy.
And there is a beginning and an end.
And between them I return +1,
and here I return -1.
So, depending on the choice
of the beginning
and the end, I will get one
hypothesis versus another.
How many parameters, or how
many degrees of freedom?
2.
And what is the VC dimension?
Then by induction, it's true.
No, induction is not true!
This is just to illustrate the idea.
Now, let's go back and
contradict ourselves.
It's not just parameters.
It's really degrees of freedom.
And I'd like to make the distinction.
So let's take an example, where the
parameters are not contributing to
degrees of freedom.
I'll construct an artificial example
just to give you the idea.
In more complicated models, it may be
difficult to argue what is a parameter
that is contributing and what is not,
but at least we are establishing the
principle that a parameter may
not necessarily contribute
a degree of freedom.
And since the VC dimension is a bottom
line-- it looks at what you were able
to achieve,
it will be a more reliable way of
measuring what is the actual degrees
of freedom you have, instead of going
through the analysis of your model.
Let's take one-dimensional
perceptron.
Very simple model.
You have only one variable and
you are going to give it
a weight, that's one parameter.
And then you are going to compare
it with a threshold w_0,
that's the second parameter.
And then you are going to
give me +1 or -1.
So this fellow has two parameters.
Indeed, two degrees of freedom.
And I get the VC dimension to
be 2, because it's d plus 1.
We proved it generally.
And here, d--
the dimensionality of the space, is 1.
This is just a real number.
Now, this is not my model.
Actually, this is only
part of the model.
What I'm going to do, I am going to take
that output, and feed it into
a perceptron.
And then get that output, and
feed it into a perceptron.
And then get that output, and feed
it into yet another perceptron.
And that will give me the
output of the model.
Now, let's see how many
parameters I have.
This guy has 2, one for the weight
here and one for the threshold.
Whatever the output here, gets weighted
by something. That's a third
parameter. Compared to a threshold-- fourth.
Fifth, sixth, seventh, eighth.
I have eight parameters in this model.
Anybody would argue at all about this?
I have eight parameters.
There's no question about it.
Do I get eight degrees of freedom?
No, because these guys are
horribly redundant.
By the time I did this, I am done.
This doesn't add anything.
Take +1 or -1, give it a weight,
compare to a threshold, what
are you going to get?
You are either going to get +1 for
+1, and -1 for -1, or the
vice-versa.
So we are just replicating a function,
and doing it again,
and again, and again.
This whole thing is a very, very
elaborate perceptron in one dimension.
That's all.
I know that I constructed it in
a very funny way, but that's
the function it does.
So if you are counting the number of
parameters, you will say I have
a bunch of parameters.
But if you are resorting to the
VC dimension, you don't
care about this box.
You don't even know it.
It's a black box.
You look at x and y and ask yourself,
how many points can I shatter?
And you get the answer that you will get
for one of these blocks by itself.
The rest of the guys don't matter.
So you can think of now the VC dimension
as measuring the effective
number of parameters, rather than
the raw number of parameters.
And I gave you a case, where the
effective number of parameters is
smaller, which seems to be the case.
Believe it or not, you can construct,
mathematically, a case where you have
one parameter, literal parameter.
A number that is a real
number--
and then you can milk out of it so many
degrees of freedom, that you can
get more than one degree to freedom.
Many more than the degree of freedom,
from one parameter.
But the other case is really--
you construct it because you want to.
But the message here is that, you don't
look at the number of parameters, you
look at the effective number
of parameters.
And effective, for us, is
as far as the result.
And the result is captured by the VC
dimension, so this is our quantity for
measuring the degrees of freedom.
Now, let's look at the number of data
points needed, which a practitioner
would be interested in, and doesn't care
about the rest of the story
that I told you.
So you have a system.
Let's say that you manage a learning
system, and you look at the hypothesis
set, and you say VC dimension is 7.
I want a certain performance.
Could you please tell me how
many examples I need?
First, we know that the most important
theoretical thing is the fact
that there is a VC dimension,
finite one.
It means that you can learn.
That is the biggest achievement that
we have done in theory.
But now we go a little bit closer.
And ask yourself, the value of the VC
dimension, how does it affect the
number of examples you need?
In order to do that, let's
do the following.
We notice that the VC inequality, in
which the VC dimension arose, has two small
quantities-- performance quantities
that we'd like to be small.
Let's remind ourselves.
One of them is this fellow.
You didn't want E_in to
be far from E_out.
So you said that they should be
tracking, within epsilon.
And therefore, the probability that they
are not tracking within epsilon,
the small number, should be small.
The probability is small.
The other quantity is the
other small quantity.
And we are just going to
call it something now.
It's a small quantity, delta.
It's not small because of the
expression, expression is long!
It's small in value.
Hopefully that when you get large N,
this will reduce to a small number.
So we're just going to call
it delta for now.
Try to phase out the details
of this and look at: I
have two quantities.
This is the probability.
This is the approximation.
And we are making a statement that is
probably approximately correct, as we
said before.
These are our two guys.
In a normal situation, what you are
trying to do is that you are trying to
say, I want a particular
epsilon and delta.
I want to be at most 10%
away from E_out.
And I want that statement to
be correct 95% of the time.
That's your starting point.
And then after you said that, you ask
yourself, how many examples do I need?
Fair enough.
When you say I want to be 10% away from
E_out, what you are really saying
is that epsilon is 0.1.
When you say that I want to be
95% sure that the statement is
correct, you are picking delta
to be 5%, or 0.05.
So that's what you do.
You want certain epsilon and delta.
And then you ask yourself, how does
N depend on the VC dimension?
You are competing with someone else.
You are solving the same problem.
The guy gives you the same data.
And you look at it and you say, I
am using a VC dimension and they are
using a VC dimension.
If I achieve this with this VC
dimension, can he also achieve it with
the bigger VC dimension?
Because a bigger VC dimension will
give them more flexibility.
They might be able to
fit the data better.
They will get a better E_in.
So if they can get the same
generalization bound,
they are better off.
So I really am interested
in this question.
I just want to know how they relate.
In order to do this, we are going to
look at this function, which is
a polynomial.
A very simple polynomial,
just one term.
It's not polynomial.
It's monomial I guess.
N to the d.
I'm just writing it as d.
It will play the role of the VC
dimension. I just want the
notation to be simple.
So N to a certain power times e to the
minus N. What is this quantity?
This quantity is a caricature
of this quantity.
There are constants here.
I have here multiple terms.
I'm just taking the biggest of them,
because it's the dominant.
I have a negative exponential, but
it has this terribly damping
coefficients, et cetera.
I am leaving them out.
I am just trying to understand
the behavior of functions
that look like this.
I am taking the simplest case, because
this will give me the tradeoff
between d and N, which is the
tradeoff I want here.
So let's look at it.
This is our quantity.
And what I am going to do, I am
going to plot it for you.
Let's plot it for the case of
d, the power, equals 4.
Here is what it looks like.
Basically, the initial part
is mostly N to the 4.
If there wasn't exponential,
this would be going up and
up and up and up.
The negative exponential is
just warming up here.
And then it starts becoming really,
really effective here.
And then it wins over,
and keeps doing it.
And by then, you will forget
that it was N to the 4.
You will just remember that there
is a negative exponential.
And the interesting part here is,
obviously, this will play the
role of the right-hand side
of the VC inequality.
So this will be a probability.
And we'd like the probability
to be small.
So obviously, the initial part of the
curve is completely meaningless.
You tell the probability--
the probability now is less than 5.
That's very nice.
But it's only interesting once you cross
back to the interesting region,
which is less than 1.
And then you are actually
making a statement.
So this will be the interesting part.
Let's look at the next one.
This is N to the 4.
Let's look at N to the 5, just to
get a feel for these quantities.
Uh!
Well, this one--
it will peak at a different point.
But the main point is, it's huge now.
The probability now is, what?
Less than 20 something.
That's nice.
But eventually, the exponential wins.
That's the good part.
So it goes down, and then it goes here.
You can see that this
is the interesting region.
And I'm going to ask myself, in order
to get to this region, which is the
performance you want,
how many examples, which is this
coordinate, do I need given the
different VC dimensions, which
supposedly is 4 here and 5 here?
Again, this is a caricature, because
this is not the function I have.
If you start adding the real
constants here, this
thing, instead of becoming--
what, 5 examples, 10 examples?
It probably will be 5,000
example, 10,000 example.
It's a pessimistic estimate, because
it's an upper bound.
But the shape will remain the same.
And similarly, if you add the other
probabilities, the probability
will not be 1.
It will be 2, et cetera, but
all you need to do is just shift a little bit,
and you will be getting here.
So if you understand this quantity, you
will be able to translate it to
the other one.
But because it's going up
so fast, I have to do
something to make it visible.
And I'll do that in a second.
So let's now look at it.
You fix the value here
at a small value.
Whatever the value is.
Not 1, maybe 0.5 or 0.1
or 0.01, et cetera.
And you would like to see
how N changes with d.
What I am going to now, I am
going to switch plots on you.
And I am going to have the y-coordinate
here, which is the
probability, drawn on
a logarithmic scale.
The reason I'm doing that is because,
obviously, if I know N equals
4 and N equals 5 get me that, if I get
to N equals 10, that will go upstairs.
So I really want to keep
a handle on it.
So I am going to do this in order
to keep a handle on it.
And more importantly, because
this is really--
you see this very, very thin slice?
That's all I'm interested in.
So I want to magnify
it and look at it.
And this happens to be
less than the value of 1.
So all the negative logarithms will
be here, and I'll be able
to look at it clearly.
So let's go and plot the N equals 5
on a logarithmic scale.
That's what it looks like.
This is exactly--
I can afford to have
more examples because I
will have more curves.
But this is the blue curve
we had before.
It peaks at a certain point
and then goes down.
And 10 to the 0 here, that's
the probability 1.
This is the interesting region.
Below the line here is the
interesting region that, when you tell
me what delta is, you are
telling me a level.
And these levels are not going
to be very much different.
On this scale, this is 1.
This is, what?
This is 10 to the minus 5.
That's a very, very, very
small probability.
So the play here is very small, as
you vary delta significantly.
And the play with epsilon, which will
affect the exponent, is that these
guys will be spread.
Instead of being 20, 40, it will
be 2000, 4000, and so on.
But this will be the shape.
So now, let's add the other curve.
So this is N to the 5.
How about N to the 10.
What does it look like?
Now, it didn't go upstairs.
Well, it went upstairs if you had it
linearly, because now, look at the
value of the top.
This is really serious business.
And you get this one.
Varying the VC dimension,
I am getting a different curve, and
I'm getting the behavior in the
interesting region.
You see the point here.
And I keep adding.
and I will add up to 30.
So these are the curves that I get by
varying the VC dimension, the alleged
VC dimension here.
5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30.
Something very nice is
observable here.
These guys are extremely regular
in their progression.
They are very much linear.
I mean, they are not exactly linear,
but very close to linear.
And indeed, you will find that,
theoretically, the bound in terms of
the number of examples to achieve
a certain level-- let's say you cut
the level here, and you are increasing
the VC dimension.
It basically is proportional
to the VC dimension.
You go from 5 to 10 to
15 to 20, et cetera.
This is the number of
examples you want.
And they are pretty much
proportional to this.
Now, this is in terms of the bound.
The problem with the bound is that,
if I am using a system and the
other guy is using a system,
I have a VC dimension and he has his.
Now, I know that my performance is less
than or equal to something, and
his performance is less than
or equal to something.
And let's say that this
thing is this way.
He has a better bound than mine.
That's the bound.
There is no guarantee that, when we get
the actual quantity that is bounded,
they will also follow that
same monotonicity.
It is conceivable that the two
quantities are this way.
The bounds were this way.
The quantities are this way.
Under those conditions, the bounds
are satisfied, correct?
And the bounds are monotonic in one
direction, and the quantity is
monotonic in the other.
That is a pretty annoying feature.
So what I am going to make now is
a statement that is not a mathematical
statement, but a practical
observation.
That is almost as good as
a mathematical statement.
The practical observation is that, the
actual quantity we are trying to bound
follows the same monotonicity
as the bound.
That is the observation.
You use bigger VC dimension, the
quantities you will get are bigger.
And actually, very close
to proportional.
This is an observation by trying this
N times, where N is very large! That
is the observation I got, and
many other people got.
So in spite of the fact that we cannot
get an absolute value, because this is
just the bound, the relative aspect
of the VC dimension holds.
And therefore, if you have
a bigger VC dimension, you
will need more examples.
And in that case, you can even-- there
are some estimates, practical
estimate, that if you take the ratio of
the VC dimension to the number of
examples, this will give you a handle on
the error. And we will see provable
versions of that, when we get to the
bias-variance tradeoff next time, in
a different theoretical
line of analysis.
So the first lesson is that there is
a proportionality between the VC
dimension and the number of examples
needed, in order to achieve a certain
level of performance.
That is a theoretical observance for
the bound, and a practical observance
for the actual quantity you get.
That's number one.
Number two is that, give us just
a guide-- proportional, not
proportional.
I just want to know, if I have just
a reasonable epsilon and a reasonable
delta, how many example does it
take me to get over this hump?
How many examples does it take me to
get to the comfort zone of the VC
inequality, where I'm actually
making a statement?
So now I have the probability
is less than 1.
Do I take the VC dimension?
Twice the VC dimension?
A hundred times the VC dimension?
This is a practical observation.
And again, it's the practical
observation. Obviously, this depends on
your epsilon and delta.
And this depends on the particular
application.
So the statement I am making is that, for
a huge range of reasonable epsilon
and delta, and for a huge
range of practical
applications, the following
rule of thumb holds.
You have a VC dimension and you are
asking for a number of examples, in
order to get reasonable
generalization.
The rule is, you need 10 times
the VC dimension.
No proof.
It's not a mathematical statement.
And I'm saying greater than or equal,
obviously. Because if you get more, you
will get better performance.
But that will get you in the middle
of the interesting region.
That will get you in the region where
the probability statement is
meaningful, rather than completely
unknown-- what the
generalization will be like.
Now, I'll spend just a couple
of minutes to talk about the
generalization bounds, which is a form
of the theory we have, that will
survive with us.
We are not going to talk about
growth functions anymore.
We are not going to go through this.
We are only going to remember that
the VC dimension is there, and it
determines the number of examples.
And it also corresponds to
the degrees of freedom.
And the form of the theoretical bound
we are going to carry will be the
following form.
I am just rearranging things.
There is absolutely nothing new
introduced here, except simplification.
But it's an important simplification,
because it's surviving with us.
We start with the VC inequality.
We can bid farewell.
This is the last time we'll see it in
this form. It's complex and all,
but we will now simplify it.
So now we have epsilon
and delta again.
And I give them different color.
And the logic we were using is
that, you specify epsilon,
and then I will compute what delta is,
depending on the number of examples.
So you tell me what your tolerance
is, and I'll tell you what
the probability is.
Another way of looking at it
is the other way around.
You tell me what delta is.
You would like to make a statement
with reliability 95%.
Can you tell me what tolerance can
you guarantee, under the 95%?
You start with the delta, and
you go to the epsilon.
That's not very difficult.
There is nothing mysterious
about this.
delta equals that.
Can I solve for epsilon?
If I start with delta, can
I solve for epsilon?
I will get this part, put
it on the other side.
That makes this ready to take
a logarithm of both sides.
So this now goes down.
Now I need to get rid of
the extra constants.
They go on the other side.
But now, there is a logarithm on the other
side, because I took a logarithm here.
And finally, I take a square root.
So that's what you get.
Very straightforward.
Now, I can start with this
fellow and get epsilon.
I'm going to call this formula
capital Omega, which is the notation
that will survive with us.
It's a formula that depends
on several things.
And as you can see, if the growth
function is bigger-- the VC dimension
is bigger, Omega is worse.
That's understood, because the bigger
the VC dimension, the worse the guarantee
on generalization, which is
this approximation thing.
And if I have more examples,
I am in good shape.
Because now, the growth function
is polynomial.
By the time you take the natural
logarithm, this guy becomes
logarithmic.
And logarithmic gets killed by linear,
as much as linear gets killed by
an exponential.
So this is just a one step down,
in the exponential scale, of
the previous statement.
Indeed, if I have more examples, I
will get a smaller value of Omega.
And obviously, if you are more finicky,
if you want the guarantee to be 99%
instead of 95%.
So now delta is 0.01, instead of 0.05.
Well, then epsilon will be looser,
because you are making a statement
that is true for more of the time.
So you will have to accommodate
bigger epsilon.
That's what we have.
So the statement now
is a positive one.
It used to be that we are characterizing
bad events, right?
Now we are going to state
the good event.
The good event happens
most of the time.
It happens with probability greater
than or equal to 1 minus delta.
And that statement is that,
E_in tracks E_out.
They are within this Omega, and Omega
happens to be a function of the number
of examples--
this goes down with it, of
the hypothesis set--
it goes up with its VC dimension,
and of the delta, the probability you
chose to make the statement about.
And this guy will go up
with smaller delta.
I'm just keeping it in this
form, because we don't
worry about this anymore.
We just want to understand this fellow.
So let's look at it.
And that will be called the
generalization bound.
With probability greater than
1 minus delta,
we have this fellow.
So now I'm going to simplify this.
Here's the first simplification.
Instead of the absolute value of E_out
minus E_in, I am going to have just
E_out minus E_in.
Why is that?
Well, because I can.
If I have the absolute value, I
guarantee this one and its opposite.
So among other things, I guarantee this
one, so I can make the statement.
The reason I'm making it is twofold.
First, this is really the
direction that matters.
Because invariably, E_in will
be much smaller than E_out.
At least, smaller than E_out.
Because E_in is the guy you
minimize deliberately.
In terms of a sample, this is E_out.
And there is a sample, so the sample
will have values here.
Now, you start deliberately
pulling this down.
The other guy--
there is an elastic band, but the
elastic band is getting looser and
looser as you make more effort.
But invariably, E_in now has a bias,
which is an optimistic bias.
And therefore, this will be
the quantity that actually
happens to be positive.
Well, that doesn't say that E_out
is always less than E_in.
Once in a blue moon, maybe on your
birthday or something, you will get
E_out that is smaller than E_in.
But the rule in general is the fact,
E_out is bigger than E_in.
So they are less than
or equal to that.
In spite of the fact that they have
all of these dependencies, I am just
going to forget about these
dependencies for the moment.
I know that Omega is
an elaborate quantity.
I don't want to carry the details.
I understand its general behavior,
so I have this fellow.
Now we rearrange this thing.
By the way, this fellow is called the
generalization error, because it's the
difference between what you did
out of sample versus in sample.
So this is a bound on the
generalization error.
And when you rearrange it, you can say
with probability greater than or equal
to 1 minus delta,
and this is the form that
will survive with us.
You just take E_in and put
it on the other side.
Now, this is a generalization bound.
And it is very interesting
to look at it.
It bounds E_out, on the left-hand
side, with E_in plus Omega.
This guy we don't know.
Both of these guys we know, and
have some control over.
This one we are minimizing.
This one is according to the choice
of our hypothesis set.
So it tells us something
about E_out, in terms of
quantities that we control.
Furthermore, it shows that--
remember when we talked
about a tradeoff.
Remember when someone asked: bigger
hypothesis set is good or bad?
It's good for E_in, but bad
for generalization.
Now you can see why.
This guy goes down with
a bigger hypothesis set.
This guy goes up with
Poorer generalization.
Therefore, it's not clear that it's
a good idea to pick a bigger hypothesis
set, or a smaller hypothesis set.
There may be a balance between them that
will make the sum the smallest
possible, and that affects the
quantity I care about.
So this will translate to that.
The other thing is that, now that I got
rid of the absolute value, we'll
be able to take expected values in
certain cases, and compare it with
other stuff.
So this will be a very friendly
quantity to do.
It's so friendly, that we are going to
derive a technique, one of the most
important techniques in machine
learning, based on this.
It's called regularization.
And the idea here is that I
use E_in as a proxy for E_out.
Now, after all of this analysis, I
realize that it's not E_in only that
affects the game.
It's also the choice of this guy.
So maybe, instead of using E_in as
a proxy, I'm going to use E_in plus
something else as a proxy, hoping that
this will be a better reflection that
will get me the E_out I want.
And that will be the subject
of regularization.
We'll stop here and take questions
and answers after a short break.
Let's go for the Q&amp;A.
Are there questions?
MODERATOR: Yeah.
There was one confusion.
Why is the VC dimension
exactly k minus 1?
PROFESSOR: OK.
When we defined the break point, we
defined that, I can call k break
point if I cannot get all dichotomies
on any k points.
That means really, that if I have
a break point, then any bigger point is
also a break point.
And most of the discussion deals
with the smallest break point.
So the notion of a break point
covers a lot of values.
The VC dimension is a unique one, which
happens to be the biggest value just
short of the first break point.
Does this cover it?
MODERATOR: Yeah.
Yeah, because people were wondering if
it was the break point for some set
of N points, or for all sets.
PROFESSOR: It's always the
case that when I say you are able to
shatter, I give you the privilege
of picking the points to shatter.
So I insist that you get all possible
dichotomies, but you get to choose
which points to shatter.
That is always the
logic in those guys.
This does not affect a break
point versus the VC
dimension, or whatever.
This is always the case when we talk
about shattering N points.
It means that you shatter
some set of N points.
Now, the only distinction between
a break point and a VC dimension is that
a break point poses it negatively, and
the VC dimension poses it positively.
Break point is a failure to shatter,
and VC dimension is
an ability to shatter.
And obviously, if you take the maximum
ability to shatter, which will give
you the value of the VC dimension, that
will be one short of the next
guy, which you failed to shatter.
So that is your smallest break point
and the other ones would be other
break points.
MODERATOR: Also, can you repeat
the practical interpretation
of epsilon and delta?
PROFESSOR: epsilon and delta.
So the epsilon and delta as two
quantities, they are the performance
parameters of learning.
There are two things that
I want to make sure of.
I want to make sure that
E_in tracks E_out.
The level of tracking is epsilon.
That's the approximation parameter.
Now, I cannot guarantee that
statement absolutely.
I can only guarantee it in
a probabilistic sense.
But I'd like that probability
to be as high as possible.
So the probability that that statement
doesn't hold is small.
And that happens to be delta, which is
the probability measure. So there are
always these two quantities, and that
is an integral part of this
type of analysis.
I think we have an in-house question.
STUDENT: I wanted to know, what is
the affect of error measure on the
number of points that
you have to choose?
PROFESSOR: OK.
Obviously, as you can see from the VC
analysis, the error measure has always
been a probability of error.
So it was always a binary error.
When you go to other co-domains,
real-valued or multi-valued.
Or you go to other error
measures, you need to
modify these things.
Some variances will come in,
and some other aspects.
So for example, in case of the error
measure, the binary error measure
happens to be bounded.
Therefore, you never worry about the
variance, because there is an upper
bound on the variance.
If you talk about, let's say, mean squared
error, depending on the probability
distribution you put on things,
this could be very big.
So you need first to say that
the variance is finite.
And then, actually the value of the
variance will come into these
inequalities, to go through.
However, the reason I didn't venture
into that is very simple.
There is really nothing
added, conceptually.
And as you can see from the utility
we're using, we are not going to go
back and unravel the mathematics, and
apply it to a practical situation.
We borrowed the following.
We borrowed that: finite, I can learn.
The value is proportional to
the number of examples.
And the rest are rules of thumb.
That's where we stand.
So it's not worth sweating bullets over
the other technicalities, when
this is the message we are getting.
And that message will hold intact
in other situations.
MODERATOR: A question about--
when you're mentioning the bound,
you usually say the VC
dimension is known.
Is it true that for most hypotheses,
this is really known?
PROFESSOR: To get the VC
dimension exactly is an exception, not
the rule, as I mentioned.
So getting it for perceptrons is really
a great achievement, because the
perceptron is a real
model that you use.
And we know the VC dimension, exactly.
When you go to neural networks, we
will get a VC dimension estimate.
We'll say the VC dimension
cannot be above--
for the same reason that we had, when
we talked about parameter versus
effective number of parameters.
Because in a neural network, the
parameters will go from one layer to
another, and there will be some
cancellation or redundancy.
And therefore, you can't really--
keep track of these redundancies
exactly,
or say it cannot be more than the
number of parameters because-- even
taking into consideration.
So in many of the cases, the VC
dimension is estimated as a bound.
But again, we are already in a bound.
Even if you know it exactly, it's not
like we know what the generalization
error will be like.
We know a bound on the
generalization error.
So in this series of logical
development, we get a bound on a bound
on a bound on a bound.
So by the time we are done, the bound
is so loose that, in absolute value,
it's really not indicative at all.
But the good news is that, in relative
value, it maintains
its conceptual meaning.
We can use it as a guide to compare
models, and to get a general number of
examples, notwithstanding the fact that
if you decide to say, I'm going to
go for a perceptron in two dimensions.
And I'm going to want epsilon to
be 0.1 and delta to be 0.05.
Could you please tell me how
many examples I need?
If you actually go and solve the VC
inequality and try to get a bound, the
bound will be ridiculously high.
Much higher than you will actually
need in practice.
But you don't use it as
an absolute indication.
You use it only as
a relative indication.
MODERATOR: Have you come across any
interesting examples, where N has to be
much bigger than 10 times
the VC dimension?
PROFESSOR: The interesting example
is when the customer is very finicky,
and wants a very small
epsilon and delta.
Because the smaller epsilon and delta,
the more number of examples you had.
So the rule of thumb is not to tell
you: use 10 times the VC dimension.
It tells you that you are in the thick
of the game, when you have 10 times--
now we are talking.
There is actually generalization.
There is a certain level.
There is some compromise between
epsilon and delta.
Now you can tighten the screws,
and try to get it better.
This is just a rule of thumb, for
getting into the interesting region of
the VC inequality.
And that has stood the test of time.
MODERATOR: Is there a relation between
this material and the topic of design
of experiments, and the number of
experiments you require to achieve
a certain confidence?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, there
is a relationship.
Some of the experimental
design and whatnot--
there are lots of commonalities
between here.
You have control over certain things
that you may not have here, but some
of the principles definitely
extend to that.
As I mentioned, when we talked about
the premise of learning, it's so
general, that it would not be a surprise
at all that many of the
concepts go and tackle situations that
are not strictly learning, but have the
same theme as learning.
MODERATOR: I think that's it.
There's no more.
PROFESSOR: So we will
see you on Thursday.